<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Sum or a brief collection of holy signes, sacrifices and sacraments, euen since the beginning of the worlde and the true originall of the sacrifice of the masse / translated out of French into Englishe by N. Lynge.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1563</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 233 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 100 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13141</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23433</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S123835</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22581851</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22581851</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25622</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13141)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25622)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1758:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Sum or a brief collection of holy signes, sacrifices and sacraments, euen since the beginning of the worlde and the true originall of the sacrifice of the masse / translated out of French into Englishe by N. Lynge.</title>
                  <author>Ling, Nicholas, fl. 1563.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[192] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Rouland Hall, dvvelling in Gutter Lane, at the signe of the Halfe Egle and the Key,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1563.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: a⁴ A-L⁸ M⁴.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Emmanuel College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sacraments --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mass --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25622:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25622:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SVM OR A BRIEF collection of holy ſignes, ſacrifices and Sacraments, euen ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the worlde.</p>
            <p>And the true originall of the ſacrifice of the Maſſe. Tranſlated out of French into Engliſhe by <hi>N. Lynge.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>MATHEVVE. 15.</bibl>
               <p>Euery plant which my heauenly father hath not planted ſhalbe plucked vp by the rootes.</p>
            </q>
            <figure/>
            <p>PRINTED AT LONDON by Rouland Hall, dvvelling in gutter Lane, at the ſigne of the halfe Egle and the Key.</p>
            <p>1563.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25622:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:25622:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE OF THE Authour to the Reader.</head>
            <p>COnſidering the controuerſies ſtirred vp amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thoſe that cal the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians (ſome ſtriuing to hold the vain ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>perſtitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s deſcended vnto them, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their prediceſſors, ſome alſo inuenting nevve ſects, ſciſmes, and hereſies, and other in number fevver, deſiring vtterly to roote out the darkenes of ignoraunce, that the light of the veritie might ſhine) me thin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth that the moſte daungerous poyſon that Satan vſeth to make men mad vvith all, hath bene dravven out of the myne of the Maſſe, ſtuffed vvith good end, &amp; couered vvith good intention. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though manye haue ſoore trauailed to diſcouer vvith diſcriptions, anatomies, &amp; other vvorks of the Maſſe, this mina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble rocke yet alvvayes more &amp; more to mine, &amp; contermine this fort, vvhich ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth vnminable (after I had read the Elaſſopolitains co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentaries treating of the number, dignitie, povver &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the high biſhops, chief prieſts &amp; ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cers
<pb facs="tcp:25622:3"/>
ſins the creatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the vvorld) I haue dravve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out a brief ſum of the holy ſignes ſacrifices, &amp; ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ordened of god fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time, the corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s crept ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiuely into the church of god, &amp; ſpecially here is deſcribed the true originall of the Maſſe, about the vvhich, preſently men are fallen into ſo great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, &amp; diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. For ſome inuey againſt it as lately forged, other defend it by long poſſeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And by theſe altrications the church of chriſt hath bene merueylouſly threſhen vvith the flail of ſeditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But if thou (faith full reader) vvilt haue pacience of vvhat ſect ſo euer thou be, papiſt, or proteſtant (reading this ſhort diſcourſe, &amp; tariyng til thou haue the bokes of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taries in their integritie) thou ſhalt knovv cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenly vvhat the originall of the maſſe is, partly very ancient &amp; partly nevv, vvho vvere her fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders &amp; patrons: &amp; to thend that thou maiſt beaſſured of the hiſtories faithfully gathered: haue recourſe to the authors coted in the mergent. Our good god inſpire thee vvith his holy ſpirit.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="translator_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:25622:3"/>
            <head>THE TRANSLATOVR to the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter I had read this litle boke ſet forthe (by a certain godly lerned ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) in the French lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, it lyked me ſo well, that partly for the worthynes of the matter, and partly for myne owne exerciſe in that tongue, I applyed my ſelfe to bring the ſame in to our Engliſh ſpeache: mynding nothing leſſe than to haue it prynted, till that I was earneſtly moued thervnto by diuers godly perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, whoſe iuſt requeſt, I could not iuſtly withſtand. The boke doubtles wil ſufficiently commend it ſelf if the enuy of ſuch, as are to much delited with idolatrie and ſuperſtition, do not let &amp; hynder the ſame. The things herein conteyned may ſeeme to ſome ſtraunge, and perhaps are vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowen to the moſt, and therefore at the fyrſt ſyght wyll be merueyled at of many. But thou (good chriſtian reader) peruſing this ſhort diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, and perceyuing that the moſte parts of the maſſe ſacrifice, were inuented by Numa Pompilius the ſecond king of the Romains and a great coniurer, 700 yeres before the incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ieſus Chriſt, ceaſe marueyling and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider that it is no ſtraunge thing, if man (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the ſaying of the Poete) be ſtill ſauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of that whiche he firſte learned, and was brought vp in. The biſhops of Rome (whiche were the greateſt corrupters of the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:25622:4"/>
&amp; true ſeruice of god, with beggerly and ſuperſtitious ceremonies) had long tyme bene noſelled in the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Pompilius. Ys it then ſtraunge, if they (according to the new fangle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of mans brayne, ſcarſe at any time co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented with the ſimplicitie of gods worde) did bring in their wonted ceremonies vſed in their ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices inuented by Numa the coniurer, to adorne and deck (as they thought) the ghoſpel of chriſt ieſus, vnto the which they were lately conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and tourned? In the tyme of the apoſtles, &amp; many yeres after the Maſſe was not hard of, and no ceremonies were vſed, but ſuch, as were com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maunded by our Lord &amp; ſauiour chriſt, as prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word, &amp; miniſtring of the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. &amp;c. But afterward whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> waxed we<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of the heauenly Manna, diligent ſearch was made to find out pleaſant thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs for him to play withal. Then in place of preaching, cam in maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, in place of ſincere miniſtring the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, came in abhominable witchcraft, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iuring, and idolatrie, &amp; in place of the true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noring of god, came in theſe trumperies &amp; tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles of Numa Pompilius: namely, the veſtments, the aulbe, the tunicle, the holy water coniured to dryue away diuels, the aulter, the burnyng of tapers or torches, the trauerſings along the aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with croſſyngs, beckyngs, and bowings, and prayers towarde the Eaſt, the proceſsion and banners, the reliques, and carying of ſhrynes by the prieſts clad in whyte ſurplyces, &amp; theyr crownes ſhauen, the Confiteor to he and ſhe ſaincts, the Orgaines, the canticles, the hymnes, and odes, the cenſor, and the encenſe, the offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie,
<pb facs="tcp:25622:4"/>
the eating of lytle rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d cakes conſecrated in their ſacrifices to their gods, &amp; in thende this pleaſant ſonge, Ite miſſa eſt. Be not theſe abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable additions to the onely ſufficient word of God? Peter was iuſtly reproued for cauſyng the gentilles to obſerue the ceremonies of the Iewes: And ſhal they be commended that cauſe the chriſtians to kepe and obſerue the vayne &amp; ſuperſtitious rites and traditions of the idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours gentills? Cerrainly I thinke, if Paull were preſent to aunſwer them by word he wold af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that which he hathe written: They are worthy to be reproued for as much as they go not ſimply to the truth of the goſpell, but pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing chriſtianite the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues cauſe other (that do ſeldome heare any preaching, or if they doe heare it, doe hardly vnderſtand it) to obſerue &amp; kepe the blynde ceremonies of the infidels, and heathen, wherein the rude and ignoraunt put ſuch confidence (by meanes their ſenſes be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually occupied about the ſame) that chriſt is quit ſhut out, his goſpel not regarded, &amp; his due worſhip in ſpirit &amp; truth vnknowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And if any would obiect that ſome or the moſt part of the ceremonies aboue mencioned, wer firſt among the iewes, and therfore ought or may be retey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by vs: I anſwere, that whatſoeuer was abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by the comming of Ieſus chriſt may not now be obſerued, without deniyng of him.</p>
            <p>Fot in retayning of them, we do ſeame to dout weather he hath fulfylled that which was fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gured and ſhadowed by the ſame. Wherefore ſins the ceremonies of the Iues, and the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious inuentions of the Gentils are by the
<pb facs="tcp:25622:5"/>
ſciptures condemned. Let thoſe that be true chriſtians, vſe ſuch onely as maye be to edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and not to contention, to inſtruction, and not ſuperſtition, to vnitie, and not vanitie, in ſuche ſorte that the faithfull bee not ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of their libertie, and that by neceſsitie they be not compelled vnto thoſe things, from the which they be made free by the goſpel of ieſus Chriſt. I will (faithfull reader) hold thee no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, beſeching thee to geue god hearty thankes for purging the church of England fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo many blinde and dumme ceremonies, &amp; earneſtlye to pray that the reſt (which at this day do moleſt the godly, and miniſter occaſion to the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to ſclaunder the true profeſſors of gods holy ghoſpell with diſcord and diſcention) may be alſo ſhortly rooted out. So that god may be freely worſhipped, the godly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forted, the enemie confounded and his people trewelye taught.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>N. LYNGE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25622:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A ſumme or a briefe collection of holy ſygnes.</hi> Sacrifices and Sacramentes inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of god euen ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the vvorlde. And of the true originall of the Sacrafice of the Maſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N THE TYME</hi> ordayned before of God, by his vnſearchable and vncomprehenſible wyſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome after he had crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted man to hys owne I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage and lyknes to thend that he might ſtirre him vp to feare and obedience, and geue vnto him alſo ſome exerciſe of ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue to acknowledge hys God hys crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, there were ordeyned many ſignes Sacrifices and Sacramentes. Firſt to our firſt father Adam and to hys ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours being bodely men, were orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb facs="tcp:25622:6"/>
corporal ſignes of god, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> better to ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>proue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and make knowen hys obedience. To wit,<note place="margin">Trees of lyfe. Gene. 2.3. Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. Theodor. &amp; Seuer.</note> the trees planted in the midſt of the herber and earthly paradiſe. Theſe trees althoughe they were of no other qualitie than the other plantes, yet they were dedicated and conſecrated of God to ſerue for ſacramentes, (that is to ſaye) for holy ſignes, their qualitie then dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated and hallowed to ſerue as a ſeale, for a witnes atteſtation and approbation of the godly wyll. For the infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of god willing to make knowen, the fellowſhippe, bond, and alliaunce, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted with man his creature, created to hys own likenes, hath from tyme to time ordayned outwarde and corporal ſygnes, which man might ſe and behold with his corporall eyes, to ſerue for aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raunce, gage, and pledge, of the diuyne couenaunt: like as to our firſt &amp; common father were ordayned trees, and corporal fruits, left and geuen vnto him to kepe, without waſting, eating, or conſumyng in payne of euerlaſting death. We muſt
<pb facs="tcp:25622:6"/>
then beleue by faith, that the trees and fruites were not ſignes or ſacramentes of vanitie, as a ſymple pycture, but more that vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>them did hange both life &amp; death they contayning the ſigne and the thing ſignified.<note place="margin">Prouer. 1.2.3.</note> Wherein did conſiſt the know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge and wiſedome to feare god and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey him. This was the cauſe wherefore they were called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruites of knowledge of good and euill, and the trees of lyfe. For in keping theſe fruites hallowed, in obeying god euerlaſting life was promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, contrariwyſe in abuſyng theſe Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes in goyinge againſt the wyll of god, declared by outwarde tokens e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting death and dampnation was gotten.</p>
            <p>For other exerciſes of man toward god,<note place="margin">Sacrifices be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the lawe written.</note> to the ende that he myght reuerence, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and worſhip him, mani and diuers ſacrifices were celebrated, yea before the lawe written by Moyſes.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 50.</note> And although the almyghtye God creatour of heauen &amp; of earth hath no nede of mans workes neyther is nouriſhed with the bloud of
<pb facs="tcp:25622:7"/>
beaſts, or fruites of the earth: Yet he hath alwayes deſyred to drawe man vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to him in feare &amp; outward obedience by Signes, Sacrifices, and Sacramentes: In ſuch ſort that the ſacrifice of the lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes offered by Abell was pleaſyng vnto god.<note place="margin">Gene. 4. Hebreo. 11. Gene. 6.7.9.</note> Noe likewyſe, after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great flouds paſſed, in ſigne of knowledge and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience towarde God did erect an aulter, offered and lifted vp ſacrifice of ſhepe without ſpotte and of byrdes, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he did make ſacrifices ſounde and pleaſing vnto god. By theſe examples it is eaſie to knowe that ſacrifices did not beginne in the tyme of Moyſes: But the innocent and iuſt lambe repreſented by the ſacrifice of Abell (the figure of Ieſus Chriſt) was ſlayne and offered vp from the beginning of the world.<note place="margin">Apoco. 13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>After the rigor of the floud comen for the puniſhement of the offences of the tyrants of the earth, in ſigne of reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation and couenaunt renued,<note place="margin">Raynbowe. Gene. 9.</note> our good god did ordeyne the ſigne of the Bow in heauen, for a gage and aſſuraunce of
<pb facs="tcp:25622:7"/>
the diuine mercifulnes. This ſigne and heauenly Bowe, although before it did apeare in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thick clouds, a token of rain to come: Yet before it had neuer bene a marke dedicated to ſerue man for a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament or holy ſigne, vntill it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned of God a ſigne of the couenaunt contracted with good father Noe and his ofſpring.</p>
            <p>Vnto the faithfull Patriarch Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham another couenaunt and alliaunce was contracted by the wyſedome of God,<note place="margin">Circumciſion in the yere of the world. 2048.</note> which he gaue vnto him for a gage and aſſuraunce of him and of his poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, the outwarde ſigne of circumciſion to ſerue for a ſacrament and perpetuall marke of the diuine wyll. It was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned vnto him to circumciſe his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren males within eyght dayes after theyr byrthe,<note place="margin">Gene. 17.</note> in paine of being reiected from the number of thoſe people, which God had adopted or choſen.</p>
            <p>To the ſame people of Iſrael was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned the ſacrifice of the vnſpotted Lambe, the bloude whereof ſpilt,<note place="margin">Paſcal lambe.</note> ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:25622:8"/>
preſerue the people from the appoynted death in Egipt,<note place="margin">Exodo. 12.</note> the fleſh alſo was ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to be eaten, &amp; in celebrating the feaſt euery yere in the day called Paſque, in ſigne &amp; commemoration of their deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance from Pharaos bondage,<note place="margin">Exodo. 12.</note> with the ſigne of the communion of the fleſhe of the paſcall Lambe, it was ordeyned to eate vnleuened bread ſeuen dayes in payne of death.</p>
            <p>Other holy ſignes were ſent of god to his elect people, alwayes to draw them to his feare &amp; obedience. As the ſigne of the cloud a token of the way to guide the people by day,<note place="margin">Cloude.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Pillor of fyer. Exodo. 13.</note> the flaming &amp; firie piller to conduct them by night out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hands of Pharao y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> tyrant. Moreouer, the ſigne of the diuiſion of the red ſea of Arabie thorow y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> middeſt whereof the elect peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of god did paſſe.<note place="margin">The diuiſion of the red ſea in the yere 2453. 1. Corin. 10. Tite. 3.</note> By the which won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull ſignes god would ſignifie tholy ſacrament of baptiſme, afterward ordey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne of water, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lauer of regeneratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; renuing of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt.</p>
            <p>During the time that the elect people
<pb facs="tcp:25622:8"/>
of god were holden in the wildernes of Arabia,<note place="margin">Manna.</note> to them was miniſtered foode of heauenly bread,<note place="margin">Exodo. 16.</note> wherew<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were nou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſhed .xl. yeres. This holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by the power of god was in ſuch great admiration, that euery of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſayd, <hi>Manhu,</hi> what is this here? they did ſée the heauenly Manna geuen vnto them without trauell,<note place="margin">1 Corin. 10. Iohn. 6.</note> a ſygne of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing bread deſcended from heauen &amp; ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing life to all the faithfull.</p>
            <p>Alſo another merueylous ſigne was ordeyned of god by the rocke flowing of lyuely water in Horeb to quench y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thirſt of thirſty people,<note place="margin">Water of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rocke. Exodo. 17. Num. 20. 1. Corin. 10. Iohn. 19.</note> a ſigne &amp; figure of the true rock Ieſus Chriſt, out of whome did iſſue water &amp; bloode to eſtaunche the thirſt of all ſynners for euermore.</p>
            <p>The ſignes &amp; ſacramentes aforeſayde, were not only ordayned of God,<note place="margin">Diuers ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces ordeyne of god in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> yere of the world. 245</note> but alſo the law of ſacrificers was publyſhed by Moyſes as ſygnes, fygures, and ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes of the Sacrifice performed by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The ſacrifices are either publicke or
<pb facs="tcp:25622:9"/>
perticulers,<note place="margin">Holocauſta.</note> ſome were heue offeryngs, ſacrifices co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſumed with fier:<note place="margin">Diuiſion of ſacrifices dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen out of Exdo. Leuiti. and Num.</note> other were of beaſts ſlayne: and offered vp to eate, ſome were of earthly beaſts, other were beaſtes of the ayre. Amonge the earthly beaſts were ſuch as were moſt obedient as Beaf, and Veale, ſhepe and Lambe, the Goat &amp; the Kidde:<note place="margin">Beaſts for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices.</note> Among y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> birdes alſo the moſt tame, the Pigion and the Turtle. Of ſacrifices ſome were pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lycke, other were particuler, the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke either were dayly,<note place="margin">Dayes appoin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted for ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices.</note> or els ſeuen ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes a daye, or in the new moones, or in tyme of abſtinence, or els in thre feaſtes celebrated in a yere: To witte, in the daies of ſwete bread, when the Paſcall Lambe was offered and eaten without leuened bread,<note place="margin">Exod. 23.</note> in the tyme alſo of har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt of firſt fruites, and in the feaſt of Wyne and Olyues towarde the end of the yere.<note place="margin">Searche the booke of Phi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lo the iew, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſophus.</note> It was commaunded euery day to offer two Lambes, the one in the morning, the other at night after that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aulter was perfumed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> incens &amp; ſwete adours. Alſo ſome of the Sacrifices
<pb facs="tcp:25622:9"/>
were ordeined for corporal things which wer offered w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſheding of blood, other for incorporal things w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out blood. The ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fices called Holocauſtes did co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cern only the honour of God,<note place="margin">Holocauſtes Philo the iew in his treatiſe of beaſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted for ſacrifices. io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus. lib. 3. cap. 10. de an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiqui. iudai.</note> becauſe all the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice was conſumed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fyer, for the which ſacrifice Holocauſtes, the male &amp; not the female was receyued, that is to ſaye, the Beaf, the Lambe, and the Goate of one yere. For the ſacrifice for health, it was indifferent to take male or female, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes three partes of the ſacrifice was reſerued for the prieſt. To witte,<note place="margin">Leui. 1.2.3.4.</note> the fatte, the two kidneyes and the kall or the fatte of the flanckes.<note place="margin">Sacrifice for health.</note> Another diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there is alſo betwixte the ſacrifice for health, and the ſacrifice celebrated for ſynne, for in the one was ordeyned to eate all the ſacrifice in two dayes,<note place="margin">Sacrifice for ſynne.</note> and in the other for ſynne it was enioyned to eate all in one day onlye. By reaſon whereof ſome ſacrifices were called Ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>locauſtes, other for health and other for ſynne. The ſacrifices for ſynne, were diuers aſwell for bycauſe of the perſons
<pb facs="tcp:25622:10"/>
as for the offerings. For he that ſynned by ignoraunce,<note place="margin">Sacrifice for the ſynne of ignoraunce.</note> was clenſed by offering an Ewe or a ſhe goat: but the clenſing of ſynne done wittingly was clenſed with a Ramme. The ſynne of the great prieſt was clenſed by offering of a calfe:<note place="margin">Sacrifice for the ſynne of the high priſt prince, magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate &amp; perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culer perſon. Leuit. 3.4.5.6. Sacrifice for the man po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted. For the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> delyuered Leuit. 12. Sacrifice for the Leprous. Leui. 14.</note> of the prince by offering a goat &amp; a bull, that of the magiſtrate with a goat, that of any particuler, with the offering of a female. The ſacrifice for clenſing of ſinne done againſt god was done with a Ramme. The ſacrifice for a man pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted was with an Ewe or a ſhe goat: for clenſing of a woman after her childbirth was a lambe of one yere, a yonge pygi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on &amp; a turtle. For the clenſing of Lepre, were two birds a liue pure and cleane, cedre wood, &amp; Iſope, two whole lambs &amp; one Ewe of a yere w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> floure &amp; oyle. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſacrifice alſo was made for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon poluted by ſeed ſhed or menſtruous with ij. turtles,<note place="margin">Sacrifice for the poluted menſtruall.</note> and .ij. yong pigio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great ſacrifices did fayle, then dyd thei repare to doues, pigions &amp; turtels, thone for the burnt offering, thother for the food of the
<pb facs="tcp:25622:10"/>
prieſts. And in all ſacrifices there was pure floure w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out leue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſalt, incens &amp; oile.<note place="margin">Leuyn &amp; ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny forbidden in all ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices. A ſacrifice for the woman ſuſpected of adulterye Num. 5.</note> And it was not lawful to offer any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> leuen or hony vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the aulter. Always in the ſacrifice ordeyned for the purging of wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuſpected of adultery, ther was no incens nor oyle as in other ſacrifices, but for her was offered water mixt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> duſt or aſhes gathered on the pauement of the temple. Again there was another ſacrifice celebrated for them which had made the great vowe called Naſerius,<note place="margin">Sacrifice of the Nazereus Num. 6. Philo the Iew in the ttearie aforeſayde.</note> when the tyme of their deuotion was done, it was ordeyned vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to offer iij. ſacrifices, a lambe, an ew &amp; a ramme. One (to wit) the lambe for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> burnt offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d (being the ewe) for the ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uation, &amp; the third for health. Moreouer, the heares of him which made the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice ſhould be caſt into the fier with the burnt offering to be burned.</p>
            <p>I haue thought good to diſcourſe the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſitie of ſacrifices, briefly to thend to make knowen the great goodnes of our god, who by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of ſacrifices publiſhed
<pb facs="tcp:25622:11"/>
by Moyſes, woulde (as with a bridel) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayne the rude people of Iſrael, which could not forget the idolatries of Egipt wherein they had bene noriſhed 400 &amp; 30 yeres vnder the tyranny of Pharao. But what ſtraight lawes, what ceremo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nies &amp; ſacrifices ſo euer were ordeyned for them, euer this people did fal to Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie abuſing the lawe of god, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting the holy ſacramentes and ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, as it ſhalbe declared hereafter. If any man deſire to knowe more of the multitude and diuerſitie of ſacrifices, let hym read the bookes of Philo the Iue, and Ioſephus of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iudaicall anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities, folowyng that which Moyſes hath playnely written in his bookes of Leuitick and Numbers.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The arcke of wytnes. Exd. 25 27.28.</note>Another ſigne &amp; ſacrament inſtituted of god by the arck of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couenaunt deſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bed in Exodus, being a holy ſigne dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to receyue the holy &amp; heauenly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres, to thend to bring the people to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> remembraunce, feare, and obedience of god. To honour and accompanye the
<pb facs="tcp:25622:11"/>
arcke of the couenaunt. Many other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terior ſignes were ordeyned of god, as the ornaments and conſecration of prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, ſpeciallye the ornament called the Ephod,<note place="margin">Ephod.</note> the which &amp; the ſacrifices the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites did abuſe by their idolatries.</p>
            <p>Another holy ſigne there was of the purging &amp; ſprinckling water,<note place="margin">Pourging wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated Num. 19.</note> ordeyned by god to Moyſes &amp; Aaron the high prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſte. This ſprinckled water was conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated with aſhes gathered by a cleane perſon of the ſacrifice offered in Holocau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſta. To witte, of a Cowe all redde with out any ſpot, &amp; which had neuer ben la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured. The Wood ordeyned to make the fyer for the burntofferyng was Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre &amp; Hiſope, Purple w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Crimſin. With this water were ſprinckled poluted per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for the purging &amp; cleanſing of their corporall defylings.</p>
            <p>At the enteryng of the temple or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle was a Lauer made of Braſſe,<note place="margin">Exod. 38.</note> and forged firſt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thimages of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of Iſraell, in this Lauer was put the ſprinckling water, wherew<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificers
<pb facs="tcp:25622:12"/>
are ſpri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kled, before the celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their ſacrifices, to the end they might be purified &amp; obteyne grace &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their ſynnes.</p>
            <p>After the death of the great prieſt Aaron, the people of Iſrael vnthankfull to god for the goodnes ſent them of him, murmuring as anoyed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the heauenly Manna frely geuen vnto them for their norriture, were puniſhed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biting of venemous ſerpents. But the mercifull god gaue vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> an holy ſigne where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thei ſhuld be ſaued &amp; reſtored to helth (to witte) the braſen ſerpent,<note place="margin">Braſen ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 3.7.</note> lifted vp in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ayre a figure of Ieſus Chriſt crucified.</p>
            <p>Theſe were in ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me the moſt part of the ſignes, ſacrifices &amp; ſacramentes or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyned of god in the firſt church of the Iſraelites, figures of the true &amp; perfect ſacrifice performed by Ieſus Chriſt, the true Meſſias &amp; euerlaſting prieſt, ſitting at the right hand of god the father.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sacramentes broken by Adam. Gene. 3.</note>Now reſteth in ſumme to bring forth, how man by his owne proper fault dyd fall in obliuion and diſobedience of god
<pb facs="tcp:25622:12"/>
his creator, abuſing gods fauour, and corrupting the holy ſignes, ſacrifices, and ſacramentes, ordeyned to hym.</p>
            <p>What perſuaded our firſt father and his companion to hyde them ſelues at the hearing of gods voyce, but becauſe they had abuſed the holy ſigne, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the lawe of the fruites to them for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden? This holy ſigne which our firſt and vniuerſall father had abuſed, was the originall of other vices &amp; corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons hereafter deſcribed, into the which all men are fallen ſauoring of the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted lumpe of Adam.</p>
            <p>Leauing the perticuler corruptions of the ſignes, ſacrifices and ſacramentes,<note place="margin">Corruption of the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce by Aaron. Exod. 32. Deute. 9.</note> before the law written by Moyſes, we wil begin to bring forth briefly the moſt notable errours committed by the moſt great ſacrificers, as kinges, prieſts, and others hauing the chief gouernment of the people.</p>
            <p>When Moyſes was abiding in mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Synay to receiue the commaundemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes of God, his brother Aaron the high
<pb facs="tcp:25622:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:13"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:14"/>
prieſt forged a calfe of gold, of the golden earings geuen vnto him by the people of Iſraell, he buylded an aulter offered incens, and celebrated ſacrifice, cauſing the common people to worſhyppe the molten Image.</p>
            <p>Was not this an abuſing of the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ordeyned of god, &amp; a corrupting of the true vſage of the ſame, in cauſing the Calfe to be worſhipped in place of the ſlaine &amp; offered ſacrifice, as it was appoynted in the lawe?<note place="margin">Corruption of the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce by Nadab and Abiu. Leui. 10. Num. 11.</note> His ſonnes alſo Nadab &amp; Abiu were not they conſumed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fyer, for abuſing the vſe of ſacrifices in takyng vnhallowed Wood &amp; corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the lawe? The people of Iſrael vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankfull for the goodnes done vnto them in being delyuered from the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roanicall captiuitie, did they not mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour againſt the holy ſacrament of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly Manna, when they did diſdeyne and contempne this bread of lyfe, &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded fleſhe to eate?<note place="margin">ioſua. 7.</note> Acham the ſonne of Charmes did not he violate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> laws of holy ſygnes, when he commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:25622:14"/>
ſacrilege, and kept backe the ſpoyles of Hierico vowed &amp; conſecrated to god for ſacrifices? If any more curiouſly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyre to ſée the continuall abuſes &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of the people them ſelues, let hym read the hiſtories of the Iudges of Iſraell,<note place="margin">iud. 2.3.6, 8.9.</note> &amp; in all times he ſhal fynd man neuer to be content with the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping ordained of God. But in ſtead of outwarde ſignes ordayned of god to drawe the people to feare &amp; obedience, they haue forged inuentions. And in place of reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſing the aulters, &amp; arke of couenaunt in the name of the onely god beyng (outwarde ſacred ſignes):<note place="margin">Iudg. 10.</note> The Iſrelites infected with the Idolatries of their neighbours, the Sirians, Sido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Moabites, Ammonites &amp; Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines, did erect alters vnto their ſtrang gods, Baall and Aſtaroth. Iephtha, iudge &amp; captaine of the Iſralites: did not he corrupt the law of ſacrifices when he ſacrificed his owne proper daughter? ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing himſelfe by a vowe, whyche he made, which was not appointed to him
<pb facs="tcp:25622:15"/>
of god?<note place="margin">The vngentle ſacrifice of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phtha. iud. 11.</note> The holy ſigne ordayned of god for the hygh prieſt to celebrat ſacrifices in (called Ephod) the vppermoſt gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,<note place="margin">iudg. 8.9. idolatrye by the golden EPhod. Iudg. 17.18.</note> was not it abuſed by Gedeon cap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne of the Iſralites whan as of the ſpoiles of the Madianites &amp; of their ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings he made an Ephod of gold, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the people fell into great idolatrye? How long time was this holy outward ſigne Ephod abuſed, an ymage beyng erected by the mother of Michas in Silo, prieſtes &amp; ſacrificers appointed expreſſly to ſacrifice therevnto, an alter buylded and the true vſe of ſacrifices corrupted? So longe as the temple contynued in Silo, into what wicked maners dyd the prieſtes and ſacrificers fall, which were ordained of god for the miniſtery of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices &amp; holy ſacramentes, when they vſurped by long poſſeſſion to haue thys priuilege of the people, that when they did ſacrifice, and the fleſhe of thoffered ſacrifice was ſeathing,<note place="margin">1. Samuel. 2.</note> their boye or ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt hauing a three grained fleſhoke of yron in his hand, had liberty to catche
<pb facs="tcp:25622:15"/>
out of the potte or cawdron, all that he cold carry with his hoke? further the le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiticall tirranny was ſuch, that this ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant of the prieſt had liberty to demand of the ſacrifice geuer, fleſhe to roſte for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrificer, otherwiſe to take it by force euen as he wold. Was not this a great abuſe &amp; deteſtable corruption practiſed by the prieſtes &amp; chiefe ſacrificers, vnder the pretence of ſacrifices? What grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can be declared, than that of the ſonnes of the chiefe prieſt Ely, called Ophni &amp; Phinees?<note place="margin">Ophni, Phini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, corruptera of the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. 1. Samuel. 4.</note> Who vnder pretence of deuotion committed ſhame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full whoredom with the couered weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> behinde the holy Tabernacle inſtituted of god, for the whiche wickednes they were miſerably ſlayne, and the arke of couenaunt taken awaye by the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines.<note place="margin">1. Samuel. 5.6.</note> Which they ſet in the temple of their god dagon,<note place="margin">The arcke of the holy co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenaunt.</note> but god not ſuffringe this holye ſigne thus to be prophaned, threwe downe the image dagon &amp; ſent greuous punſhiments to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Philiſtines in ſuch ſort that they were conſtrayned
<pb facs="tcp:25622:16"/>
to reſtore the Arke of the couenaunt of god, This holye ſigne was ſo precious that for as muche as the Bethſamites (which were not of the order of the Leui<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes) had abuſed it 50000. of the common people, and 70. of the chiefe rulers were rooted out &amp; ſlayne by the vengeaunce of god.<note place="margin">Againſt cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption of holy ſignes.</note> This example mighte make all thoſe to tremble whyche enterpryſe to abuſe the holy ſygnes and ſacramentes ordayned of god.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Samuel. 6. Oſa.</note>Oſa alſo for that he abuſed the ſame ſacred ſygne (notwithſtandinge that he did it of a good intention) for to lift vp the Arke of witnes hanging to much on thonſide) was he not puniſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> death? Of others abuſes committed by the Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralites,<note place="margin">Oſias. 2. Chron 26.</note> there is many examples, Oſias was puniſhed with liproſie for abuſing the ſacrifices,<note place="margin">Saule. 1. Samuel. 13. Ioſeph. lib. 7. cap. 4. of the Iewes anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</note> in takyng vpon hym the miniſtery of encenſing appointed to the prieſtes onely. Saule he firſt elected king of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſralits was ſlaine &amp; his king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome geuen vnto another (as was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared before of Samuell) for abuſyng
<pb facs="tcp:25622:16"/>
the ſacrifices, and ſuffering his people to commit the lyke abuſes. His ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours in the kingdomes of Iuda &amp; Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell haue not they alwayes continued in abuſing &amp; corrupting the ſacrifices &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments ordeyned of God, when they did offer ſacrifices to the gods,<note place="margin">1. Kyngs. 8.11.</note> Aſtaroth of the Sidonions, to Chanios of the Mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>abites, &amp; to Melcom or Moloch of the Ammonites, in ſo much that they buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded temples &amp; oratories, euen to offer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>encens &amp; to do ſacrifices vnto them.</p>
            <p>Hieroboam king of the Iſraelites,<note place="margin">Hieroboam, 1. Kyngs. 12.</note> did not onely cauſe a Golden calfe to be erected, as the high prieſt Aaron had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed before, but alſo did ordeyne two Golden Kyne in the two Temples of Bethell &amp; Dan, and ordeyned ſtraunge prieſts corrupting the lawe of God, and cauſing them to do ſacrifice after the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of Aaron.<note place="margin">1. Kyngs. 14.</note> This idolatrie &amp; corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſacrifices did continue amonge the Iſraelites more than .400. yeres du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the raigne of their kyngs, who had taught them to corrupt the true vſe of
<pb facs="tcp:25622:17"/>
the ſacrifices in chapels &amp; perticuler ora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tories buylded in the tops of hils &amp; thick foreſts conſecrated, inviolating the law of ſacrifices ordeyned by God in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly temple,<note place="margin">1. Kyngs. 15.</note> within the holy citie. For par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ticuler examples, of the abuſes commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted agaynſt the trew vſe of ſacrifices, the hiſtorie of Maacha mother of kyng Aſa is manifeſt, who erected an image of the god Pan, &amp; did conſecrate &amp; dedicate vnto him a thicke foreſt offeryng ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices vnto it.<note place="margin">Achab. 1. Kyngs. 16.</note> Achab another kyng of the Iſraelites did erecte an aulter &amp; made ſacrifices to the God Mars, otherwyſe called Baal, vnto whom he dedicated a Groue to ſatiſfie hys wycked wyfe Ieſabell.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ioſeph. lib. 8. chap. 10.</note>He cauſed alſo another aulter &amp; tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to be erected to the God of the Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, he ordeyned Prieſts, Sacrificers, and inſtituted foure hundred falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes. Hys ſonne &amp; ſucceſſour Ocho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias taught of his father to corrupt the vſe of the ſacrifices,<note place="margin">Ochoſias.</note> dyd not onely offer to Baal (otherwyſe called Mars) but
<pb facs="tcp:25622:17"/>
went forwarde in greater abuſe,<note place="margin">2. Kyngs. 1. Ioſeph. lib. 9. chap. 1.</note> he buylded a temple vnto the god of Acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronites called by Ioſephus <hi>Myos</hi> and by the Gréekes <hi>Priapus,</hi> vnto the which god he did ſacrifice.</p>
            <p>To be ſhort, what more abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble corruption can be deſcribed,<note place="margin">Purgatorye.</note> than the inuention of the fyer Purgatorie?<note place="margin">2. Kyngs. 16. 2. Kings. 16.23 in the booke Alcoran. Aſoar. 29.46. Aſoar. 5.</note> wher with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites did tranſgres cauſing their children to paſſe through the fier in Tophet, a valley of the ſons of Ennon, ſacrificing vnto the God Moloch. This corruption of ſacrifices, not withſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that it was in the tyme of Moyſes,<note place="margin">igne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nae non niſi nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero dierum preterminato animas ſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re docet Aco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rani liber, &amp; ad diem veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis omnes accedere ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſuorum mercedem accepturas Aſoar.</note> yet the Idoll Moloch in the valley of Ennon, was not caſte downe tyll the raygne of good Kyng Ioſias, more then nyne hundred yeres after Moyſes. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertheleſſe this abuſe doth continue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Arabians &amp; Affricans to this preſent, ſo that the Alcoramiſts &amp; Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hometiſts haue this beliefe, that the ſoules of the departed muſte paſſe tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe the fyer to be purged and purified from theyr offences.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:18"/>By this briefe gathering a man may clearely perceyue that from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world, man by his own fault hath fallen into the bottome of errour &amp; corruption of holy ſignes, ſacrifices &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, ordened to him of god. But y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> principall abuſe,<note place="margin">Cauſe of the corruption of ſacraments.</note> whereof is ſprong the originall of all idolatrie entred by this meanes, that fleſhly and carnal men did ſtick more to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> viſible ſignes &amp; outward ceremonies, then to the things ſignified by the Sacraments:<note place="margin">Apo. 13.</note> for in place of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſing their harts, &amp; cutting awaye the old ſkinne of ſynne, to be regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and purified by the bloud of the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſacrifice offered before all worlds,<note place="margin">Deut. 10.30.</note> they haue taken circumciſion carnally for the cutting of the carnall ſkynne. Wherefore did they not folowe the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of god, by Moyſes to cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſe the foreſkynne of their hearts? Wherefore did not the children of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell geue credit to the good prophet Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remie,<note place="margin">Ierem. 4.</note> whiche admoniſhed them of the ſpirituall circumciſion, &amp; to circumciſe
<pb facs="tcp:25622:18"/>
the foreſkynne of their hearts, in put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinge awaye the foreſkynne of their naturall corruption. The lyke is come to paſſe of the ſacrifices &amp; holye ſygnes ordeyned of god, for figures of the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice fulfilled by Ieſus Chriſt: For the carnall man reſteth in the corporall bloud of earthly beaſts, where he ought to lyft vp his ſpirite to heauen to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend &amp; conceyue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is figured &amp; ſignified by the ſacrifices of beaſts of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered vp. For this therefore the iuſtice of God is declared by the Prophetes. What nede haue I (ſayth the Lord god) of your ſacrifices?<note place="margin">Eſay. 1.</note> I am werye of your offerings of ſhepe. Moreouer, I take no pleaſure in the blood of beaſts, lambes, &amp; goates offered. Wherefore trauell you to addreſſe aulters vnto me, I wyll non of your offerynges &amp; vayne ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, I abhorre your incens, I can not ſuffer your newe Moones, your Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bothes your aſſembles, &amp; your feaſts: all is but vanitie. I hate your feaſts of new Moones (O Iſraelites) &amp; your ſolemne
<pb facs="tcp:25622:19"/>
feaſts. I am wery in ſuffering ſo much. You haue goodly directed your prayers vnto me, I wil not heare you any more, for the abuſes which you haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted with your handes embrued with bloud. Moreouer I wil not receiue of the houſe of Iſraell any bull,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 51. Eſay. 66. Ierem. 6.</note> becauſe your ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces are not pleaſing vnto me. I am as well pleaſed with thoffring of a beaſt as with the murderyng of a man,<note place="margin">Eccle. 7.</note> &amp; with the offering of Incens, as with the wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipping of an Idoll. Wherefore then (ſayth god) do ye take ſo much paynes to ſeeke Incens vnto Sabba, &amp; odours from far countreys, to offer &amp; make ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices vnto me wherein I delyte not? Who hath moued you (O Iſraelites) to erect images vnto the Gods Moloch, and the ſterre Rompham duryng the tyme that you were in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, where I dyd nouryſhe you wyth my heauenlye Manna? Your feaſtes be odious vnto me, your offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rynges,<note place="margin">Amos. 5.</note> oblations, &amp; ſacrifices for the healthe, I wyll reiect, your offeryngs
<pb facs="tcp:25622:19"/>
do diſpleaſe me.<note place="margin">Mich. 6.</note> After what maner ſhoulde one prepare him ſelfe to god? Shall it be by ſacrifices of Bullocks of one yere? Doth God take pleaſure in a great number of ſhepe offered vnto him? Or in a great quantitie of holye oyles? To him ſayth the Prophet ſhall I offer of the firſt borne, for the remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ſynnes.</p>
            <p>Our good God hath verye clearelye declared that ſeruyce whiche he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth, followe equitie, loue,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 51.</note> mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye, and of an humble and contrite hearte, fall downe before hym, for obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience is more worthe then ſacrifice, or the fatte of offered Rammes.<note place="margin">1. Samuel. 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>What gaue an occaſion to God to put awaye thoſe ſacrifices and ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes whyche he hym ſelfe had ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but the abuſe and corruption whyche the Iſraelites had commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, takynge ouer groſſelye the Signes and Ceremonies, ordeyned to drawe them to feare and obedience?</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:20"/>For in place of conceyuing that whiche was figured by the ſignes &amp; corporall ſacrifices they did reſt in the fleſhe of the beaſts offered. And in ſtead of cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting away the foreſkynne of theyr hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, they reſted in the carnall circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, &amp; in the meane tyme tourned away from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true worſhipping of god, addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing them ſelues to creatures. As to ſtarres, to the queene of heauen, &amp; other ſtraunge Gods, offeringe to them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens, buyldyng for them temples, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring for them prieſts, chaplaynes &amp; ſacrificers to offer vnto them oblations and ſacrifices.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, to accompliſhe this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, they did ſacrifice with the blood of innocents, offering of them, &amp; cauſing them to paſſe thorowe the fyer of pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie in the valley of Tophet. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (for the abuſe committed by the chil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell againſt the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,<note place="margin">4. Eſdr. 1.</note> ſacred ſignes &amp; ſacrifices ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God) it was ſayde vnto them by the prophetes, that god woulde no more
<pb facs="tcp:25622:20"/>
of their feaſts, of their newe Moones, of their circumciſion,<note place="margin">4. Eſdr. 1.</note> nor of their ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces celebrated by people idolatrous and full of blood.</p>
            <p>When the vnſerchable wiſedome of god did perceyue the hardneſſe &amp; infide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie of the people of Iſraell, which did euer continue to commit idolatrie, by corrupting the holy ſignes, ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; ſacrifices, in place of acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging the infinite goodnes of god, which had delyuered them from the Pharaoni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>call tyrranny, whiche had nouriſhed them in the Wilderneſſe, whiche had brought them into the fruitfull lande promiſed vnto them. And which ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny tymes had ſuccoured them in the warres againſt their neighbours, the Cananites, Moabites, Madianites, Philiſtines, Ammonites, Sirians, Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donians, Sicyonians, &amp; other enuious people: Neuertheleſſe this rude people did continue in their idolatries taught them by their prieſts, ſacrificers, kings, &amp; princes, without tourning to the trew
<pb facs="tcp:25622:21"/>
worſhipping of one onely God.</p>
            <p>Wherefore after the great mercye and longe tarying of the iuſte Iudge, whiche by all maner corrections would haue brought agayne his people by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine vengeaunce particulerly, as by reaſyng vp of warres, by captiuitie and bondage, by diuidyng of the kyngdome parted betwene Roboam and Hiero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam, the ſucceſſours of Salamon plounged in the depth of Idolatrye, by inwarde warres amonge the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple diuided, and by other ſcourges ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to correcte thoſe whome God doth fauour, to the ende to bryng them to hys feare and obedience. In the end thys people, to muche hardened, and waxed olde in theyr Idolatries, were taken into miſerable bondage, vnder the tyrannye of Infidels Aſſirians,<note place="margin">4. King 15 24</note> and Idolatrous Babilonians, theyr real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes quyte ouerthrowen.</p>
            <p>But wythin a lytle whyle after, that, thys ſelfe ſame people, by the great mercye of God was delyuered from
<pb facs="tcp:25622:21"/>
the handes of vnfaythfull tyrauntes, was ſet agayne at lybertye, and was reſtored to theyr lande of promyſe: they fell agayne to theyr Idolatries more then euer before,<note place="margin">Ioſephus lib. 13. cap. 18. of the Iewes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities.</note> vnder the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of theyr Sacrificers &amp; hygh Prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes, whiche ioyned the temporaltye &amp; the ſpiritualtie ſo together, that they were clad wyth Scepter Royall and Crowne. Then ſucceded the hereſyes of the Phariſeis, of the Saduces, Eſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, Gallileens, Maſbutheens,<note place="margin">Ioſephus in the boke of the antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the iewes.</note> Heme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robaptiſts &amp; Samaritans, corrupted by the diuerſitie of ſtraunge nations, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che had inhabited &amp; ſubdued the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey of Samaria neare vnto Iudea. For the Babilonians did worſhyp for theyr god Soccobenoth, the Cutheens &amp; Perſians hauing for theyr God Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal or Mergel, the Hematenſes called vppon theyr god Aſima, the Ananoys dyd worſhyppe theyr god Nebahaze &amp; Thartace, the Sepharuainenſes dyd holde vppon theyr gods Adramelech and Anamelech.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:25622:22"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:25622:22"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:23"/>Vnto the whiche gods they ſacrificed their children, cauſyng them to paſſe thorowe the fyer.</p>
            <p>Thus then, when all kynde of idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie was ſpred among the Iſraelites, the ſacrifices were altogether corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the prieſts became byers &amp; ſellers couetous, tyrants &amp; Idolaters, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple payed tribute to the tyrantes of Rome, theyr countrey of Iudea made one with the Prouince ioyning vnto Siria vnder the power of the Romains.<note place="margin">Ioſephus lib. 15. cap. 3. Ioſephus lib. 18. cap. 3. Eurrop. lib. 1. cap. 12.</note> The order alſo, the law &amp; election of the high prieſts was corrupted, &amp; their dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie abaſtarded altogether, in ſo much that without regard of the Leuiticall race, the high prieſts were appoynted by Conſulls or Lieutenants of Rome as pleaſed them.<note place="margin">Geneſ. 49.</note> And where as before they continued during their lyues, now they chaunged yerely. And when as the Scepter was taken from the ſtocke of Iuda, &amp; her kyngdome quyte ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen, as before it was prophecied: The incomprehenſible greatnes of God did
<pb facs="tcp:25622:23"/>
manifeſt it ſelfe by his ſonne begotten before all worlds, which did ſo humble himſelfe, that he tooke humaine fleſhe of the Virgins wombe to redeme his people, and reſtore them to grace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God.</p>
            <p>For as in Adam by his breaking and abuſing of the holy ſigne geuen vnto hym to keepe,<note place="margin">A conferryng of Adam with Ieſus chriſt.</note> all the lumpe of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde was corrupted with the leuaine of ſynne: Euen ſo by the ſeconde Adam Ieſus Chriſt we are by grace purged from our offences. To our firſt &amp; vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall father Adam was geuen a holy ſigne to exerciſe his obedience, and to his ſucceſſors was geuen other holy ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes, ſacrifices &amp; ſacraments inſtituted of God, as the tree of lyfe, the fruits of the tree of knowledge of good &amp; euyll, the rainebowe, circumciſion, the lambe without blemiſhe, the bread without leuain, the cloud, the fyrypillour, the red ſea deuided, the heauenly Manna, the water of the rocke, the immolation and offering of beaſts for ſacrifices, the arck
<pb facs="tcp:25622:24"/>
of couaunt, the Braſen ſerpent, the pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ging water, the temple buylded in the middeſt of the holy citie: All which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred ſignes, ſacrifices &amp; ſacraments, wer figures of that whiche was accompli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Ieſus chriſt the tree of lyfe. Apoca. 2. Rom. 11.</note>For firſt he was the trew tree of lyfe planted in the myddeſt of the garden of God, in whome &amp; by whome we which were baſtarde trées are grafted and ſet, to the obteyning of eternal lyfe: he hath geuen vs the keepyng of the fruites of the tree of wiſedome by his holy ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and commaunded vs to keepe it whole without abuſing, without cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting, without adding or dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhyng, in payne of eternall death.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rainebowe.</note>He hath bene as the celeſtial Bow ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the aire to aſſure vs of the bande and couenaunt contracted betwene god and vs that we ſhuld be no more drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the floud of ſynne. He was circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed to accompliſh the law in himſelfe,<note place="margin">Circumciſion Gala. 4.</note> that he might cut away the foreſkynne of our harts, to ſpoyle vs of our old cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted
<pb facs="tcp:25622:24"/>
ſkinne in Adam.<note place="margin">The burning buſhe.</note> He was the flame in the burning buſh, taking fleſh in the wombe of the virgin conceyued by the grace of the holy ghoſt, without the ſéed of man, the holy virgin as the buſhe, remaining neuertheles perfect &amp; vncorrupte. He was ſacrificed as the iuſt and innocent Lambe, hys blood be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng ſhed to preſerue vs from the tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of Sathan,<note place="margin">Paſcal lambe. Iohn. 1. Hebr. 13.</note> and to open vnto vs the paſſage into the land of promiſe the kyngdome of heauen.<note place="margin">Bread of lyfe. Iohn. 6.</note> He is the trew bread which came downe from heauen, wythout leuaine, without corruption, and ſpotte, whereof we muſte eate for our ſpirituall nouriſhement, to the ende we maye celebrate the feaſt of the Pharaonicall paſſage in the lande of libertie. He was the cloude,<note place="margin">1. Corin. 5. The cloude, fyry pillour &amp; red ſea.</note> the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rye Pyllour, the redde Sea deuided, why<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che hathe conducted vs, whyche hath delyuered vs from the handes of oure enemyes, oute of whoſe ſyde opened,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. Iohn. 19.</note> came bloode and water for oure ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation and redemption.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:25"/>
               <note place="margin">The heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Manna, the rock flowing water of lyfe. 1. Corin. 10.</note>He was the heauenly Manna ſent from heauen to nouryſhe vs for euer, and the true rocke from whence flowed water to quenche the thruſt of al thoſe for euer which thruſt and beleue in him. It was he that made the ſacrifice of health for the defacing of our ſynnes,<note place="margin">Sacrifice. Heb. 7.8.9.10</note> the ſacrificer and ſacrifice, the offering &amp; offerer abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for euer, a ſacrificer at the ryght hand of God hys father. He entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the heauenly ſanctuary, buylded not with the handes of men,<note place="margin">Heb. 9.</note> but with the hand of God. He was the trew arcke of couenaunt &amp; appoyntment,<note place="margin">The arcke of witnes.</note> by the whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch god did manifeſt &amp; declare his oracles and in the which he did reſt to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhe his diuine and incomprehenſible miſteries. He was as the braſen ſerpent faſtened to the croſſe,<note place="margin">Braſent ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent. Iohn. 3.</note> to geue health to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſickenneſſe of all thoſe which did tourne toward hym, &amp; beholde him in faith.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">temple of god Iohn. 2.</note>He was the trew temple of God wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the holy ghoſt doth dwell, in whome and by whom one god in trinitie is wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhipped. He was the true &amp; holy ſacrifice
<pb facs="tcp:25622:25"/>
whereof was made the purgyng water for the cleanſing of all ſpotts,<note place="margin">The hoſte &amp; holy water.</note> hauynge by his owne aſhes, that is by hys owne body offered vp,<note place="margin">Iohn. 19.</note> ſprinckeled &amp; watered with water iſſuing out of his ſide, all people beleuing in him.</p>
            <p>The ceremoniall law being thus ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed not by fygures, but really executed by thincarnation, death, &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of Ieſus Chriſt, our ſauiour, our mediatour, our euerlaſting ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, &amp; mercy obteyner, the infinite good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of God was yet more manifeſted by the new band,<note place="margin">Hebr. 9.</note> new couenaunt &amp; new comming of the ſonne of God incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> For by his new teſtament confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the death of the teſtator, he hath made vs fellow heyres &amp; inheritours of the kingdome of heauen with God.</p>
            <p>For aſſuraunce of this heauenly ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion gotten to vs by grace, after that he had finiſhed the ceremoniall lawe, and aboliſhed the ſame (as we haue ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed) by the ſacrifice perfectly made by the euerlaſtyng Sacrificer, there were
<pb facs="tcp:25622:26"/>
left vnto vs two ſacred ſignes and holy ſacraments,<note place="margin">S. Auguſtine in his 3. boke of the chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an doctrine. chapter. 9.</note> wherein God hath vſed more fauour and more ſpeciall grace, than euer he dyd before his incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in this that he hath delyuered vs from the ſeruile lawe of circumciſion, of difference of meates, and of diuers ſacrifices ordeyned in the fyrſte churche of the Iſraelites, and in diſchargynge vs of this heauye burthen, he hathe ſo muche the moore comforted vs in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deyning vnto vs for a memorye and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membraunce of our regencration and lyfe euerlaſtyng, two holy ſacramentes, vnder two holye ſygnes.<note place="margin">Sacramentes of the newe teſtament.</note> To witte, the water of Baptiſme, and the bread, and wyne, for the partakyng of hys bodye, and that hys grace myght extend to all nations, God dyd chooſe thoſe tokens and ſygnes whyche were moſte com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and eaſye.</p>
            <p>For Circumciſion was a ſpeciall marke for Abraham and hys poſteritie, the which Circumciſion other nations were not accuſtomed to vſe, althoughe
<pb facs="tcp:25622:26"/>
Herodote a Gréeke in the hiſtory which he writeth of the maners of the Egip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,<note place="margin">Herod lib. 2.</note> doth attribute vnto them the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome to circumciſe, eſpeciallye their Prieſtes. But it is eaſie to coniecture, that he had heard ſpeaking of the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes dwelling in Egipt for the ſpace of foure hundred and thirtie yeres obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the circumciſion.<note place="margin">A comparing of the circum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſion with baptiſme. Exod. 12.</note> Moreouer the Circumciſion was ordeyned for the men only, and not for the women: there was alſo a day ſet for Circumciſion, the eyght day after the natiuitie: &amp; the cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the ſkynne was paynefull and greuouſe.<note place="margin">Geneſ 17.</note> But the grace of God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing abolyſhed, by his incarnation and perfect ſacrifice, the rigour of the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall lawe, as well for the difference of meates as of dayes, hath left vnto vs by his new wyll and couenaunt, the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſigne of water common to all, aſwell men as women,<note place="margin">Num. 19.</note> without difference of dayes, and in this holye ſacrament the chyld baptized féeleth no grief, as he did féele in cutting of the ſkynne.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:27"/>This ſigne of water, to repreſent vnto vs the purging and cleanſing of our ſinnes by the bloude of Ieſus Chriſt, was common not onely to the Iewes, which were wont to vſe their cleanſing water, but alſo to the Gentils and all nacions who had in vſe the cleanſyng and waſhynge with this water called <hi>Luſtrale &amp; Expiatorye,</hi> as may appear by reading of auncient hiſtories.</p>
            <p>To the ende then that the grace of god, by Ieſus Chriſt might extend to all the worlde generally, to all nations, coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys &amp; prouinces, as well circumciſed as vncircumciſed, Iewes as Gentilles, god did chooſe the ſigne of water moſte common, ſo muche the more applying it to the commoditie of man to draw hym to feare &amp; obedience. By the which ſigne he inſtituted the holy ſacrament of bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, for a note &amp; aſſured marke of our regeneration, &amp; purifiyng repreſented ſacramentally by the vertue of the holy ghoſt,<note place="margin">Titus. 3. Galath. 3.</note> in the which ſacrament god doth aſſiſt &amp; aſſure vs to be borne a newe and
<pb facs="tcp:25622:27"/>
made one with Chriſt Ieſus, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued and made members of his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and that he wyll receyue vs as clad and incorporate into him &amp; by him.</p>
            <p>Lyke reaſons might be brought for the other holy ſacrament ordeyned of god by his newe teſtament, to witte,<note place="margin">Sacrament of the holy ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of ieſus Chriſt.</note> of bread and wyne. Which ſignes, tokens figures and notable formes, all nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons haue bene accuſtomed to vſe in their ſacrifices, oblations, and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, concerning their religions, aſwell circumciſed as vncircumciſed, aſwell Iewes as Gentils. Alſo the two kyndes of foodes for the nouriſhment of man are contayned vnder bread and wyne. For theſe cauſes our good god deſyring to draw vnto him all nacions, to noriſhe and miniſter moſt neceſſary foode vnto them, did inſtitute the communion of the body and blooud of our ſauour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt vnder the formes, holy ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnes, and ſacraments of bread &amp; wyne. For as we are aſſured by the mark and element of water in baptiſme to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate
<pb facs="tcp:25622:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:28"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:29"/>
and renued in the bodye and bloode of Ieſus Chriſt repreſented by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament of holy water, by the vertue of the holy ghoſt. Euen ſo are we nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by the communion of his bodye and bloode repreſented reallye by the bread and Wyne conſecrated for ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall foode and nouriſhment euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting and quickening by the power of the holye Ghoſt. Wherein God fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured vs muche in diſcharginge vs of bloody ſacrifices ordeyned in the firſt churche of the Iſraelits, whiche were wont to be charged with many and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſacrifices celebrated with the ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the bloode of earthly beaſts, after the diuerſitie of offences, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons offendynge. All whyche ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices were ended, and put awaye by the ſhedynge of the bloode of the iuſte and innocent Lambe,<note place="margin">Heb. 9,</note> Ieſus Chriſt, whiche by hys perfecte ſacrifice hath vtterlye abolyſſhed all other ſacrifyces reſeruynge vnto hym ſelfe the dignitie of the great and euerlaſtynge ſacrificer,
<pb facs="tcp:25622:29"/>
ſittyng at the ryghte hande of God hys father. But he hath fauoured vs ſo muche, that in place of the abolyſhed ſacrifices, he hath inſtituted the two holye ſacramentes before mencioned to aſſure vs of our regeneration, our purgynge, our adoption, our nouryſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and eternall lyfe geuen vs by the blood of our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>But as the Iſraelites to groſſe,<note place="margin">Corruption of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes.</note> and carnall, dyd reſt in the exterior ſignes, corruptynge the trewe vſe of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes and ſacrifices geuen vnto them of God. Euen ſo lyke abuſe, yea, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter corruptions, are come vnto oure two holye Sacramentes lefte vnto vs by the newe teſtament of Ieſus Chriſt, for the ſacrament of Baptiſme ſucce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the place of Circumciſion, man (conceyued of corrupted clay) would not be contented w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Gods holye inſtitution: But ſome haue brewed &amp; corrupted the vſe of the holy ſacrament of baptiſme w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> adiurations &amp; coniurings,<note place="margin">Sacrament of Baptiſme corrupte.</note> iuggling of ſalt, of oyle, of tapers, creame, blowings,
<pb facs="tcp:25622:30"/>
hoodes, or biggyns, with an infinite number of croſſes, on the forehead, on the eyes, on the noſe, on the backe, on the breſte,<note place="margin">Theodor in his booke of the fables of heretikes.</note> on the ſhulders, and on the mouth, to chaſe away Deuills. For the Maſſalians heretikes authours of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuring and croſſing, do ſays that the chylde borne is accompanied with his ſpirit or deuill,<note place="margin">Ca. ſine: Ca. poſtquam de conſecratione diſtinct. 4.</note> which can not be chaſed awaye but by adiuration and coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. And for this cauſe this holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Baptiſme hath bene corrupted ſo farre, that they haue added therevnto ſtrang termes of the Syrian language,<note place="margin">Ephetath. per Satyr. 2.</note> with ſpittell and purging ſnyuell.</p>
            <p>What greater corruption coulde there be deſcribed then theſe abhominable inuentions? as if the blood of Ieſus Chriſt had not bene ſufficient for our regeneration and purgation?<note place="margin">Gala. 3. Ephe. 4. 1. Cor. 15.</note> And as yf God had not bene of power ſufficient to perfect and regenerate vs by the holye ſigne of water repreſenting the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, if there were not ſpittel coniured ſnyuell, oyles, ſalt, biggyns,
<pb facs="tcp:25622:30"/>
creame, tourches or tapers, or milke, or honny inuented by other heretikes.</p>
            <p>Other more ſubtill Magicians,<note place="margin">Tertulian in his booke of the crouned ſouldier.</note> Pitha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorians, inſtructed in the Maſſalian do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, haue added moreouer to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunce twenty times ouer the man child preſented to Baptiſme the name of a Deuill (which they ſaye) doth accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie him, by that meanes to adiure and coniure him away. And at the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of a wenche, to ſaye the ſame thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie times. Was there euer ſuch deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble corruption in the ſacrament of cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion? Wherefore (O Maſſalians) haue you brued your oyles, in the holy ſacrament of Baptiſme? Folowing the hereſye of Marcus &amp; Marcoſus,<note place="margin">Epipha. lib. 1. tom. 3. hereſ. 34.</note> which commaunded to annoynt the children that were to be baptized. The holy ſigne of water inſtituted by the hand of God, was it not ſufficient to repreſent the pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious blood of Ieſus Chriſt for our rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration &amp; purification, without bruing of greſes, of oyles, of ſpittell, &amp; other minglings inuented by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corruptors of
<pb facs="tcp:25622:31"/>
the holy ſacraments? The body &amp; bloud of Ieſus Chriſt wherewith we be clade by the holy water of Baptiſme, was it not ſufficient to preſerue vs from all tempeſts without borowing of biggins and criſomes? And for an other more great corruption &amp; abuſe it was permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto wemen to baptiſe,<note place="margin">Tom. 1. Epipha. lib. 1. hereſ. 42. &amp; lib. 2. tom. 1. hereſ. 49.</note> folowinge the error of the Marcioniſts, Quintili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Cataphriges, Montaniſtes, Pepu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zians, Priſcillians &amp; Artotirites. Was it euer permitted vnto wemen by the law of god to adminiſter the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes or ſacrifice inſtituted in the firſt church of the Iſralites, or in the newe teſtament of Ieſus Chriſt. In the Hiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of Moiſes it is reſited,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.</note> how that his wife Sephora, moued with a womanly rage, toke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtone or knife wherwith ſhe circumciſed her ſonne, but it is not wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that ſhe, or any other her like, hath at any time ben permitted to miniſter the holy ſacraments. By ſuche corruptions of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſacrament of baptiſme, Many hereſies haue ſpro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vp by Catabaptiſts
<pb facs="tcp:25622:31"/>
Anabaptiſtes Antipedobaptiſts &amp; other heritiks, &amp; ſciſmaticks, which not conten<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the pure &amp; ſincere inſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of god did more reſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> outwarde ſignes than in that which by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was repreſented in ſpirit. He y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſireth to know more parti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>culerly the abuſes &amp; corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s inuented at diuers tymes by diuers humurrs of men, let him read our eccleſiaſticall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries. It remaineth preſently to come to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corruptions of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> other holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy &amp; blood of Ieſus Chriſt. By this ſhort diſcourſe a man may clerely know how variable &amp; fraile man is, alwais hauing abuſed the grace of god. For like as fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the beginning of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law &amp; inſtruction ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the people of Iſrael did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer corrupt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true vſe of ſacrifices, holy ſignes &amp; ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ordeined of god: euen ſo is it come to paſſe of of the law of god by Ieſus chriſt, hauing inſtituted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municat his body &amp; blood vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figures &amp; holy ſignes of bread &amp; wine. The which holy ſacrament was abuſed in the time of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtles by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s:
<pb facs="tcp:25622:32"/>
Againſt whom the holy apoſtle did writ epiſtilles,<note place="margin">Sacrament of the ſupper corrupted. 1. Cor. 11.</note> to the end to bringe them to the true and ſincere obſeruacion of thys holy Sacrament. Let no man therefore hereafter thinke it ſtraunge yf the ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours of the Apoſtles from tyme, to tyme haue corrupted the true vſe of this holy Sacrament. And the more they were diſtaunt from the time of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of Ieſus Chriſte, the more they fell into corruption: Yea abhominable: turnyng the vſe of the Sacrament into a depth of Idolatry. Firſt into what con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tention, fell the church y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was next vnto the apoſtles,<note place="margin">Eccleſiaſticall hiſtorie,</note> about y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> determining of the dayes wherin the holy ſacrament ſhuld be celebrated? Sabatius the heretik did inſtitute the celebration of Eaſter with vnleauened breade after the maner of the Iewes.<note place="margin">Hiſto. tripart. lib. 9 ca. 37. &amp; lib. 11. cap. 5</note> Certaine of hys ſecte dyd or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayne the vſe of the holy Sacrament to be celebrated the .xiiij.<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 5. cap. 24. Hiſto. tripart. lib. 9. cap. 38 &amp; 39,</note> Moone, as the Iewes did. It is ſayd, there were of this ſect Policrates biſhop of the Epheſians, philip Hieropolitain Policarp, Truſeas
<pb facs="tcp:25622:32"/>
Melite and Narciſſus, biſhop of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lem. Of the contrary opinion were, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor biſhop of Rome, &amp; Eluther his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diceſſor, with Theophile biſhop of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine. This contention continued more than three hundred yeres after the Apoſtles. Some celebrated the feaſt of Eaſter after the Equinoxall, when the Sunne did enter into the ſigne of Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. Other obſerued the moneth Xanthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoe, called by the Romains Aprill.</p>
            <p>Some ſayed (to witte) the Quartodeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, that it was inſtituted by Sainct Iohn, to celebrate in the xiiij. Moone. Others aduaunced them ſelues to be taught by Sainct Peter, whereas yet there was no euident appearaunce of any thing. The Montaniſts Phrygians condempned the Quartodecimans ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruers of the courſe of the Moone, and that they ought to order them ſelues by the courſe of the Sunne, beginning at the Equinoxall in Primtyde: And by this meanes they celebrated the eyght Ides of Aprill, which is the .xiiij. day of
<pb facs="tcp:25622:33"/>
the ſayde moneth. Prouided that it fell vppon Sondaye.</p>
            <p>There was not onely contention for the vſe of the ſacraments in what dayes it ſhoulde be celebrated,<note place="margin">Eueſ. lib. 5. cap. 4.</note> but alſo there was great diuiſion among the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans for ceremonies inuented to prepare them ſelues to receyue the ſame wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thely. For ſome (as the Romains) dyd keepe the faſt three weekes before Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter. The Illyriens and all Grece with the Alexandrians did ordeyne a Lent to faſte ſixe weekes. Others ordeyned vij. weekes of faſting, leauing of from fyue dayes to fyue dayes.</p>
            <p>More and more to corrupt the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the ſupper, there was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored another Iudaicall ceremony,<note place="margin">Hiſto. tripart. cap. 8.</note> by the differencie of meates. For ſome (du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ryng the tyme of faſt) forbad eatynge of fleſhe and fiſhe. Other forbad eating of fleſhe onely, permitting to eate fiſhe and foules, whyche they ſayde (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge to Moyſes) dyd take parte of the ſubſtaunce of the water. Some alſo
<pb facs="tcp:25622:33"/>
dyd ordeyne to eate drye bread and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter only. Others faſted till noone w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out diſtinction of meates. And to be ſhorte, there was in the beginning an infinite nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of cuſtomes &amp; corruptions in the vſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſacrament of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper, by ceremonies brought in by the difference of dayes and meates, abrogated &amp; put away by the grace and lawe of Ieſus Chriſt. But was there euer any holy Apoſtle of god,<note place="margin">Coloſ. 2. Galath. 4. Heb. 7.</note> which euer left in wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting any lawe or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maudement, for the diſtinction of dayes or meates, to cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brate the holy ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt? Their intention was not to inſtitute a religion of feaſts &amp; a diſtinction of daies and meates, but their doctrine did tend onely to teach good life, &amp; the true wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of one god onely. Wherefore we muſt néeds co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude that the ceremonie &amp; feaſt of Eaſter, to celebrate the ſupper of our Lorde God,<note place="margin">Hiſto. tripart. lib. 9. cap. 38</note> is proceded of mere cuſtome. For none of the Apoſtles hathe lefte anye thynge in wrytynge touchyng the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:34"/>To moderate ſuch diſſentions &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions many counſells were aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, one at Sangaria in Bytine by the which (to auoyde al contentions) it was permitted to euery one to celebrate Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter when he would.<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 5. chap. 23.</note> Another counſell was holden at Ceſaria by Theophile biſhop of that place, and by Narciſſus biſhop of Ieruſalem. Another counſell in Achaye. And another counſell was holden at Rome, by Victor biſhoppe of that place.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">In the yere of Chriſt. 114.</note>After theſe litle corruptions, there ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded greater from tyme to tyme, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the humours &amp; affections of the biſhoppes of Rome,<note place="margin">Platine Sabellie.</note> Alexander the firſt of that name, being come to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perintendant of the Romaine churche, the firſt of the ſucceſſors of the Apoſtles of Ieſus Chriſt, and alſo the firſt of the corrupters of the holy ſacrament of the ſupper, ordeyned to mixe water with the wyne before the communion: wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he ment to reforme the ghoſpel of Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, which had inſtituted the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munion
<pb facs="tcp:25622:34"/>
of his body &amp; bloode, to be vnder two kyndes bread and wyne, but Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander added a thirde kynde (to ſay) wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 3. cap. 27. &amp; lib. 6. cap. 14.</note> He reſtored alſo the Iudaicall cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of vnleauened bread (called ſwete bread) to celebrate the Eaſter as the Iewes did. Followyng therein the Ebionites, which taught that the cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniall law of Moyſes was neceſſarye for ſaluation: as alſo Symmachus an heretike in Paleſtine had taught. If Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt was circumciſed to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſh the ceremoniall law, is it therefore needfull for vs to be circumciſed? More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouer if it pleaſed him (to accompliſh the ceremoniall law) to vſe in the dayes of ſwete bread, vnleauened bread: Is it therefore neceſſary to tourne agayn vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the rigour of this ceremonie abroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſacrifice perfectly ended by Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt?<note place="margin">Cel. lib. 39. cap. 21.</note> In what place of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel cold Alexa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der euer finde to mixe wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the wyne? And for to bynde Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtians to vnleauened bread, is it of any more value, than his inuention, to
<pb facs="tcp:25622:35"/>
chaſe away deuills with water ſalted &amp; coniured? And as touching his coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red water ordeyned by him, we wyll ſhewe hereafter that the original there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of came from Neuma Pompilius the great coniurer and Romaine Idolater. But as for the mingling of the water with wyne, that ſhoulde ſéeme to be taught by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> religion of the ancient Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters, which were wont in celebrating their ſacrifices, in one chalyce to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate the water with the bread, ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the feaſt dedicated to the Sunne, which the Perſians did worſhip, called of them Mythros.<note place="margin">Iuſtin in his apologie.</note> And in the feaſt alſo of Nephalies water was vſed for the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice. According to this compariſon, Iuſtin martyr maketh relation of the cuſtome obſerued amonge the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, &amp; Chriſtians, for the bread, wyne, &amp; water co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated. By the one, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſay by the Idolatours, in the name of theyr Idolles: &amp; by the Chriſtians in the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of theyr trewe God. Alwayes this firſt corruption in the vſage of the holye
<pb facs="tcp:25622:35"/>
ſacrament by the minglynge of water with wyne beyonde the commaunde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment &amp; ordinannce of God,<note place="margin">Inno. lib. 4. cap. 5.</note> did not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue without controuerſie: For the Greekes were of a contrarye opinion, that it was not neceſſarye to mixe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with wyne, and that they would not followe the corruption of Alexander. Amarcanus was of the ſame aduice that Alexander was: ſaying that it was neceſſarye to mingle it with water.</p>
            <p>The ſubtill Sophiſte Scot doeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme abſolutelye that it is not neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſarye the water to bee myngled wyth the Wyne, becauſe (ſayeth he) it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be chaunged and tranſſubſtancia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into bloode yf fyrſte it be not chaunged into Wyne.</p>
            <p>Other moore ingenious woulde ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther interpretate the inſtitution of Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xander, ſaying y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Wyne to be conuerted into blood, but as for the water, it was tranſſubſtantiated into the water whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che came out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyde of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:36"/>
               <note place="margin">S. Auguſtine in his boke of the relikes chapter. 26. &amp; 64.</note>This firſt corruption of Alexander did geue occation of many other to ſuccede. for ſome inuented greater brueyngs to mingle it w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> blood drawen out of yonge infants to mixt with the bread of tholy ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt, as the Cataphri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, which began a kynde of tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantion of wyne into blood really &amp; cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally.<note place="margin">Epipha. lib. 2. Tom. 1. hereſ. 49.</note> Some other adioyned therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to cheaſe called Artotirites, that is to ſay, cheaſe bread. Others alſo abuſing this ſacrament, in ſteed of wyne tooke water, vnder pretence of moore greater abſtinence. Other ordeyned to temper the bread with wyne, which the Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians doe yet holde in their miſſall ſacrificers.</p>
            <p>For another more deteſtable corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy ſacrament, ſome biſhops of Rome haue forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their Maſſalian ſacrificers to miniſter vnto the chriſten people (which they call laye) the body of Ieſus Chriſt vnder both kinds, but only vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſigne of bread, and not of wine, the which they kept for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Prieſtes
<pb facs="tcp:25622:36"/>
Maſſalians ſacrificers.<note place="margin">Math. 29. Marc. 14. Luc. 22. 1. Cor. 11.</note> Is not this cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption directly againſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſpell &amp; inſtitution of the ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt which hath ordeyned and commaunded all faythfull to eate his bodye &amp; drynke his blood. When he toke the cuppe vſed he not theſe proper termes, drynke al of this wyne in memory &amp; remembrance of my bloode ſhed. Hath he vſed anye other tearmes for eating of hys bodye by the figure of bread, than he hath done for drynkyng of hys bloode by the ſygne of wyne? If one ſhould compare herewith the holy ſigne ordeyned of god in the church of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſraelites, a figure of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Ieſus chriſt (which was the paſcal lambe) the fleſhe whereof was commaunded to be ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of all perſons wythout exception, for as muche as they were circumciſed: Was there euer anye difference in the eatyng of the paſcall Lambe, and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bratyng of the Paſſeouer of the Iewes amonge the Leuites of the ſtocke of the Prieſts and the other common people?
<pb facs="tcp:25622:37"/>
For another deteſtable corruption, the Maſſalians haue inſtituted by theyr miſſall Idolatries, to ſacrifice and offer the body and blood of Ieſus Chriſt, in reiterating (by that meanes) the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of Ieſus Chriſt perfectly ended, and can not be done againe: for that it was not after the order of Aaron, but after the order of Melchiſedech,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> an euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting ſacrificer, who hath left no ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor. Alſo the holy apoſtle when he admo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed the Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s reuerently to ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrate y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt, dyd he commaunde them to ſacrifice? No, but to communicate and eate together the body and blood of Ieſus Chriſt. The be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the holy ſupper was not to kyll, offer, and ordeyne a ſacrifice, to offer to God: But onelye to eate and drynke at the holy feaſt prepared for vs by Ieſus Chriſt the euerlaſting ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice and euerlaſting ſacrificer, whiche hath reſerued vnto him ſelfe onely this eternall prieſthode. And yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe hath lefte his holye inſtitution a
<pb facs="tcp:25622:37"/>
banquet ordeined for vs of bread &amp; wine repreſenting hys body and blood.</p>
            <p>After the corruptions aboueſayde, Sathan the diligent Babilonicall buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der imployed al his forces &amp; ſtrengthes, to buyld an inuincible fortreſſe of Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie: to the end to fight againſt &amp; vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly throw downe the kingdome of Ieſus Chriſt, when he did enterpriſe the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng of the Maſſe to be brought in, in the place of the holy ſacrament of the ſupper, as we will briefly and ſo cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly declare, that the moſte hard hearted Phariſies (made olde in their auncient Idolatries) ſhall acknowledge by the veritie of hiſtories their errours and abhominable hereſies.</p>
            <p>Before the painting out of this Maze of error (whereinto the Maſſalians are plunged) I haue thought it neceſſarye, briefly to diſcouer the auncient religion of the Romaines, the reigne of the occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental empire, &amp; of the emperors which haue exerciſed both the temporal office, &amp; the dignitie of the great biſhops ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tendents of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; church of Rom.
<pb facs="tcp:25622:38"/>
All other (as well as I) ſhall confeſſe that the Romaine religion all together for the moſte part to haue bene inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by Neuma Pompilius the ſeconde kyng of the Romains,<note place="margin">Titenile lib. 1 Decad. 1.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Funeſtral in his boke of magiſtrats of Rome.</note> about 700 yeres before the incarnation of Ieſus Chriſt. Then were inſtituted the biſhops whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che afterwarde were broughte to a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne number, vnto foure, than the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber was augmented to eyght, and by Sylla to fyftene. In the colledge of bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes there was one chiefe biſhoppe, which was choſen by the other leſſe bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes of the ſame order and dignitie, lyke as the lytle byſhoppes purple Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals haue practiſed the election of the great Romain biſhoppe, of their eſtate order and dignitie. This Pompilian religion hath bene ſo well obſerued by the Romaines from the father to the ſonne, that it hath bene impoſſible to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroye and plucke vp the ſame, but hath continued to this daye, as euerye one may eaſly perceiue by this litle collectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>To confirme this poynt there is none
<pb facs="tcp:25622:38"/>
that can be ignoraunt, which luſteth to read the Romaine hiſtories, that before the incarnation of Ieſus Chriſt there was not one King, Conſul, Dictator, or Romaine Emperour inſtructed in the law of God. But all were Idolaters, &amp; Infidels, folowing the religion of Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Pompilius the coniurer. And that more is, after the incarnation of Ieſus Chriſt, for the ſpace of 300 yeres or there abouts, there was no Emperour,<note place="margin">Euſeb. in hys boke of the church hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye the yeres of Chriſt. 34. 68. 94. 112. 113. 167, 202, 238, 254, 257, 276, &amp; 292.</note> nor Romain councell which would change his religion to embrace the lawe of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. But contrariwiſe they haue laboured with toothe and nayle to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe all kynde of crueltie agaynſt the churche of Ieſus Chriſt, as the eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall hiſtories do largely declare, pain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting out great perſecutions vnder the great Romain biſhops, to wit, Claud. Tiber. Nero, Claud. Domitian Nero, Fla. Domitian, Traian, Elie Hadri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Antonian Phiſopher, Septime Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uere, Iul. Maximus, Max. Quin. Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian, Dece, Licime, Valerian, Valere
<pb facs="tcp:25622:39"/>
Aurelian &amp; Diocletian. Al which were emperours and gouerned the empire &amp; romain religion for 300 yeres after the incarnation of Ieſus Chriſt, and in their moneyes, ſepultures, monume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, tytles and autentique letters, did holde the name of great biſhops &amp; high prieſts, as diligently is gathered in a booke of the antiquities of Rome, wherein be deſcribed the Images, moneyes, &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numentes, of the auncient Emperours of Rome,<note place="margin">In the booke intituled the diſcourſe of the religion of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Romains by Wylliam de Choul. bay lye of Daul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phine.</note> which were all called great biſhops, by theſe tytles, <hi>Iul. Ceſ. Pontif. max. Tiber. Nero Pontif. max. Claud. Nero. pontif. max. Vaſpaſianus Ceſ. pontif. max. Traianus Impera. Pontif. max. Marc. Aurel. Antonn. Auguſt. Pontif. Heliogabalus ſummus ſacerdos Aug. Adrianus Imper. Pontif. max. Galerius Maximinianus Pontif. max. Tit. Ceſ. Pontif. max. Commod. Impe. pontif. max. Flauius Conſtantius Aug. Pontif. max.</hi> Which being than Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous &amp; great biſhoppes would ſuffer
<pb facs="tcp:25622:39"/>
none other head in the religion &amp; Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main church then them ſelues, beynge alwayes enemies of Ieſus Chriſt. For when the Apoſtles did preach Chriſt to be the ſoueraine prieſt, great and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ſacrificer without any ſucceſſour after the order of Melchiſedech, the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rauntes of Rome and theyr Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunts, dyd take an occaſion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempne Ieſus Chriſt, fearing that the authoritie of the Emperours and great Romaine biſhoppes ſhould be demini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed. With what furour were they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged for the ſpace of 300 yeres agaynſt the Chriſtians &amp; Chriſts religion,<note place="margin">In the Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logg of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, in the ende of the hiſtorie of Nicephors the yere of Chriſt. 410.</note> to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend their auncient religion of Pompi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius? what anſwer was geuen to Theo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>doſe thmperour by the ſenate &amp; ſenators of Rome, when it was put forth vnto them to chaung their religion, and to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue the religion of Ieſus Chriſt. Thei ſhewed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei had poſſeſſed their Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian religion more then 1000 yeres, and that all chaunging of religions were the deſtructions of common welthes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:40"/>Wherefore conſiſting in their olde Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine religion, they remained without receyuing of the lawe of Ieſus Chriſt. By theſe hiſtories it is eaſie to be reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued that for the ſpace of 400 yeres and more, the biſhops of Rome (whiche cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led themſelues Chriſtians) could neuer obteyne of the Senate &amp; Romaine Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours to receyue the holye ghoſpell, muche leſſe could they conuert the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Idolaters, cauſing them to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their inueterate Idolatry. For the biſhops of Rome were to much occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in reſtoring the Iudaycall &amp; Pagans ceremonies for the deſtinction of mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,<note place="margin">In the canon reueled by clement bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of rome 21, 22, 62, 95.</note> ordinance not to faſt Sondaye and Thurſday, to ſet an order for table clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, veales, veſſels of golde and ſiluer, ſerſors and tapeſtrye, and other orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the aulters, whiche conſumed with age, were ordeyned to be burned and the aſhes to be put into the founte. Other were merueylouſly occupyed to reſtore the Iudaycall ceremonies, of ſweete bread, &amp; trauayled their ſpirites
<pb facs="tcp:25622:40"/>
greatly to corrupt the true vſage of the holy ſacramentes inſtituted of god,<note place="margin">Alexander the firſte of that name bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome in the yere of Chriſt. 110.</note> by mingling of water with wyne, bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing of ſalte with the water to make it purged and coniured to dryue awaye deuils. Other alſo did trauell to inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Corporaſſes of fyue linnen to laye vp the conſecrated hoſtes,<note place="margin">Xiſtus biſhop of Rome in the yere of Chriſt. 121.</note> &amp; to ordeyne alſo albes &amp; other veſtiments of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes for their ſacrifices of whyte colour without ſpot.<note place="margin">Silueſter bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome</note> Some did torment theyr braynes, to inuent the feaſts of dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; conſecration, with coniuring with ſalt to dryue awaye deuills.<note place="margin">Higinus bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome in the yere of chriſt. 140.</note> And ſome other to inuent oyles and creames to corrupt the holy ſacrament of baptiſme. Moreouer (during the reygne of theſe tyrants, Emperours,<note place="margin">Fabian bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome in the yere of chriſt 240.</note> &amp; great biſhops) the biſhops of Rome deſiring to make their names continue for euer, did drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me in their ſpirites to buylde temples, not vnto the honour of God,<note place="margin">Pius biſhop of Rome in the yere of chriſt 144.</note> but in the name of their he &amp; ſhe ſaincts canonized by them at their pleaſure. Other did oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupye them ſelues to ordeyne that the
<pb facs="tcp:25622:41"/>
conſecrated bread and wyne falling vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ground, ſhould be left to the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificer, and the reſt remaining ſhoulde be bourned with fyer: and the aſhes ſhould be layed vp among the reliques. Other did trauaile to ſette an order amonge chaliſes,<note place="margin">Zepherin bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome in the yere of Chriſt. 200. Calixtus bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome in the yere of chriſt. 220. Eutich bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome in the yere of chriſt 282.</note> whether they ſhoulde be of glaſſe or of wood. And by other were inſtituted ſolempne ceremonies foure tymes a yere, to bring Chriſtians to the bondage of diſtinction of dayes. Some were occupied merueylouflye to ordeyne the offering and conſecration of fables, to celebrate funerals in pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple garmentes after the maner of the veſtment called Trabea, the which the Idolators did vſe in triumphes celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the honour of their Gods.<note place="margin">The red ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes of Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalles.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And the lyke purple garment is vſed of the Cardynalles to this daye. Others were occupyed to inuent a confirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for yonge chyldren,<note place="margin">Silueſter bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome in the yere of Chriſt 314.</note> and that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes onely ſhoulde conſecrate the creame: To honour alſo the Biſhop of Hoſtienſe, by whoſe hands the Biſhop
<pb facs="tcp:25622:41"/>
of Rome muſte be conſecrated, with a cloke called Pallium. And to inuent an infinite nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of other vnneceſſary cere<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monies, contrarye to the libertie of the ghoſpel geuen vnto vs by Ieſus Chriſt. Howe was it than poſſible that the firſt Biſhoppes of Rome ſhoulde drawe the princes and Senators Romaynes vnto the lawe of the Ghoſpell, durynge 300 or 400 yeres after the incarnation of Ieſus Chriſt, ſeyng they did not labour but to corrupt the vſe of the holye ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and to reſtore the Iudaicall ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, and Idolatries of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the auncient Romaines?</p>
            <p>But here might one obiect one Philip which ſome vau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to haue bene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted to holy baptiſme (the maners of whome were ſo wicked that they gaue occation to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt credible authours, to deſcribe him vnworthy the name of a chriſtian. One might bringe in Conſtantyn the great,<note place="margin">Chronicle of Iohn Baptiſt.</note> which cauſed the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel of Nice to aſſemble: but his reſide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was in Grecia being called the emperour of the Eaſt.
<pb facs="tcp:25622:42"/>
And yet wolde he neuer receiue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne of Baptiſme,<note place="margin">Hiſto. tripart. lib. 3. cap. 12.</note> to be regenerate by the blood of Ieſus Chriſt, vntyll he was lxv. yeres olde, at what tyme he was baptiſed by a biſhop of Nicomede Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, named Euſebe, the ſame Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine being at point of death. Siluer than the biſhoppe of Rome, muſte not crake that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted this Emperour to the fayth. For this ſame Silueſter woulde not aſſiſt the aſſemble of the counſell holden at Nice in the yere of Ieſus Chriſt 327. Howe ſoeuer it be, it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenient to haue recourſe always to the veritie of Hiſtories, wherein is recited the anſwere of the Senate and Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Rome, to the Emperour Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doze, more then 60 yeres after the death of the ſayde Conſtantine the great: Which was, that they woulde not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the lawe of Ieſus Chriſt, but ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theyr auncient lawe Pompilian, to auoyde the ruine of theyr common wealthe, whiche mighte come by the chaungyng of religion. Whereby may
<pb facs="tcp:25622:42"/>
be well gathered, that than the lawe of god was not receyued nor approued at Rome by the Senate and Senators.</p>
            <p>It reſteth that preſently we come nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to the tyme folowyng. After the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe of Theodoze, the Romaine Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre of the Weſt began ſo to bowe, that in ſhort tyme it was quyte put out by Wandeloys and Alayns,<note place="margin">Paul. Emil. lib 1. the yere of chriſt. 412. 154.</note> which were the chief that ſacked Rome, burnt the moſt part of it, and rauiſhed the proper doughter of the Emperour Theodore: whome they married to Ataulphe king of the Gothes.<note place="margin">Blond lib. 2. Decad. 1.</note> A lytle whyle after ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceded the Hunnes. Then Attilia kyng of the Gothes, which vſurped Italy.</p>
            <p>About this tyme the Romaine Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyre of the Weſte was ſpoyled of all Germany, Acia, Sarmatia,<note place="margin">Procop. lib. 3. of the warre of the Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dales in the yere of chriſt 486.</note> and all the Prouinces tributaries, vnto Danube: Spaygne alſo, Aquitania, Gaſcoygne, Bourgoyne, &amp; al the Gaules did reuolt fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the romain tyrany. Then ſucceded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Oſtrogots w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their king Valemir, The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odemer, Theodoricke &amp; other Heathen
<pb facs="tcp:25622:43"/>
and Infidels.<note place="margin">The yere of chriſt. 550. 554</note> The Viſigothes alſo, all vſurpers ſucceſſiuely of Italy. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward raigned Totilas, whiche forced, robbed and burned Rome,<note place="margin">Paul. Emil. lib 1. the yere of chriſt. 568.</note> and all Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile. In the ende the Lomberds condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by their kyngs Alboin did raygne, which vſurped Italye. Theſe barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous nations, Idolators, and Infidels did ſerue as whippes ordeyned of God to puniſhe the Idolaters of Rome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by them, whiche had knowledge of the holye Ghoſpell. And yet tourned back from the true worſhipping of god: Violating and corrupting the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments by the inuentions of men: To puniſhe alſo the infidelitie and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinatie of the Emperours and Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of Rome, which firſt of all cauſed theyr Lieutenaunts, and officers ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted in Iudea to crucifie Chriſt and his holy Apoſtles, to perſecute the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and always to reſiſt the lawe of the Ghoſpell, to mayntayne theyr re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion Pompilian.</p>
            <p>Thus we maye conclude, that du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb facs="tcp:25622:43"/>
the ſpace of 400 yeres, the Romain churche of Emperours and Senatours hath euer bene contrarye and enemies to the lawe of Ieſus Chriſt. Than af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward (the occidentall Empyre be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ouerthrowen) Rome and all Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye was ruled and gouerned 300 yeres or there aboute, by Kynges, Prynces, and Dukes, Idolators and Infidels, namely by the Wandales, by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, by the Hunnes, by the Oſtrogo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes, by the Viſigothes, and by the Lumbards, in ſuch ſorte, that duryng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpace of 700 yeres or there aboute, after the incarnation of Ieſus Chriſt, there was no Emperour, King, nor prince, of Rome, which woulde embrace the law of Ieſus Chriſt. The which gladly and ſhortly I haue declared, to the ende that the reader thynke it not ſtraunge, that I haue here ſhewed the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, to haue taken hys beginning of the auncient religion inſtituted by Neuma Pompilius, moore then 700 yeres before the incarnation of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:44"/>And ſo afterwarde alſo the ſame ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice hath bene continued by the Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Romains inueterate &amp; hardened ſo in their Pompilian religion, that thei would neuer put away the ſame.</p>
            <p>But to the ende that nothing in the Romayne hiſtories be kept cloſe which might obſcure the clearenes of the veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, during the tyranye &amp; vſurping of the nations aforeſayd,<note place="margin">In the yere of chriſt. 572.</note> in Italy was ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted a lytle Lordſhip at Rauenna, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che continued about 183 yeres,<note place="margin">Plantin. Blond. Volatteran.</note> vntyll it was rauiſhed by a biſhop, which inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted him ſelfe and encroiched into the chayre of S. Peter by the meanes of a donation and dimiſſion practiſed by Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pin in the yere 758, in recompence of a tyranny exerciſed by Zacharie Grec. bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome,<note place="margin">Paul. Emul. 2. Blond. lib. 10.</note> who ſpoyled the true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritours of the crown of Fraunce, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely Chilperic, or Childeric, whome he ſhut vp in a Cloyſter, to make the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to fall to the ſaid Pipin, the ſonne of Charles Martell baſtarde. This do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Pipin thus geuen to the great
<pb facs="tcp:25622:44"/>
Romaine biſhop, was the firſt originall of the greatnes of the Popes of Rome, who do holde vnto this daye the Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Rauenna (800 yeres beyng paſt) with a great number of townes a long the Sea Hadriatick,<note place="margin">Blond. lib. 1. Paul. Emul. 2.</note> committed vnto them by Pepin contrary to the expreſſe commaundements of Conſtantin than raignynge Emperour of the Eaſt in Grecia.</p>
            <p>Whyles this lytle lordſhip was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued at Rauenna,<note place="margin">The yere of chriſt. 588.</note> longe tyme before the donation of Pepin, the biſhoppe of that place ſeing that there were no more Emperours of Rome (which was go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerned and kepte vnder by barbarous people and Infidels) lift vp his hornes in ſuch ſorte that he preferred hymſelfe to be biſhop of Rome,<note place="margin">Sabellie.</note> &amp; made himſelfe the head of the Church, and alſo hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his ſucceſſours biſhops of Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenna, ſo long as the Lorſhip hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued. This was the firſt litle Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt which would take vpon him a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannye in the churche, to folowe the
<pb facs="tcp:25622:45"/>
earthly tyrannye of his Lordſhippe.</p>
            <p>Afterwarde there roſe vp another greater Antichriſt in Conſtantinoble,<note place="margin">In the yere of chriſt. 600. Blond. lib. 1.</note> named Iohn biſhop of that place: Who ſeing the occidentall Empyre of Rome ouerthrowen,<note place="margin">Greg. lib. 4. of his epiſtles, cap. 26.</note> and the other of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinople highly exalted, he would alſo fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the tyrrannye of the worlde, and ſtyrre vp a ſpirituall rule in the churche of Ieſus Chriſt. He cauſed himſelfe to be declared (by a counſell holden at hys pleaſure) biſhop Ecumenique,<note place="margin">the yere of chriſt 604.</note> that is to ſaye, generall and head of the whole churche.<note place="margin">Plantin. Sabellie.</note> But ſoone after the great Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome gaue ſuch order, that by treaſon the Emperour Maurice in Conſtantinople was cruelly ſlaine, he, his wife, and familie, by wicked Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas: who to recompence this deteſtable murder committed by the aduiſe of the Churche of Rome, alwayes contrarye to Ieſus Chriſt,<note place="margin">the yere of chriſt. 612.</note> he declared Boniface the thyrde of that name the generall head of the churche of God, takyng vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon hym the authoritie of Ieſus Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:25622:45"/>
the great and euerlaſtyng high Prieſt, the onely ſpouſe and head of his church. Who can better deſcribe an Antichriſt, than he that doth enterpriſe a tyrranny in the churche of God, a poligamie in the churche the ſpouſe of Ieſus Chriſt attributynge to hymſelfe that power,<note place="margin">Marc. 26.</note> whiche Ieſus Chriſt hath reſerued to himſelfe, to be perpetuall with his churche, by the vertue of hys holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite to conducte and gouerne the ſame? Maye not he rightlye be called Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſte whyche doeth enforce hym ſelfe directlye to goe agaynſte the holye Ghoſpell of Ieſus Chriſt, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded hys apoſtles (when he ſent them to preache hys worde) that they ſhoulde not inſtitute a Monarchie in the churche, as the Prynces, Kings,<note place="margin">Math. 23. Luc. 11. Marc. 2.</note> and tyrraunts of the earth? That none amonges them ſhoulde enterpriſe to call hym ſelfe the head or greater then other: but all as brethren were humble beynge aſſured to haue one head, and one heauenlye father,
<pb facs="tcp:25622:46"/>
which wyll tarye with them and aſſiſt them for euer, to inſpire and conduct them to his holy wyll. Is not he of good right Antichriſt, which wyll haue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf called the ſucceſſour of Ieſus Chriſt in the great biſhoprick, and in the high prieſthode by him exerciſed? The which dignitie he hath reſerued to himſelf, abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding a high ſoueraigne prieſt for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more: who hath left no ſucceſſour in his dignitie as Aaron did &amp; his ſucceſſors in the dignities of the high prieſts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wes: But is after the order of Melchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dech a king and high prieſt without any ſucceſſour in his dignitie. Wherefore then (O Antichriſts of Rome) haue you taken vppon you the dignitie of the higheſt biſhoppes as the heads of the church of God, and vſurped alſo the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie of Ieſus Chriſt, cauſing your ſelues to be called moſt bleſſed and moſt reuerend fathers and Popes, hauynge inſtituted a colledge of lytle purple bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes to choſe the great biſhoppe, but onely to the end to renewe the auncient
<pb facs="tcp:25622:46"/>
romaine religion of Neuma Pompili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, the firſt authour of your pontificall dignities.</p>
            <p>Aboute the ſame tyme that Phocas the cruell murtherer dyd erect an Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt in the romaine churche, Mahomet was ryſen in the church of Arabia, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed by the Monke Sergius, aboute the yere 620, for this apoſtate heretyke, ſeyng the lawe of God altogether cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by the traditions of men, and the holye Ghoſpell contemned, ſectes and diuers hereſies ſowed, as well by the Iewes, Phariſes, Eſſeens, Sadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Maſbutheans, Gallileans,<note place="margin">Seeke the church hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries.</note> Heme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robaptiſts, and Samaritans: as alſo by the Chriſtians, Simoniaques, Nico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laites, Cerinthiens, Memandriens, and Ebronites, Valentinians, Cardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians, Marcioniſtes, Montaniſtes, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphryges, Tatians, Eueratites, Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerians, Artemoniſtes, Porpherians, Helcheſaites, Nouatians, Sabellians, Chiliaſtes, Paulianiſtes, Maniche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Automouſiaſtes, Arians, Euno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,
<pb facs="tcp:25622:47"/>
Macedonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, Euuomiotheophro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niens, Euuomidentichiens, Aetians, Donatiſtes, Luciferiens, Patripaſſians or Theopathites, Photiniens, Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians, Pauloſamoſetans, Apolinariſtes, Iouinianiſtes, Pelagians, Acariens, Olimpiens Quaternitaries Monothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites. And other heritikes hauing corrup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted the true vſage of the holy Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, ordayned of god. Seyng alſo ſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Meſſalien ſecte to proſper in their ceremonies, taken partly out of the Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daicall laws, &amp; partly out of the heathen Idolatry he inuented the great Alcoran decree. Wherin he ſet manye Chapters and articles called Azoares, whiche are as lawes and rules of the Machomette religion.</p>
            <p>Thys preface and bryefe diſcourſe of the romayne Hiſtory, me thought neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to recite before I would beginne to diſcribe the originall of the ſacryfice of the Maſſe. Alwayes to brynge the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to vnderſtand the veritye of the fact, How the Empyre of Rome hathe bene
<pb facs="tcp:25622:47"/>
gouerned vntyll the decaye thereof, aboute the yere of Chriſt foure hundred and tenne, and howe the barbarous Idolatours dyd vſurpe the ſame, for the ſpace of three hundred yeres, howe alſo the Antichriſtes did ryſe, and in the ende, the Empyre of Rome was tranſferred to the Almaynes, whiche kéepe it to this day, fyue hundred yeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſſed.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb facs="tcp:25622:48"/>
               <head>OF THE Maſse.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O begynne this our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle treatiſe of the Maſſe, firſt of all it is conueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to interprete thys terme Maſſe,<note place="margin">The originall of the terme of the Maſſe.</note> of the aun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient Romaynes called <hi>Miſſa.</hi> Some haue honored this Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal ſacrifice to haue taken his beginning of the Hebrues, bringing in the place of Daniell ſpeaking of <hi>Maozin,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Daniell. 11.</note> as if they woulde ſignifie the Maſſe by <hi>Maozin.</hi> But this terme is verye ſtraunge from <hi>Miſſa,</hi> or Maſſe. And there is other He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewe wordes which are more nearer, to witte, <hi>Meſſa,</hi> whiche is as much to ſaye as conculcation or treading down, whereof mencion is made in the hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of the Kynges of Iſraell. Another terme alſo is founde,<note place="margin">4. Kings. 11. Miſſa.</note> very conformable vnto this common tearme Maſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:25622:48"/>
namely Meſſall, that is to ſaye,<note place="margin">Ioſ. 19. Meſſall.</note> hell or graue. But I am well aſſured that the high prieſts of Rome wyll not take the originall of their ſacrifice of the Maſſe from the Hebrues, acknowledgynge their Maſſe and Meſſall to be a concul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, graue, or hell.<note place="margin">Meſſal. Hell.</note> Further (to ſpeake the trueth) the Authour of the romaine religion Neuma Pompilius neuer thought of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Hebreus when he firſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe. Much leſſe terme this <hi>Miſſa</hi> or Maſſe can haue hys originall of the Greekes, ſeyng they haue no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice of that name, not withſtandyng that ſome haue made ſome reaſon to bryng in this terme of Greke <hi>Myzein,</hi> that is to ſaye in Engliſhe, to whyſper, or hyde in ſecrete. As if the Meſſalian ſacrificers had receyued of the auncient Gréekes Idolatours, to keepe ſecrete the chiefe and principall wordes of their Maſſes, to the ende they ſhoulde not be vnderſtand of thaſſiſtance, but haue ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued to murmour, &amp; blowe betwene their téeth the Canons, &amp; other ſpeciall
<pb facs="tcp:25622:49"/>
wordes, which neyther they vnderſtode them ſelues, nor other, whiche behelde them. Neuertheles, neither the Hebrue termes nor Greeke vocables in no wiſe can be appropriated to the Miſſall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. Wherefore it behoueth to haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to the trewe originall of the terme Miſſa or Maſſe taken of the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Latyns the Romaines,<note place="margin">Maſſe taken of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Latins Romains.</note> whiche were accuſtomed to vſe theſe termes, <hi>Miſſus, Miſſa, Miſsilis,</hi> and <hi>Miſsio.</hi> As we ſaye in Engliſhe a meſſenger, a meſſage, and miſſiues, for letters ſent. For when the auncient Idolaters Romaines woulde geue leaue vnto the aſſiſtaunce at their Sacrifices cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated to goe home, they cauſed to be pronounced in the ende of the Sacrifice theſe wordes.<note place="margin">Apud Graecos Sacerdos fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctus miſterio ſic renuncia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat: Laois apheſis qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> populu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum faceret.</note> 
                  <hi>I, licet, Miſſa eſt.</hi> Depart it is permitted the aſſemblye hath leaue to retyre or departe. And in proceſſe of tyme, for that thys ſonge dyd note vnto the people a licence to go home moſte agreable and deſyred, as a ſonge and terme moſt comfortable and pleaſaunt,
<pb facs="tcp:25622:49"/>
it hath bene kepte,<note place="margin">Apul. lib. 11. de aſin. a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and the ſacrifice ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured with this terme Maſſe or Miſſa. To confirme this poynt, there is two thouſande yeres paſte, and the ſame termes be ſonge yet vnto thys preſent daye, <hi>Ite Miſſa eſt,</hi> whiche doeth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie a leaue geuen to the companye or aſſemblye to departe and goe home.</p>
               <p>In ſuche ſorte that thoſe whiche doe haunte the temples or churches, as ſoone as they do vnderſtande this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaunt ſonge, <hi>Ite Miſſa eſt,</hi> a man maye ſee them ordinarelye to awake, &amp; leape for ioye, as beyng aſſured to haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence to go to dynner.</p>
               <p>The Arabian Machomiſtes inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of long tyme by the monke Sergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, as we haue declared, haue this terme of the Maſſe in great commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation,<note place="margin">In the booke of the diſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Affrick by Ihon Leon Affricain. Meſſa of the Turkes.</note> with which vocable they haue honoured three townes or Cities cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Meſſa ſituate vppon the mouthe of the Ocean, vppon the poynt whiche doeth make the begynnynge of the mounte Atlas.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:50"/>Nere vnto the ſame townes in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbes, there was a temple muche re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſed by the Idolatrous Turkes, for that they did beleue that in Meſſa ſhuld be borne the iuſt biſhop promiſed &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied by Machomet. They dyd beleue alſo that vppon the coaſte of the ſayde place of Meſſa, Ionas was caſt after he was ſwalowed vp of the Whale.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Meſſalamans. In the boke of the great turkes courte by frere An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tony Gueffrei</note>They haue alſo this name Meſſala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains in as great honour as we haue the name of Chriſtians. As if they woulde ſignifie by this vocable Meſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanian ſaued.</p>
               <p>Moreouer, the Mahomatiſts do ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour alſo their prieſts with the name of Maſſe,<note place="margin">in the booke aboue ſayde. Meſſen. Meſſit.</note> calling them Meſſen, and theyr temples Meſſit or Meſchit. Thoſe then which are inforced to bryng to lyght the Anotomy or diſcription of the Maſſe, the pieces, the groundes, the patches, &amp; encreaſements, oughte to deſcribe it with great reuerence, hauynge due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to the auncient religion Pompili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Alcoran of Mahomet.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:50"/>Nowe after that we haue reſolued the name of Maſſe, and of <hi>Miſſa,</hi> in the Latyne tongue,<note place="margin">Pontife. boke 1. of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries.</note> to haue taken her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the auncient romain Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours, &amp; not of the Greekes or Hebru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es. It behoueth vs to come to the gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Meſſalian ſacrificers. But in paſſing by we muſt not omit y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name Biſhoppe, to haue hys originall alſo of the Romaynes as we haue declared in our commentaries. Alſo the name Papa or Pope had his beginning of the auncient Idolatours, who were wonte to call vpon their God Iupiter calling him Papa Iupiter, ſpecially the Bithi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians and Scithes. The whiche name Pope is taken of the Greke worde Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus that is to ſaye great father. And alſo the very tytle written vppon all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtes preſented vnto the great Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mayne Biſhoppe, is moſte bleſſed fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to the leſſe purple Biſhoppes moſte reuerende father, and to the ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Biſhoppes reuerende father. Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge all this worde father or Papa, a
<pb facs="tcp:25622:51"/>
great father, which was wonte to be a common name for all biſhops. But af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward the great romaine biſhops did reſerue it for them ſelues onely. There is alſo another name reſerued for the litle biſhops, called curates, whiche are ſuperintendentes in euery lytle pariſhe, 2hauyng borowed this name Curate of the auncient Curions of Rome. If one will not deduce the etimologie or ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication of the ſame from the Greeke word Cura,<note place="margin">Cura. Curio, ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos, Cure, qui in ſua cura, id eſt in ſua par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochia ſacris praeerat. Tit Liu. lib. 1 Decad. 1.</note> that is ſhauing or polling, for that the auncient Curions &amp; Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers had their pollings &amp; head ſhauen after the forme of the Babilonians, or of the Herculians biſhops, called for the ſame cauſe Stephanophores, as bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a crown vpon their heads. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me thinketh that all the members of the miſſall ſacrifice had their begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Pompilion religion, &amp; that one ſhould do wrong vnto the auncient romain Idolators,<note place="margin">Tit. Liu. Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt. Pompo. Let.</note> if he ſhuld take from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the original of the names of Maſſe, of biſhop, &amp; of curate, as it is iuſtified and
<pb facs="tcp:25622:51"/>
euident by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auncient romain hiſtories. Touching the veſtiments of the Maſſe ſacrificers Neuma ordeyned y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhould be whyte, called by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Latin word Alba an aulbe. The which name aulbe hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinued to this day for the veſtiment of the prieſt celebrating Maſſe.<note place="margin">Aulbe. Alex. ab Alex. lib. 4. cap. 17. Super tunica<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aenea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pectori tegumen. Tit. lib. Deca. 1.</note> Aboue the aulbe was alſo ordeyned for the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer to weare a lytle Iacket paynted in colours. And aboue that an ornament for the breſt of braſſe or copper, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward chaunged into gold or ſiluer, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che the Maſſalians called a Cheaſuble,<note place="margin">Chaſuble.</note> they vſed alſo a vaile to couer their head in ſacrificing called an ammas firſt inſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuted by Eneas.<note place="margin">Virgil. lib. Ene. 3. pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o velare comas adoper tus amictu, fit capite ante aras phrigio velamus ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctu.</note> Theſe be the principal veſtiments inſtituted by Numa, more then 700 yeres before the incarnation of Ieſus Chriſt. True it is that afterward manye enrichementes of the Iewes were added thereto, as the Stole, the Ephod, the Zone, or Gyrdle, the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or Thear, and certayne other orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, the goodlyer to garnyſhe the great whore of Babilon.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:52"/>
                  <hi>But the Maſſalians wyllynge to diſguyſe the originall of their veſtements of the maſſe haue imagined the aulbe to fygure the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſation of Ieſu chriſt in his fleſhe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Titelman in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>racta. de ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſi. myniſte. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſſae. &amp; Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e Biel. in lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e expoſi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iſſae.</note> 
                  <hi>or the pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ritie of his bodye incarnate in the wombe of the virgyn. Other do interprete the whyte colour to ſygnifye chaſtitie and continence. Others playing and mocking the paſsion of Ieſu chriſt do ſophiſticallye ſygnifye by the aulbe, the whyte garment preſented by He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rode vnto chriſt when he was ſent backe (as a foole) to Pilate. Philo the Iewe a more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent philoſopher, in his treatiſe of dreames, doth ſubtelly ſay the aulbe doth ſygnifye the certentie of the moſte cleare lighte of god, which he calleth ens: the linnen alſo whereof the aulbe is made, thei do interprete the ſubtel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of the ſcriptures. And as touching the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas inuented by Eneas, they diſguyſe it to be the vayle wherwith chriſt was couered when the Iues in the houſe of caiphas did mock him in buffeting hym. Titelman one of the moſt ſubtel maſſalians doth ſophiſtically ſay by the ammas to be ſygnifyed the diuinitie of chriſt hid vnder the humanitie. Some other alſo do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fes the ammas to be come in, in place of the Ephod of the Iewes. The zone, the manipule and the ſtole, whiche be thre kyndes, they fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure the thre cordes wherewith chriſt was bonde and led before the prieſtes, and before
<pb facs="tcp:25622:52"/>
the lieutenaunts of the Romaines in Iewrye. Biel another ſubtell maſſalian doth interprete by zone the roddes wherewith chriſt was whipped, by the ſtole layed a croſſe, to ſygni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye the gibber or gallowes that chriſt cary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vppon his ſhulders. The manipule alſo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried vppon the left arme to fygure the bonde of loue wherewith chriſt was holden. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther mummerie by the zone wherewith the aulbe is truſſed to ſygnifye the bonde of the charitie of god. The ſtole put vppon the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas in the necke of the maſſalian in forme of the croſſe to fygure the obedience of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus chriſt vnto the death of the croſſe. The manipule caryed vpon the left hand to fygure eternall felicitie of Ieſus chriſt. Another ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiſtrie by the ammas to fygure fayth, by the ſtole the humilitie of obedience, by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipule, the watch and hartye deuotion of the maſſyng ſacrificer. Titelman doth ſurmyſe otherwyſe of the manipule on the left hand, to be fygured the force and battell of chriſt agaynſt all powers viſible and inuiſible, as a bockler againſt all temptations: and the hem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes of the manipule to fygure a fynall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeueraunce. He doth ſophiſt alſo by the left hand to be vnderſtande the humain infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of chriſt, the which bound with the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipule, doeth fygure chriſt holden as it were ouercome by the diuinitie. Brunus another
<pb facs="tcp:25622:53"/>
Maſſalian doctour doth imagin by the mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pule the care of the maſſyng prieſt to chaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way euill affections, or otherwyſe to fygure the cord wherwyth Chriſt was bound by the Iewes: by the Stoel, to be figured the yocke of the Lord, the which the Maſſalian ought to haue garniſhed with armes of righteouſnes on the left ſide &amp; on the right. The other pain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted ornament firſte inſtituted by Neuma the magician they haue diſguyſed it wyth the name of planet as a wauering veſtment, others wyſe called a cape or a chaſuble, whiche they doe ſophiſt to repreſent the purple to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented vnto chriſt in the iudgement hal of Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, to mocke him, calling him king of the Iewes. Another ſophiſtry by ſuch a garment to be figured the nature of chriſt, where the dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye was hid. Philo the Iue platoniſing, doth in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terprete by this veſtment decked with dyuers colours, to be figured the ſtarres &amp; heauenlye ſignes. Then the Maſſilia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſacrificer thus rigged with his aulbe, Ammas, his zone, manipule ſtarres, &amp; with his chaſuble or cape of diuers colors, muſt ſtretch out his armes, to play two perſonags at one, repreſenting by his chaſuble or cape (whereof the part before is leſſe then that behind) the firſt church fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Abel to chriſt. And by the part behind more large &amp; alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched with the ſigne of the croſſe to figure the chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> people. This chaſuble muſt accord
<pb facs="tcp:25622:53"/>
with the Ammas which was before vpon the bedde, to ſignifie the coniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ction of chriſt and his church. The aulbe alſo muſt be agreable to the chaſuble to ſignifie chriſt to be applyed vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to our infirmites. Beſide the veſtments aboue ſaid, Philo the Iue doth adde the mitre to figure the riall diademe of the maſſalians whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch ought to haue their heddes anoynted with creame,<note place="margin">Philo in lib. de profug.</note> or with holy oyle to ſignifye the prin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>celines of the prieſtes. The whych ornament of the mytte is nowe reſerued for the greate ſacryfycers onely.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yt reſtith to deſcend to the diſcription of the partes of the Maſſe, the originall wherof particularly we deſire according to the trueth. Fyrſt to the maſſes called high celebrated on Sondaies. The Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalian ſacryfycers, haue taken of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion Pompilian to coniure a clenſyng water called hollywater,<note place="margin">Apul. lib. 11. of the golden Aſſe. Proclus in li. de ſacrifi. &amp; Gag. Proel. Platoni ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>u.</note> conſecrated to ſprinkle the aſſyſtauntes at the ſacrifice. The comuration and enchaunting inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted by Neuma was of ſea or ſalt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, for thys cauſe ſayth he, that the ſalte was participant of a fyery nature, or of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er very apt to puryfye.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:54"/>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Eius aquae aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſione, pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cata, preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim periuria, mendatiaque dilui crede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant.</p>
                     <p>Blond. lib. de Rom. trium. Ouid lib.</p>
                     <p>Faſt 3. in the law of the diſcourſe the religion by Choul. i. Holy water ſtocks of two ſortes.</p>
                     <p>Diis ſuperis ſacra facturus corporis ablu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tione purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>batur: cum ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ro inferis li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum erat ſola aſperſio ſufficiebat.</p>
                     <p>Blond. lib. 2. de. Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. trium Macro. lib. 3. Satu. cap. 1. In Delii Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonis templo praecipua erat equa ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantium vſui accommoda quam ad ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os vſus hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſſe magni criminis in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtar erat. Alex. ab Alex. lib. 4 cap. 17.</p>
                     <p>Platine Si cinis vitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la aſperſus po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pulum iudae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum munde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat, multo ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gis aqua ſale conſperſa po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulum ſancti ficat &amp; inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dias diaboli auertit ca. aquam de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrat. di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. 1.</p>
                     <p>Law of god corrupted.</p>
                  </note>For this cauſe the aunciaunt Romain Idolatours did ſprynckle with thys ſalt water coniured (as with Mercury wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter) purging and cleanſyng the faultes of the people, ſpecially of periured and lyers. To conſerue this water halowed and coniured, they had two ſortes of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly water veſſels. The one great fixed and made faſt at the entrie of their tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, where they did worſhippe theyr Images: to the ende to ſprynckle with the ſame ſalted water thoſe which dyd enter into the ſayde temples. The other holy water veſſel was cariable, to tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porte of the ſame water through theyr temples or houſes: to the ende to water them for theyr cleanſings &amp; purifyings. They whiche oughte to celebrate the Maſſe, if it were to the inferiour gods, it was ſufficient that the ſacrificing prieſt did ſprynckle him ſelfe with the ſame purging water. But if the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer did celebrate Maſſe to the ſuperiour gods, he muſte bathe his whole bodye, and waſhe all hys members. It was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo
<pb facs="tcp:25622:54"/>
defended to apply this purging water to any other vſe, ſaue for clenſings and purginges. Alexander the firſte of that name: next ſucceſſour of the appoſtles of Ieſus chriſt. And one of the firſt corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours of the holy ſacramentes ordayned of god, folowing the ſame inſtitution of Pompilius contynued this Idolatry of coniuring and conſecrating of holye water, to chaſe away diuills. But the better to colour this Pompilian witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft he inuented this compariſon. Yf it be ſo (ſaith Alexander) that the aſhes of a redd cowe offered vp in ſacrifice ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with water of the fountaine pury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied the people of the Iues. By muche greater reaſon the water coniured with ſalt ſhoulde purifie chriſtians &amp; chaſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waye diuills. Is not this a breakinge &amp; corrupting of the holy lawe of god, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord with the Romaines taughte in the auncient doctrine and religion of Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Pompilius the coniurer. Yf Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander had not beene ſo much geuen to the vſe of ſalt, inſtituted by the auncient
<pb facs="tcp:25622:55"/>
Idolatours for their clenſing water, he would rather haue followed the iudai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call ceremony,<note place="margin">Num. 19.</note> and haue ordayned aſhes to conſecrate the purgynge water. And where he would thynke to vyſer his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng by the miracle of Elizeus which did puryfie the water with ſalte.<note place="margin">4. Kyngs. 2.</note> Moyſes al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo dyd the lyke wyth the woode ſhowed vnto hym, when the people of Iſraell were in ſuche neceſſitie of ſwete water to drinke.<note place="margin">Exod. 15.</note> But by theſe myracles it is not recited that Elizeus nor Moiſes had inſtituted a purgynge water to puryfye the people of the Iewes. And it ſhal not be founde, that there was at anye tyme amongs the iudaicall ceremonies any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purging water, but with the aſhes of the beaſt offred vp for burnt ſacrifyce.<note place="margin">Num. 19.</note> Wherfore Alexander and his like muſt fréelye acknowledge the inuention of their Salte and coniured water for the purginge of ſynnes, to haue taken hys originall of Neuma Pompilius, more then. 700. yeares before the incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:55"/>This purging water was ſo well obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued of the Romayne Idolatours,<note place="margin">Hiſto. tripart. lib. 6. cap. 35.</note> that more than. 360. yeares after the incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ieſus Chriſt, it is recited howe the Emperour Valentinian entryng in-into the temple of the goddeſſe fortune,<note place="margin">Valentinian the emperour againſt holy water ſprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keled.</note> a ſacrifycer watchyng the ſayd Temple dyd ſprinkle him with thys bleſſed pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyng ſalted water, whiche he had taken out of the holly water ſtocke beynge at the entraunce of the ſaid temple, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyth the Emperour beynge chauffed ſmote the Pryeſt holdyng the holly wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſtycke, ſaying he was rather defyled then puryfyed. By theſe true Hiſtories the Maſſalians may vaunt themſelues, the firſt part of their Maſſe ſacrifice to be very auncient. And that their holywater ſtockes,<note place="margin">Holy vvater very auncie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</note> &amp; ſalted clenſing &amp; purging wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, are of the auncient doctrine of Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma pompilius &amp; not of the Euangelicall doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt, whyche they call new doctrine, &amp; new Teſtament, as diffring from the auncient Ceremonies of the Iewes and Panyms Idolatours.
<pb facs="tcp:25622:56"/>
But againe I cannot meruell inough, wherefore Alexander did enterpriſe the reſtoring of the Pompilion Idolatrye,<note place="margin">Againſt ſalt holy water of Alexander pope of rome</note> ſeing he had a meane to reinſtitute the ceremoniall water after the faſhion of the Iues. And this doing to followe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the law of god then Neuma Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilius, for he had eaſye meanes to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer aſhes to make a purging water af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the maner of the Iues: namely of ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly and precious aſhes, to ſay of the aſhes kept in their ſhrienes, and comming of courtaines Towells &amp; veſſels conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,<note place="margin">Ca. Omnes de conſecrat. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. 4. &amp; ca. Altaria. &amp; ca. Veſtimenta. deſtinct. 1.</note> which the byſhop Cleament prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſour of Alexander had forbidden to be applyed to any prophane vſe. But being worne with oldnes, to be burned in the fyer. And the aſhes to be put into the Fount. Were not theſe holye aſhes, to haue moued Alexander to reſtoore the aſhye and purginge water after the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the Iues, if he had not beene ſo denty of ſalt and found a better taſte, to continue the auncient Romain religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Other aſhes might haue ben found
<pb facs="tcp:25622:56"/>
by the ſucceſſours of Alexander: To witte,<note place="margin">Ca. Altaria de conſecrat. diſtinct.</note> of the rounde hoſtes vnleuened &amp; conſecrated, which the great biſhop Higinus ordeyned to be burned (which falling vpon the earth might not be left for the maſſing ſacrificer) and the aſhes of the ſame hoſtes to be put into the ſhri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. Other aſhes alſo might haue bene gotten of the rattes, myce, and other beaſts deuouring the ſayde conſecrated hoſtes, and ordeyned to be burned,<note place="margin">In lib. cantel. Miſſ.</note> and the aſhes to be put into the ſhrynes.</p>
               <p>Seing then that Alexander woulde not followe the ceremoniall lawe of God, to ordeyne a water bleſſed, ſalted, conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated and coniured: Why did he not at the leaſt put his ſalte in the hoſte of the Maſſalian ſacrificer,<note place="margin">Leuit. 2.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> which they ſaye is offered to God as a health ſacrifice? In doing whereof he ſhoulde haue folowed the ceremonie of Moyſes, by the whiche he commaunded y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſalt ſhould be offered in all ſacrifices, &amp; therw<hi rend="sup">t</hi> to ſprinckle the ſacrifice offered for health. But if Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander and his ſucceſſours woulde haue
<pb facs="tcp:25622:57"/>
folowed the lawe of God, they woulde haue inuented nothing of their owne braynes, they would neuer haue made them ſelues ſo renowmed to haue lefte the memorie of their inſtitutions.<note place="margin">The occation of inuenting newe idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</note> For this occaſion they would in nothing fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe the lawe of God, but contrarywiſe haue forbidden to put ſalt into the rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hoſtes conſecrated to celebrate the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall ſacrifices. They haue forbidden alſo to put aſhes into their holy water, to the ende that in all their inſtitutions, men ſhuld know, that they borow nothing of the law of God, nor of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of Moyſes, much leſſe of the euangelical law of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus chriſt, but only haue taken thought to bring in inuentions, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that they were inuented by thaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Painims and Romain Idolators 700 yeres before the incarnation of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt. To finiſhe thys fyrſt parte of the Maſſe: it had bene more expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent (O Maſſalians) that in place of your ſacrifices, and coniured ſalt wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, wherewith you ſprinkle the people
<pb facs="tcp:25622:57"/>
to haue clearely declared the holy ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, cauſing the people to vnderſtande,<note place="margin">The true ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly water of al chriſtians.</note> that the purifying and waſhing of their ſinnes, did hang onely on the bloode of Ieſus Chriſt, who is ſtrong inough to driue awaye diuelles, to bring vs from hell,<note place="margin">Hebre. 9.</note> to preſerue vs from death euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and to deface in vs all ſpottes of ſynne, withoute vſing of adiurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and coniurynge with ſalte, to driue awaye Diuelles, accordynge to the Witchecrafte of Pompilius, and the hereſie of the Samaritains,<note place="margin">Epipha. lib 1. tom. 1. ſec. 9 &amp; 17. conte. haec.</note> which dyd beleue to be purified by waſhyng them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues euery day with holy water.</p>
               <p>After the Aſperges ſong,<note place="margin">2. part of the maſſe.</note> and the holy coniured water ſprinkeled vpon all the aulters, Images, and aſſiſtaunce at the miſſall ſacrifice,<note place="margin">Proceſsion.</note> followed the Proceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whyche ſome woulde attribute to Agapet Byſhoppe of Rome.<note place="margin">Platine</note> But it was inſtituted moore than a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande yeares before hym:<note place="margin">Tit. Liuius in his decades.</note> whyche the auncient Romayne Idolatours did call Supplication.</p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Chi Rho and Alpha and Omega</figDesc>
               </figure>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:60"/>But in place of painting there the name of Ieſus Chriſt they haue painted the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages and likneſſes of diuers gods and godeſſes he ſaincts &amp; ſhe ſaincts patrons of euery pariſhe. This in ſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>me is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Miſſall proceſſion, for the ſecond part of the Maſſe. Was there e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſo great Idolatry emongs the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites, when they woulde celebrate their feaſts of ſweat bread, to eate the paſchall lambe a figure of the holye ſacrament of of the ſupper, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſalians haue diſguiſed by their ſacrifices of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe? dyd they euer cauſe to be carryed in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion the fleſh &amp; bloud of the vnſpotted lambe? Did they euer lay it vp in ſhriene to be caryed in proceſſion throughte the ſtreates? The braſen ſerpent (notwyth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandinge they abuſed it) dyd they euer cauſe it to be borne in a ſhryne vpon the ſhulders of the prieſtes which had theyr heades and beards ſhauen.<note place="margin">In the yere of Chriſt. 1264.</note> As the great byſhop Vrbain did ordain to carry in pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſion the conſecrated hoſt by the maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians. And inſtituted a ſolempne feaſt a
<pb facs="tcp:25622:60"/>
thurſday euery yeare, to thende to turne the vſe of the ſacrament into a more dete<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtable idolatry, then al his predeceſſours had done before him? After the ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling or holy water, &amp; the proceſſion done Neuma ordained that the Maſſing ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ficer to celebrate the ſacrifice,<note place="margin">3. part of the maſſe, are the aulter, taper and lyght.</note> being clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his aulbe, &amp; chaſuble or tunicle painted, the head crowned, &amp; beard ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſhuld approch to the alter, to the end to make all things ready for the ſacrifice furniſhed with a Lampe or Taper light which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly was of Tede or pinapole tree.<note place="margin">Ouid. lib. 4 de faſt. Apul. lib. 11. de aſin. aur. Plutar in Neuma.</note> For without an alter &amp; fier no ſacri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fice could be celebrated. He ordained alſo that the maſſing prieſt ſhuld turne hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf to the alter toward y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eaſt. Porphier the hereticke did not only continue this Pompilius witchraſt but alſo did ordain the porches &amp; thimmages to be tourned toward the Eaſt, to the end y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thoſe that entred into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temples in bowing them<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelues before them ſhould addreſſe theyr praiers toward the Eaſt,<note place="margin">Alex. ab Alex. lib. 4. cap. 17</note> like as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians doe worſhip the ſunne in the eaſt.
<pb facs="tcp:25622:61"/>
Be not theſe inſtitutions Maſſalians and Pompilions contrary to the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent ceremoniall lawe of the Iewes, in the whiche it was forbidden to addreſſe prayers towarde the Eaſt, for a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence from the auncient Idolators.</p>
               <p>Acknowledge then (O Maſſalians) that the erection of your aulters toward the Eaſt,<note place="margin">Exod. 20. Leuit. 26. Deut. 5. Eſay. 40.</note> your lampes and tapers lyght, your pictures &amp; Images reuerenſed in your miſſall ſacrifices to haue taken their beginninge of the auncient Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main religion appoynted by you from one to another. For the pictures &amp; ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges wherewith your aulters be decked and adorned to celebrate your miſſall ſacrifices, can not take theyr originall of the law of God, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which doth not forbid onely the ſufferynge of any Images in the churches, but alſo to make them, and reuerence them. Vnto whome can God be made lyke? What Image, picture, or what portrature can be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uented for hym? Neuertheleſſe, by a moſte deteſtable and abhominable
<pb facs="tcp:25622:61"/>
heriſie,<note place="margin">Abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble idolatrie</note> you (O Maſſalians) haue cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Image and likeneſſe of the Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie one God and three perſons to be prynted in your rounde hooſtes whyche you cauſe to be worſhipped.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neuertheleſſe the two doctours Maſſalians Titelman and Biell interprete the aulter o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwyſe, when the maſſyng prieſt doeth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche laden with his chaliſe of golde to fy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure Chriſt carying the croſſe vnto the moun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tayne of Caluery, then the prieſt kyſſyng the aulter to fygure the marriage and weddyng ſynge of chriſt with hys churche. The right hand of the aulter to fygure the people of the Iewes, and the left hande the people of the Gentiles.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Durand. lib. rubr. de m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tat.</note> 
                  <hi>For this cauſe Durand a ſubtel maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalian hath written, that the miſſall memorie oughte to beginne at the right hande of the aulter, and on the ſame part to ende. And yet notwithſtanding the principal aperies are cele<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>brated at the left hand of the aulter. Touchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the fyer and lyghted taper, they fygure chriſt: as beyng the fyer that conſumeth the ruſt of our ſynnes, or otherwyſe the fyer of charitie compaſſing aboute the chriſtian people, and the bournyng taper to ſygnifie the lyght of fayth, the ioyes to come, and the incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:62"/>
                  <hi>Be not theſe deteſtable ſophiſtries, the which Neuma the Sorcerer neuer thought of, when he inſtituted the aulter, the fyer, and the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning taper to ſacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">4. part of the Maſſe.</note>To continue the order of the miſſall ſacrifice, the Maſſalian prieſt approching to the aulter, the taper burning and cled and adorned with his aulbe and chaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble tourning his face toward the Eaſt, beholding the Images gilt and carued, before all thyngs muſt ſay hys <hi>Confiteor</hi> and confeſſe him ſelf,<note place="margin">Confiteor.</note> in acknowledging hys offences,<note place="margin">Rem diuina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facturus ad ſuam leuan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam culpam ſe inprimis rerum dicere debebat &amp; noxae penite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re ac fateri admiſſum, vultu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittere. Alex. ab Alex, lib. 4. cap. 17 Blond. lib. 1. de Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. trium.</note> and aſke pardon of the gods and goddeſſes, of the he ſaincts and ſhe ſaincts, requiring iuſt and reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble things. As Pythagoras doth ſaye in his golden verſes, and Orpheus in hys hymnes, for Neuma the Sorcerer eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the conſcience of the Prieſt maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian to be well purged by hys confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. And that without Confiteor the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice coulde not be well celebrated.</p>
               <p>Beholde than, neyther Damaze nor Pontiam Byſhoppes of Rome, can not geue the glorye to themſelues that they
<pb facs="tcp:25622:62"/>
firſt inſtituted the <hi>Confiteor,</hi> For the Maſſalian ſacrificer: for more than a thouſande yeres before them, it was forged by the auncient Romain Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. And yet is continued to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day, that the prieſtes celebratinge their miſſall ſacrifice ſhall pronounce or murmour a <hi>Confiteor,</hi> in a language neyther vnderſtande of them, nor of the aſſiſtaunts, addreſſing their praiers and requeſtes vnto the gods and goddeſſes, to the he ſaincts and ſhe ſaincts, in place of reuerenſing, honouring, praying, &amp; worſhipping the true, onely and almigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tye God, creator of all goodnes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neuertheleſſe, the Alcoran of Titelman doth interprete the Confiteor of the Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian to ſignifye the confeſsion of chriſt for the ſynnes of the people.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 9.</note>
               </p>
               <p>After the <hi>Confiteor</hi> murmured to ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſerue the religion and ceremonies of Pompilius,<note place="margin">5. part of the maſſe.</note> the maſſyng prieſt ought to toſſe and retoſſe, tourne and retourne,<note place="margin">Turnings &amp; beckings.</note> along the aulter: Liftyng vp his hands,
<pb facs="tcp:25622:63"/>
than letting them downe?<note place="margin">Hae ſunt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>igines in ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tis a Numa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſtitutae dex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eram ad oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ulum ferre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſe in orbe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ircumagere. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lond. lib. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. trium. Macro. in Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>urnali.</note> with prayers and meditations towarde the Eaſt. For Neuma the ſorcerer, had an opinion of great holines to be in theſe tournynges bowings &amp; conuerſions of the prieſts bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. This is the occation (as a man maye coniecture) of the adding to of this plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſong at the enterance of the Maſſe, when the ſacrifycer begynneth to make his noddes, &amp; tournes, I will enter (ſaith he) vnto the Alter of god which maketh my youth to reioyſe.<note place="margin">The entrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the maſſe.</note> Hath he not iuſte cauſe of reioyſing ſeyng the Table cloth layed, the Table furniſhed, the bancket prepared the Muſick of orgaines, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inſtruments ſonding, the odors and encenſing, the cup full of wine, the colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion ready, the pot and offring to fyll hys purſe? Be not al theſe meanes to reioice the youth of the ſacrificer, entringe vnto the alter, to maſſe, turne, &amp; daunce after the maner preſcribed vnto him by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gician Numa Pompilius?<note place="margin">Plin. lib. 28.</note> And not one<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly the Romaynes, but alſo the other Ido<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>latours in celebratynge their ſacrifyces
<pb facs="tcp:25622:63"/>
were wont to tourne, and retourne, lyf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting vp the right hand vnto their mouth then tournyng all their body, the whych turnynges and noddings were accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted holye.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Titelman in hys alcoran doth reſite that the maſſing ſacrificer in making his trauerſinge a long the aulter, doth make .7. courteſies or ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutations vnto the aſſyſtaunce in his ſacrifice. To the end to chaſe away the .7. deadly ſinnes by the ſeuenfold grace of the holy ghoſt. but in making his .7, courteſies in his Maſſe dance, he ought to tourne hymſelfe toward the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce (except before the preface, and kiſſing the paxe) what time he is occupied in the brea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king of the round hooſt, to tranſubſtanciat him into an accidence without a ſubſtaunce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe beckynges bowynges,<note place="margin">6. part of the maſſe. Organes.</note> tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nynges, and towynges fyniſhed by the Maſſalian ſacryfycer, Numa ordayned the ſounde of Orgaynes, flutes, and Vyolles, to ſynge hymnes, prayſes, and ſonges, to the honour of their goddes in the name of whome, the Myſſall ſacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyce was celebrated.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:64"/>This part of the Maſſe hath bene enry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched wyth diuers ſonges, by diuers by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes of Rome. Some as Flaman &amp; Diodore did inſtitute Anthemes The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſphore,<note place="margin">Antiphones.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Collectes.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Collects: Leon or Gelaſe the Graduels,<note place="margin">Graduels.</note> Gregory or Gelaſe, the Traic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes,<note place="margin">Sequences.</note> Gothgere abbot of Sandall, the Se<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quenſes. Whiche are diuers ſonges of muſicke ſeruing to adorne &amp; enriche the miſſall ſacrifice. But if the commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the auncient Romaines biſhops inſtituted by Neuma were diſcouered,<note place="margin">Hymnorum plures ſpecies erant, hypin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gos Dianae, Apollini pean &amp; proſoedia Dioniſio di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiranibus, Cereri iulus: Veneri eroti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus: praeter quos fuere proſoedion, hyporchema, &amp; ſtafimon. Alex. ab Alex. lib. 4. cap. 17.</note> much greater deuerſitie, of ſongs ballets hymnes, odes &amp; cantiles, ſhuld be found dedicated and conſecrated to diuers gods &amp; goddeſſes. euen like as the diuerſitie of diuers ſonges of muſicke hath increaſed according to the diuerſitie of diuers Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall ſacrifices ordayned to dyuers gods &amp; goddeſſes he ſainctes and ſhe ſainctes. For like as the auncient Idolatours did celebrate their ſacrifices to dyuers gods &amp; goddeſſes. So the Maſſalians conty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued the celebration of their Maſſes to dyuers he and ſhe ſainctes, One in the
<pb facs="tcp:25622:64"/>
name of our lady, another in the name of Sainct Sebeſtian,<note place="margin">Diuers maſſes</note> other of the holye ghoſt &amp; other of Requiem,<note place="margin">Drye maſſes.</note> in ſo much y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they made a difference betewene drye Maſſes &amp; other common Maſſes, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they made the ſoppe ſtieped in wyne. In ſuch ſort that therof came an infinite number of Miſſal ſacrifices vnto diuers he and ſhe ſainctes. Vnto the whiche were ſonge diuers ſonges and ſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Be not theſe horrible and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable corruptions of the holy ſacrament of the ſupper of Ieſus Chriſt, thereof hauing made an Idolatrie after the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of the auncient ſacrifices inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the coniurer Neuma? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Biſhoppe Vitalian ought not to glorifie him ſelfe that he enriched the ſacrifice of the Maſſe with the ſounde of Organs. For more then 1200 yeres be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him this inſtitution was publiſhed by the Magician Neuma.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But to ſtuffe this babilonicall ſacrifyce, the maſſalian Alcoraniſts haue interpreted the di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uerſitie of their muſicall ſonges, by a pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goricall,
<pb facs="tcp:25622:65"/>
philoſophie. Touching the collectes, that is to ſaye, the patched praiers they haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, that they ſhalbe ſonge in number odde, to wit, 3, 5, or .7. the .3. to figure the trinite the .5. to repreſent the fyue woundes of chriſt, the .7. to figure the .7. wordes of chriſt vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſe, or elles the .7. giftes of the holy ghoſt. Moreouer for a more ſubtill pithagoricall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinitie, the Maſſeſayer oughte not to paſſe the number of .7. by the ordinance of pope Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent the third of that name: the ſophiſt Biel in his alcoran of the interpretation of the Maſſe, doth adde that the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of the collects ſhuld be equall to the praiers of the ſecrets, that is to ſay praiers of the Maſſemonger murmured in ſecret to the end they be not contempned of the people. After the collects is the ſong of the graduell more ſharpe &amp; graue a figure of the confeſsion of the publicans hauing heard the preaching of Iohn baptiſt. Notwythſtandyng the ſong of the graduell was not ſong in the Miſſall ſacrifices from Eaſter vnto the feaſte of penticoſt, to figure the bleſsed eſtate of the world to come.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Further beſyde the ſounde of orgay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,<note place="margin">7. part of the maſſe.</note> and ſonges of Muſick the auncient Romaynes Idolatours were wonte to
<pb facs="tcp:25622:65"/>
vſe in their ſacrifices parfume of encens whiche they cauſed to be keepte in a lyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle veſſell called Acerra a cenſour.<note place="margin">Perfume of encence.</note> In this litle Frankenſens coffer were put the odours whych the ſacerficer did take to encence the Aulter, the Images,<note place="margin">Blond. lib. 1. de Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. trium. Alex. ab Alex. lib. 4. cap. 17. iliacis tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus veteres non thu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, ſed cedri, &amp; citri fumo deos adolebant. Platine</note> the hooſtes or ſacrifices ſpecially in the Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes celebrated vnto the god Ianus, and vnto the goddeſſe Veſta, whyche toke pleaſure in encence &amp; wine offered vnto them. For in the time of the Troians, in ſtead of encence, cedre and Citron were vſed for parfume. It was not then Leo biſhop of Rome that firſt inſtituted the vſe of encence and encenſing in the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall ſacrifice. For more then .700. yeares before the incarnation of Ieſu Chriſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> auncient Romain Idolatours dyd vſe encence in their ſacrifices.<note place="margin">Tit. Liui. lib. 3 Decades. 3.</note> And alſo the Romaines did retayn the word in latin. <hi>Thus,</hi> which ſignifieth encence, of the auncient word <hi>Thyo,</hi> that is to ſay I ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, bycauſe the Idolatours did vſe in all their ſacrifices encence,<note place="margin">Tit. Liui. lib. 9. Decad. 3.</note> they had alſo a portable encenſor to encence wythall.
<pb facs="tcp:25622:66"/>
Neuertheleſſe, ſome wryte that the auncient Romaine Idolators celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting theyr ſacrifices vnto the Goddeſſe Ceres vſed the gumme of Pyne called Tede,<note place="margin">Ouid. de faſt. lib. 3.</note> in ſtede of encence, for whyche cauſe Ceres was called of the Poetes Tedifere.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By the Alcoram of Titelman, the encenſe is interpreted the prayer of the Maſſalian, for that it doeth mounte vp into heauen in a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of ſweteneſſe, euen as the ſmoke of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence doth riſe vp on heyght. He doth ſophiſt alſo with Biel his companion, the cenſour to fygure the grace of the holy ghoſt. Theſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tell Alcoraniſts alledge the place of Tobie, who chaſed away the deuyll by the perfume of the broyled lyuer. The ſame Biel interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth otherwyſe, the encenſe to fygure Mary Magdalenes annoynting of chriſt, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe chriſt was twyſe annoynted, the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe muſte be alſo offered twyſe in the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall ſacrifice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">8. part of the maſſe. Plin. lib. 1. cap. 3. Offertorie.</note>For another parte of the miſſall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice celebrated by the auncient Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lators, was the Offertorie, of the fyrſt fruictes offered, to the honour of the
<pb facs="tcp:25622:66"/>
gods in the name of whom the ſacrifice was celebrated. This Offertorie was for the maſſinge ſacrificer, whiche he might frely carye into hys owne houſe, for the nouriſhement of him ſelfe and his familie: notwithſtanding there wer other offeryngs diſtributed to thoſe that wer nedefull. After by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> couetouſnes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſalians, this vſage was chaunged into an offertorie or offering of ſiluer or golde to enriche the coffer, which ſome woulde haue attributed to Leo biſhop of Rome,<note place="margin">Platine</note> notwithſtandinge that the Offertorie was practiſed moore then a thouſande yeres before him. And to the ende to iuſtifie this by the Romaine hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories: When Neuma had inſtituted the Miniſters of the religion, as Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Augures, Sauliens, Feciaux, Curions and others,<note place="margin">Blond. lib 2. de Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. trium.</note> he ordeyned alſo the meanes howe to nouriſh and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne them, he commaunded to make of the common reuenues foundations, for the nouriſhment and maintenance of the religions Veſtales. Folowinge
<pb facs="tcp:25622:67"/>
his example manye particuler perſons did the lyke.<note place="margin">Sacerdotioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſiue benefici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum duo erant genera, vnum quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> collatio ad rep. aut prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipem aut ad pontificum collegium ſpectabat: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> collatio ad aliquam fami<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liam eiuſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſucceſſores pertinebat, quae beneficia vitis patrona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus cenſeban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Blond. lib. 2. de Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> trium. A diſpence for many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices. Tit. Liuiuius lib. 30. The foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices. Vacations &amp; ſetting ouer Offertorie. Tertia ſacer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> opu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenta, a ſoluti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>onibus inue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niebat, quas inferiores ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioribꝰ pon<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tificibus im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendebant quale apud nos eſt cum pontifici ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mano fructus primos anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtites &amp; his minores ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes ad obtinuenda beneficia pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuniam diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoluunt. Biond. lib. 2. de Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. trium. Cicero in ora<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tione pro do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ſua ad pontifices Blond. lib. 3. de Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. trium.</note> So that benefices became riche by foundations. The ſame bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices were of two ſortes. The one at the preſentation &amp; beſtowing of the prynce, or of the comon welth or of the colledge of biſhops. The other were at the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of ſome particuler patrons of the ſayde benefices, by whome they were founded and endowed with great riches. Of the whiche benefices the great biſhoppes of Rome haue vſurped authoritie to geue diſpenſation to haue two at once, euen as it is recited in the hiſtorie of Liuie, of Fabius Maximus, who had by diſpence two benefices than when he was created biſhop, more then two hundred yeres before the incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ieſus Chriſt. This was then firſt reuenewe of the Maſſalian ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers to haue benefices rychely foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. The ſeconde reuenewe was the Offertorie, or offerynge, the Offertory and oblations. The thyrde reuenewe was the vocations and the firſt fruicts,
<pb facs="tcp:25622:67"/>
whiche the Idolatrous Romaine Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes were accuſtomed to take, for the vacation of the benefices whyche they gaue, ſolde, or diſpenſed with.</p>
               <p>The fourthe reuenewe was deathes, annualls, legacies, and bequeſtes ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to pray vnto their gods for the ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les of the departed. The whiche is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified this daye by the monuments and tombes of the auncient Idolatours.</p>
               <p>The firſt reuenew was amerciaments, condemnations and confications leuied by the biſhops of Rome: as the place &amp; houſe of Cicero (when he was baniſhed) wer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fiſcate to the colledge of the prie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſts, &amp; dedicated ſpecially to the ſacrifices celebrated in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> temple co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated to the goddeſſe Libertie. Paſſing by I thought good to recite this ſumme of thauncient romain ſacrificers, to the end that vnto all it maye be knowen, that all the abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Idolatries, ſucceded in the churche of Ieſus Chriſt are not newe: But had theyr originall reſtored &amp; ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the auncient romaine Idolators:
<pb facs="tcp:25622:68"/>
As the foundations of Maſſes, Obites, Mounthmindes the diſpenſing of many benefices, annalls, vaccantes, tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlations, offeringes &amp; Maſſe boxe, amer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cementes and confiſcations, adiudged by the ſentence of the biſhop of Rome, as are alſo other ordinances reſtored by the new Romain Biſhops &amp; continued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the one to the other.<note place="margin">The yere of our lord. 383. Blond. lib. 2. de Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. trium.</note> To this porpoſe it is recited in the Romain hiſtories that ſynce the raign of the Emperour Valen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tinian the .xii. of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> name, great ſedition happened at Rome betwen y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chriſtians, &amp; the Idolatours prieſts whych ſtryued amongs themſelues, whether had more enriched the church by fundations, laga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, bequeſts, offerings &amp; other inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: in ſuch ſort that the heathen Idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tours &amp; infidels which did vſurpe again the temple preſently called the church of S. Peter at Lians, did fight againſt the chriſtians of Rome which would haue dedicated the ſame to their deuotion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>After the offertorie the Aleoran of Titleman doth hold that the maſſe monger muſt for a time kepe ſilence,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>to figure the fliyng of chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:25622:68"/>
or feare of the diſciples to confeſſe him before the Iewes. Then after the ſacrificer doth ſinge on hygh Per omnia ſecula ſeculorum for thys that chriſt after that he was in ſecret did ſhovv himſelf openly in the houſe of Lazarus, Then he ſyngeth ſanctus ſanctus ſanctus: to ſygnifie the ſong of the Iues whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt entred into Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This muſyke ended the ſacrificer muſt ſecretly murmur, betwene his teath, counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting ſadnes without anye tourninges, but yet he muſte playe a domme mommerie by ſygnes of croſſes drawen here awaies &amp; there awaies as we ſhall hereafter declare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>After the offertorie we muſt come to the ix. part of the Maſſe,<note place="margin">9. part of the Maſſe the round hoſt of floure. Plutar in Numa.</note> the moſt ryche &amp; moſt dentie for the Maſſalians. That is the hoſte or ſacryfyce. Wherein dothe conſiſt the principall end or marke of the maſſe ſacrifice.<note place="margin">Pollux in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom. lib. 6. Myſteriis per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actis, qui ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cris interera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, rotundis pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibꝰ, quos in honorem deo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rum adhib e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant ſtantes reſceban<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur nec niſi ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio perfecto veſci licebat. Alex. ab Alex. lib. 4. cap. 17</note> In the time of the coniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer Numa the Romaines had not yet in vſe to kill &amp; offer vp the bloud of beaſtes But aboute the ende of the Maſſe ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, it was ordained to eate and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate togither wythin the temple lytle round Cakes conſecrated to the honour of the gods in whoſe name y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe was
<pb facs="tcp:25622:69"/>
celebrated. The lytle rounde hoſts of fyne flowre were eaten by the ſacrificer and the aſſiſtants ſtanding and not ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting. The flowre whereof they were made was called <hi>Mola,</hi> whereof com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this worde <hi>immolare,</hi> to offer.</p>
               <p>There was diuers hoſts, that is to ſaye, diuers lytle round cakes, dedicated vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to diuers gods lyke as they had diuers ſacrifices of the Maſſe. With the ſame round hoſts was offered wyne (the aul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſeruinge in place of tables.) And whyles the ſacrificer and the aſſiſtaunts at the ſacrifice did eate &amp; communicate together the foreſayd lytle round cakes, conſecrated to the honour of their gods, there was ſong hymnes, and pleaſaunt ſongs. Some playing vppon Orgaynes and Cymbales.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Before the deuouryng of this rounde hoſte prynted with pictures, the maſſalian doctours haue ordeyned that the Sacrificer ſhal vſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iurations and coniuringe by ſygnes of the croſſe, fyrſt he ought to make thre croſſes vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the rounde hoſte to fygure the threfolde doctrine of chriſt. To witte, by the father, by
<pb facs="tcp:25622:69"/>
himſelfe, and by the holy ghoſt, in pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing theſe words: Haec dona, haec munera, haec ſancta ſacrificia illibata. Other doctours Alco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raniſts &amp; Maſſalians interpret the third croſſe to ſignifie the treaſon of Iudas who deliuered his maiſter into the hands of the Iues. Beſide the foreſaid thre croſſes, doth folow fiue mo, to figure the fiue dayes of reſpit from paulme ſonday to good fryday, or otherwiſe to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the fiue wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds of chriſt, two in his hands two in his feete &amp; one in his right ſyde. Of the which fiue croſſes, the thre firſt muſt be made vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the chalice &amp; vpon the round hoſt to figure the deliuering of chriſt vnto the prie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtes, ſcribes &amp; Phariſies: or to figure the price that chriſt was ſold for, to wit thre tymes ten which is .30. pence. The two other croſſes are ſeperatly made: the one (being the fourth) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hoſt, thother vpon the chalice alone, to play the two perſons of chriſt &amp; iudas: which the maſſalian ſacrificer doth continuing ſtyll his mocks &amp; mummeries, ſtretching out hys armes to figure chriſt ſtretched on the croſſe. Then he lifteth vp his round hoſt printed full of pictures to cauſe it to be worſhipped. And that he beginneth agayne to make thre other croſſes. One vpon the hoſt, another vpon the cuppe, and the thyrde vpon hymſelfe, to playe the perſonages of thre eſtates: of thoſe that be in heauen, in purgatorie, and in earth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:70"/>
                  <hi>He ſmiteth afterward vpon his breſt, to play the perſonage of the theſe hangyng vppon the croſſe, whiche repented hym ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the ſmiting of the ſtomack muſt be with the thre hyndermoſt fyngers of the hande, for the thombe and the next fynger be reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to conſecrate and tranſubſtantiate the round hoſt. Moreouer he muſt ſmyte his breſt thre tymes to fygure the threfolde offence of the heart, mouth and deede. In lifting vp hys voyce to repreſent the thefe or the centurion, which confeſſed god in the paſsion. Sixe other croſſes are made once againe, thre vppon the chalice couered, to figure the thre houres that Chriſt hanged on the croſſe on lyue: and the thre other croſſes are made vpon the chalice diſcouered (with the round hoſte lifted vp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain) to fygure the thre houres that chriſt han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged vpon the croſſe dead. Then after the maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalian hath kiſſed his chalice there are yet two croſſes more, to fygure the myſterie of the bloude and water iſſuyng out of chriſts ſyde. Beſyde the dumme mummeries aboueſayde, the prieſt muſt take the couering cloth from the chalice, and couer it with the plantyn to figure the breaking of the vaile of the temple in the middeſt at the death of chriſt. This done the round hoſt is put fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue the chalice, &amp; is couched vnder the corporas to figure the bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riyng of chriſt. The prieſt thus hauing played
<pb facs="tcp:25622:70"/>
the perſon of the hanged thefe, of the traitour Iudas of chriſt, &amp; of the publicans, playeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde the perſonage of the centurian, in ſinging the Pater noſter. But the Alcoran of Durand expoundeth by the ſeuen petitions of the Pater noſter the ſeuen wepings of the vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin Marye, or the ſeuen vertues, or the ſeuen giftes of the holy ghoſt, or the ſeuen Beatitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, or the ſeuen deadly ſynnes. This ſong fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, the Maſſalian a lytle whyle kepeth ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, to fygure the ſilence or reſt of chriſt in the tombe.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <p>Re diuina &amp; ceremoniis celebratis, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdos tunc, I, licet ſuccla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mabat, qua voce illos qui inter fuerant, miſſos facie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat.</p>
                     <p>Alex ab Alex lib. 4. cap. 17 Parts of the maſſe ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma 700 yeres before the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>carnation of Ieſu chriſt.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Another aperie or mu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>merie doth the Maſſalian play with his round hoſte, the vvhiche he layeth vppon the paten to fygure the vnitie of the diuinitie with the humani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle: but when he playeth the ſecrete myſterie, then the hoſt is hyd out of ſyght.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſacrifice thus finiſhed &amp; the litle rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hoſts eate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Numa ordeined to ſing theſe wordes: <hi>I, licet (vel) It<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e miſſa eſt,</hi> that is to ſay, go it is graunted, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble is ſuffered to go home. Be not all theſe partes of the Maſſe ſacrifice ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Numa the coniurer more then 700 yeres before the incarnation of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, to witte, the veſtments, the aulbe, the chaſuble, the holy purginge water coniured with ſalt to chaſe away
<pb facs="tcp:25622:71"/>
diuells, the aulter, the taper light, the the turnings and trauerſings along the aulter, with prayers and meditations toward the Eaſt. The proceſſions with ſhrines and relikes carried vppon the ſhulders of the prieſts clothed in whyte ſurplices &amp; crownes vppon their heads: the Confiteor made to the he ſainctes &amp; ſhe ſaincts: the playing on the Organs, the Canticles, Peanes, Hymnes, and Odes: the Cenſour and the Encens: the communion of lytle round bread conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated in the name of their godds: and in thend this ſong <hi>Ite miſſa eſt:</hi> Do ye not acknowledge (O ye Maſſalians) that ye haue borowed all theſe partes &amp; mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of your Maſſe of Pompilians reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion? Why doe you holde this worde Maſſe,<note place="margin">Math, 27. Luke. 20. Mark. 14. 1. Cor. 11.</note> ſeing Ieſus Chriſt did name it a ſupper, or the partaking of his bodye? Why haue ye taken vp theſe veſtemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, the Aulbe, &amp; paynted Chaſuble pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to the auncient romain Idolators, of the which garments Chriſt ordeyned nothing? Why haue ye geuen more
<pb facs="tcp:25622:71"/>
credit vnto the witchcraft of Pompilius to chaſe away diuels w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſalt water coniu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red, &amp; called holy water, then vnto the holy ghoſpel of Ieſus Chriſt, the which doth aſſure you in his name to driue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wai diuels, &amp; not with witchcraft of ſalt?<note place="margin">Mark. 16.</note> Who but the ſpirite of Neuma, did in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire you to ſhaue your crowne round: &amp; to deck your ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whyte ſurplices, to beare the ſhrines &amp; banners in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion? When Ieſus Chriſt celebrated his holy ſupper &amp; inſtructed his apoſtles of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his body &amp; blood, did he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maund the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to folow the religion of the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient romain Idolators, to haue their alters enriched w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> images, to vſe turnin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gs &amp; trauerſings alonge the alter, to be ſhorne rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, to haue aulbs &amp; chaſubles, addreſſing their praiers &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion to he &amp; ſhe ſaincts, to pipe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> organs, to ꝑfume their alters &amp; images w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> encence to, go to the offrings, to cary monie to the prieſts box, to eat litle rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hoſts co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrated, &amp; laſte of all to ſing <hi>Ite miſſa eſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I well perceyue (O Maſſalians) your Maſſe ſubtelties, wherby you ſhal
<pb facs="tcp:25622:72"/>
confeſſe to me, that the body and chiefe parts of the Maſſe toke their beginning and creation of Numa Pompilius.</p>
               <p>Neuertheleſſe the deckinges and enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chings were inuented by other biſhops of Rome: ſpeciallye by a monke called Gregorye the firſt of that name, that came to the Popedome. Who was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the Magike and Philoſophie of Pythagoras, and had alſo ſtudied the lawes of Tullius Hoſtillius, king and ſucceſſour of Numa, to the end to make his name euerlaſtinge by addinge ſome new thinge to the miſſall ſacrifice, he ordeyned to ſinge nyne tymes theſe wordes in Greeke,<note place="margin">Platine. Volaterran Kyrie eleyſon</note> 
                  <hi>Kyrie eleyſon.</hi> For Gregory did greatly eſteme this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber nyne: euen as the auncient romayn Idolators had recourſe vnto the nouen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall ſacrifice for ſignes and monſtrous wonders.<note place="margin">Quoties pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digium nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciabatur, ſacru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nouendiale per nouem dies agebatur Tit. Liui. lib. 1 Decades. 1.</note> He did alſo ordeine that in the Maſſeſacrifice ſhuld be ſong two words of Hebrue, to accompanye the two wordes in Greke. And that at certaine tymes men ſhoulde ſynge theſe two
<pb facs="tcp:25622:72"/>
wordes <hi>Allelu ya:</hi> and certayne tymes they ſhoulde not.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In place of which Allelu ya, is ſong another ſong called the tract, with ſharpenes of voyce prolixitie of ſong, and heauineſſe of notes of muſicke, to fygure the miſeries of this world, and he that ſyngeth Allelu ya, muſt be higher then he that houleth the graduel, as the alco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran of Titelman doth recite.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Is there not witchcraft inough in your ſacrifice (O Maſſalians) onleſſe ye put therevnto Hebrue and Greke wordes? and mingle together Pithagoricall numbers and nouendiall ſonges, and inſtitute a difference of dayes to ſinge and not to ſing Hebrue words, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent croſſes and dumme mummeries? Be not theſe corruptions of the holye ſacrament of the ſupper ordeyned of God?<note place="margin">Platine. Sabellie.</note> Some other haue enriched the miſſall ſacrifice,<note place="margin">Gloria patri Agnus dei Kiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>g the Pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ten or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</note> as Damaſe biſhoppe of Rome with a <hi>Gloria patri,</hi> Sergius with an <hi>Agnus dei,</hi> ſonge three tymes (which Titelman expoundeth to figure the Aſcention of Chriſt) Innocent the kiſſing of the prieſts Paten.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:73"/>
                  <hi>The which paten of gold by the doctrine of the Alcoran dothe ſignifie the diuinitie of chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">cap. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>The Gloria in excelcis by Symmachus, the which ſong pronounced in a voyce ſwete &amp; baſſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Cap. 56.57.</note> 
                  <hi>doth ſignifie (as holdeth the Alcoran of Titelman) the warlike &amp; childiſhe voice of Chriſt, beyng yet in the cradle. O blaſphemye and deteſtable mommry of the ſonne of god. Leo the ſecond inſtituted the kiſſynge of the paxe: whych the Alcoran of Titelman ſayeth doeth ſignifye the vnion of chriſtians.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pax kiſsing.</note> 
                  <hi>And that the kiſſynge of the paxe came in, in the place of the holy communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> obſerued in the firſt church next the Apoſtles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This kiſſing of the Paxe was ſonge of the Maſſalian ſayinge theſe wordes <hi>Pax domini:</hi> and making 3. croſſes vpon the Chalice when the thyrd parte of the hooſt is caſt into the wine, to fygure the incarnation of Chriſt: or for the thréefold peace, of the time, of the ſpirit, and of the euerlaſtyngnes to come. Moreouer the forging of the Canon of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe is attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted to Alexander,<note place="margin">The canon of the maſſe.</note> Gelace, Syricie, Leo, and Pelage. Theſe be peeces pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched to, according to the humours of the
<pb facs="tcp:25622:73"/>
Biſhops of Rome, the authours and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorers, the founders and augmentours of the maſſe ſacrifice.</p>
               <p>The beſt enrychynge inſtituted in the Maſſe ſacrifice muſt not be forgotten to witte certayne places of the olde &amp; new teſtament called the epiſtles and Ghoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pells.<note place="margin">Platine. Sabellie.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">The epiſtles and ghoſpels cut in the maſſe.</note> The whiche the Meſſalians haue cut &amp; mingled with the Pompilian Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry &amp; therein haue prophaned the lawe of god, euen as dyd the Apoſtate Sergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us doctour of the Machomet, the whiche decked the Alcoran with many places of the holy byble, &amp; patched a hotchpotch of fables &amp; hereſies, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> the holy law of god.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The maſſalians haue ordeyned two perſons to ſing the epiſtles and ghoſpelles to the ende to enriche their Maſſedaunce: to wit, the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deacon, who marcheth before to play the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the firſt law of the Iewes: and the dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con. whiche commeth after with more great dignitie to repreſent the lawe of the ghoſpell: the whiche deacon carieth vppon his breſt a quoſhon to figure the humblenes of hart The ſubdeacon receyueth not the bleſsing of the Maſsing ſacrificer as the deacon doth, for this (ſaye the Maſſalian doctours) that God ſent his prophetes inuiſiblie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:74"/>
                  <hi>But the deacon playinge the perſonage of the law of the goſpel, he receiueth bleſſyng as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſent among wolues, becauſe chriſt ſent his Apoſtles as men viſibly. It is ordained that the deacon ſhall weare a ſtoell croſſwiſe hanging vpon his ſhulders, one end ouer the other, to figure force &amp; continence ioyned together in the maſſemonger. The deacon playing his pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen and ſinging ſome pece of the goſpell in a language vnderſtanded neither of him nor of the aſſiſtantes muſt turne himſelf towarde the north ſtanding vpright. Becauſe (ſaith Titelma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) the north part is cold and malicious. And ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore he muſt make a croſſe to chaſe away the deuills of the north. Be not theſe ſorceries and conflictes more horrible than al the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cient Romain biſhops idolators?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Againſt the long poſſeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Idolators.</note>Doth not this approue the Alcoran of Machomet, the long poſſeſſion whereof Turks preſently haue had for theſe .900. y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yeres paſt, hauing conquered countres Realmes,<note place="margin">Againſt Turks</note> and Empiers, proſpered in al their interpriſes, &amp; ſtil obſeruing the abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>minable law ſette oute in the Alcoran?<note place="margin">Againſt the people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael offering to Moloch.</note> Were the people of Iſraell excuſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God (when they dyd ſacrifice in the valley of Tophet to Moloch w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts bloud) by alledging the long poſſeſſion,
<pb facs="tcp:25622:74"/>
&amp; accuſtomed vſage, for the ſpace of .1200.<note place="margin">4. Kings. 16 23</note> yeres before this Idolatrie was algeto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſtroied by the good kinge Ioſias?<note place="margin">Againſt the idolatrie of the braſen ſerpent. Num. 21.</note> Did the Iſraelits murmur agaynſt the vertuous king Ezechias whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the braſen, ſerpent whiche was made by the expreſſe commaundement of god 900. yeres before? Were the ſame people excuſed of their Idolatries committed in Dan &amp; Bethell,<note place="margin">Againſt the image ſet vp by Hierobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am. 3. Kings. 12.</note> wherein were the Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of two heffers of gold inſtituted by their kinge Hieroboam, vnder pretence of long poſſeſſion, &amp; that they had conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued this Idolatrie for the ſpace of .300. or .400. yeres. The Iues,<note place="margin">Againſt the infidelitie of the iewes.</note> now vacabo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds ſhall they be excuſed before the maieſtye of god by ſhowing the long poſſeſſion of their ceremoniall lawe inſtituted yea of god himſelf .3. thouſand yeres ago?</p>
               <p>Alſo you (O maſſalians) can you aledge againſt god the continuance and longe poſſeſſion of celebratinge your Pompi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lian Maſſes long time, and that you and your predeceſſours haue vſed ſold &amp; put to vſurie your Miſſall ſacrifyces? is this
<pb facs="tcp:25622:75"/>
reaſon ſufficient to grounde vpon long poſſeſſion, as your predeceſſours ſena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of Rome did alledge vnto Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſe the Emperour, their Pompilian re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ligion to haue been obſerued more then a .M. yeres? This is not an excuſe ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to bring in long poſſeſſion &amp; vſage of long tyme obſerued, for the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of your Idolatries. For if god of his mercie &amp; wonderfull patience did ſuffer the Iewes in their vnfaithfulneſſe, the Turks in their Alcoran law, &amp; the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in their Maſſe Idolatries: It is not for vs to diſpute of the incomprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſecretes of god, but with all humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie to take againe the waye of truth, when it ſhall pleaſe him to geue it vs, af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter long and déepe darknes, whereunto the people in all ages hath fallen &amp; tour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the true worſhippinge &amp; ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce of god: euen ſo as briefly before we haue declared of the Iſraelites the choſen people of god, the which notwith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtanding y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they had Moyſes &amp; the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets which did admoniſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by many
<pb facs="tcp:25622:75"/>
miracles &amp; threatenings, how they ſhuld honor god &amp; kepe the law, neuertheleſſe they neuer ceaſed by mens inuentions to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit idolatries. So that during the raigne of the princes Iudges of Iſrael when the people were gouerned as in Ariſtocratia, than after ſubmitted vnder the yoke of kings as in a monarchie, and laſt of all brought vnder the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the prieſts hauing gotten both the temporalitie &amp; ſpiritualitie, the lawe of god hath bene corrupted, the ſacrifices and ſacramentes defaced &amp; defiled, and idolatry continued more then 1600 yeres from the law written by Moyſes, vnto the incarnation of Ieſus Chriſt. What maye one hope for then of the people of Rome inſtructed in all Idolatrie as a dry tree, a heatheniſhe &amp; baſtard people? But theſe Maſſalian heritikes can not vaunt themſelues of very long poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Maſſe ſacrifices, except of the ix. pieces before deſcribed, reſtored &amp; boro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed of Numa Pompilius, for the other parts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſe wer inuented at diuers
<pb facs="tcp:25622:76"/>
times by diuers antichriſts corruptours of the holy ſacraments ordained of God And to vnderſtand the times &amp; yeres of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> chiefe builders, Agapet Pope of Rome raigned in the yere of chriſt .533. &amp; brought in the proceſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> after the order preſcribed by Numa. The <hi>Confiteor,</hi> was reſtoored by Damaſe raigning the yere .577. The <hi>Kyrie eleyſon</hi> &amp; the Letanies, by Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry raigning in the yere .593. The graduel the collects &amp; the Traict by Gelaſe raig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the yere 493. The Sequences by Gothere abbot of Sandale. The <hi>Gloria in excelcis</hi> by Simmach raigning in the yere .508. The incens &amp; the offertorie re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored from the auncient doctrine Pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilian by Leo y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> third of that name in the yere .800. The kiſſing of the pax by Inno<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt of that name in the yere .408. <hi>Agnus dei</hi> inſtituted by Sergius in the yere .697. The commemoration of the dead inuented by Pelagius in the yere. 558. The Canon forged by Gelaſe, Siri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, Leo, &amp; Pelagi raigning in the yeare. 800. The tranſubſtanciacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> inſtituted by
<pb facs="tcp:25622:76"/>
the biſhops of Rome about the yeare of chriſt 1062. Wherfore of what impuden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie are theſe Alcoraniſts Maſſe doctours to be condempned, the which faulſely do affirme that the holye Apoſtles of Ieſus Chriſt did celebrate their miſſal ſacrifice. Seinge y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this ſacrifice was not reſtored to his integritie after Numa Pompili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us but after Chriſt .800. yeres? In what approued hiſtories is there mentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> made that ſuch Idolatrie was commytted by the holy apoſtles of god? How is it poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible to beleue or to thinke it, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as this great whore of Babilion hath not bene reſtored with her deceipt &amp; maſke of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines till longe time after the incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>But it behoueth to returne to our hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie of Rome, more &amp; more to diſcouer the true original of the maſſe.<note place="margin">Continuing of hiſtories.</note> We haue declared in diſcouering the parts &amp; chief members of the maſſe ſacrifice, how the auncient Romains before they were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed to ſacrifice w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the blood of beſts did vſe litle round cakes conſecrated in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:77"/>
honour of their gods, the which ſtanding they did eate within the temple aboute the end of the ſacrifice. Theſe litle rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hoſts of wheate flowre were taken vp of the maſſalian ſacrificers: but they haue enriched the witchcraft &amp; idolatrie of Nu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ma Pompilius in ſo much as they haue decked the litle rounde hoſts with ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges &amp; pictures printed within the round circle of the ſayd hoſts,<note place="margin">Abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble idolatrie.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">Againſt the idolatrie of the rounde Hoſts.</note> to thend to make them more holy, euen to be worſhipped, by thinuention of Honorius antichriſt of Rome, the yere 1226, the which Numa y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> coniurer neuer practiſed, ne yet came to this abominable idolatrie. What more deteſtable hereſie can ther be diſcouered then to paint the maieſtie of god in form &amp; likenes of a man, as the Antropomor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phits imagen? Who taught you (o maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalians) to corrupt the holy ſacrament of our lord Ieſus chriſts ſupper, in making litle rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hoſts, if not Numa y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iurer? When Ieſus chriſt celebrated hys holy ſupper w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his apoſtles, did he ordeyne to haue litle rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hoſts, &amp; to print them ful
<pb facs="tcp:25622:77"/>
of pictures &amp; likeneſſes of men, to adiure &amp; coniure w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> croſſings &amp; bleſſings odde or euen, &amp; to make them to be worſhipped? Acknowledge then (o Maſſalians) your principal part of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſe to wit, your litle rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hoſts to haue take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their beginning of Numa more then 700 yeres before y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> incarnatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſus chriſt, who neuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded you this rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dnes of hoſts, nor y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they ſhuld be rather rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d then ſquare, thre cornered, or eight cornered. But ſo far was he fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chuſing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> figure of rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes after the faſhion of Numa, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariwiſe when he inſtituted the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of his body, he vſed breaking of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread in morſels, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch he diſtributed to his diſciples for a ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bol, ſigne, &amp; figure, ſignifiyng really &amp; ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tally his body by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly goſt. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maſſalians haue not only choſen the faſhion rounde in their lytle conſecrated hoſts printed full of pictures to cauſe them to be worſhipped after the maner of the auncient Romaynes, but further they haue exceded al Idolators.
<pb facs="tcp:25622:78"/>
For in the tyme of Neuma Pompilius, thoſe that aſſiſted at the ſacrifice of the Maſſe did eate together ſtandinge the ſaid lytle round hoſts conſecrated. But ſince the Maſſalians haue reſerued for them ſelues the communion of the ſayd litle rounde hoſtes conſecrated, vſing no charitie towarde thoſe that ſtoode by at their miſſall ſacrifice. Is this to followe the ordinaunce of Ieſus Chriſt, who brake the bread and gaue it to his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles? Ieſus Chriſt the euerlaſting ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficer, was he alone at the aulter, eating one lytle round hoſt grauen full of ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, when he celebrated the holye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of his body? Can you (O Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalians, toto abhominable, and muche leſſe charitable Idolators than all the auncient Romains) ſo muche playe the ſubtell ſophiſters that you wyll make men to vnderſtand that your maſſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice (wherein the ſacrificer alone de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoureth all the lytle round hoſt printed full of pictures without geuyng parts to any other) is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, &amp; by a mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueylous
<pb facs="tcp:25622:78"/>
witchcraft to cauſe the aſſiſtans at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrifice to beleue, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thei haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nicated together w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the prieſt, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that they neyther receyued nor did eate any portion of the rounde hoſte.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And beſyde this for a more extreme idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie. the maſſalian doctours expounders do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare the rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hoſt to be deuided in thre parts, one for thoſe which ar in paradiſe, another for thoſe whiche are in purgatorie to haue remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their ſynnes, and the thyrde drenched in wyne for thoſe whiche are lyuyng in thys worlde. But the Alcoran of Durand declareth the thre parts of the hoſt broken, to repreſent the thre faſhioned body of chriſt, in the ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre ſleping, in the earth lying, and after reſing againe. The other ſubtell doctour Biel, becauſe he would not confeſſe the bodye of chriſt in the round hoſt to be bruſed and broken, doth ſubtelly defyne the breaking of the hoſte to be done in an accidence without a ſubſtance. Be not theſe horrible hereſies to make the ſoules to communicate which are in heauen, or in purgatorie, inſtituted by Sergius doctour of the Machomet, by the meanes of one round hoſt deuoured by the maſſalian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But you (O Maſſalians) maye here obiect vnto me the vſe of the primatiue churche obſerued in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> communion of the holy ſupper, whereas euery one of the
<pb facs="tcp:25622:79"/>
aſſemblye in the temple did take a por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the broken bread conſecrated to eate and communicate together.<note place="margin">A communio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of holy bread</note> The which vſe hath bene kept vnto this daye in your Miſſal ſacrifices celebrated vpon Sondayes, the which you cauſe to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed by morcelles of holy bread vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thaſſiſtaunts within the temple. But in this auncient communion doth abide nothing but an image onely. Becauſe the Maſſalians abſing the holye ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, haue reſerued for them ſelues on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the litle rounde hoſte conſcrated to be deuoured,<note place="margin">Notable diffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twene the round hoſt &amp; the holye bread.</note> without geuing any portion vnto the aſſiſtaunts: vnto whome they leaue the bittes of holy bread, which are foure ſquare for the moſte parte. The round hoſt without leauen, and the holy bread is with leauen. The rounde hoſte is without ſalt, &amp; the holy bread w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſalt. The rounde hoſt is printed full of pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, &amp; the holy bread is w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out print or pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture. The rounde hoſt is worſhipped, &amp; the holy bread is receyued w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thanks ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing. The round hoſt is deuoured of the
<pb facs="tcp:25622:79"/>
prieſt, &amp; the holy bread is deuided among thaſſemble to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate &amp; to eate toge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther. The round hoſt is ſtieped in wyne, the holy bread is eaten without wyne. To be ſhort there is as great difference betwene theſe two kynds of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, as there is betwene thauncient lawe of the Idolators &amp; the lawe of the ghoſpell. Prouided always that they agre in one poynct, that is, that both in the one &amp; the other there is a corruption of the holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament of the ſupper ordeyned of god. It reſteth to come downe to the deepe Maze of Idolatrie.<note place="margin">Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation.</note> We haue recited the hiſtory of the people of Iſrael, which did not content them ſelues w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the heauenly bread Manna geuen vnto them of God, during the tyme that they were in the wildernes: but did murmur againſt god and Moyſes their leader, requiring to eate fleſhe. The people alſo of Rome beinge Heathen and Infidelles, were not contented with the inſtitution of Pompilian touchynge the communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the lytle rounde Cakes;<note place="margin">Blond. lib. 1. de Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. trium.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:80"/>But the biſhiops of Rome, Idolators, did inſtitute the killing and offering vp of beaſtes, to the ende to eate and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate the fleſhe of the offerings in in their ſacrifices, ſpecially the ſhepe, the Sowe, the Goate, and the Beofe, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che firſte were ordeyned by Euander king of Arcadie. To the ende therefore that the Maſſalian ſhould not go out of kynde from the Idolatries of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſours, they haue folowed this com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>munion of fleſhe, and are not contented with the lytle rounde, vnleauened hoſts conſecrated and prynted full of pictures: but haue in tyme inuented a new witch crafte,<note place="margin">Hoſts of mea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le are chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into fleſh and wyne in to blood.</note> to chaunge theyr litle hoſtes of floure into fleſh and bone, the bread be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no more bread, but an accidence w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſubſtaunce: and by this meanes to chaunge their rounde hoſt of meale into an hoſt of fleſhe and bloude. The wyne alſo offered in their Maſſe challices to be chaunged into bloude: the wyne beyng no more wyne, but an accident without ſubſtaunce. Was there euer any witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crafte
<pb facs="tcp:25622:80"/>
more abhominable and hereſie more deteſtable than this tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation of the Maſſe? When the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſrael were weryed with the ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Manna, and the heauenly bread, demaunding fleſh, was the Manna tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into fleſhe bones and bloode?</p>
               <p>When the Romains the auncient Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laters did chaunge theyr round hoſts of meale, and demaunded to eate of the fleſhe in their ſacrifices, did they vſe this witchcraft of tranſubſtantiation?</p>
               <p>Wherefore I do frely affirme that the Maſſalians haue lately inſtituted this addicion of the Maſſe, yea more than 1000 yeres after the incarnation of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">In the yere of Chriſt. 1062. in Chrono. log. Fon. Volater.</note> This hereſie began to ſprede abroad greatly in the tyme of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt Nicolaite, crept into the Romaine biſhopricke by the conſpiratie of Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brant, hauing chaſed awaye by force the other choſen biſhop, namely Benedict the .xij.<note place="margin">Lanfranc, de ſacr.</note> of that name in the yere of Ieſus chriſt 1062. Afterward it aduaunce it ſelf by a conſpiratie holden in the Lateran
<pb facs="tcp:25622:81"/>
at Rome during the eccleſiaſticall tyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny of Innocent the third of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name: about 200 yeres after the ſolemne recan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Berengarius deane of S. Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice of Angiers.<note place="margin">Againſt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> Againſt the which ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominable witchcraft &amp; heriſie, we muſt briefely bring in by the way of recapitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation the inſtitutions of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacraments ordeyned of god.</p>
               <p>Firſt the fruites of the knowledge of good &amp; euill,<note place="margin">Trees of lyfe</note> forbidden to our firſt father Adam, as holy ſignes &amp; ſacraments of feare &amp; obedience, wherevpon did hange life &amp; death, were they chaunged &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted into knowledge or death, leauing the nature of trées &amp; fruits, &amp; reduced in to an accidence without ſubſtaunce?<note place="margin">Heauenlye Manna, &amp; the rock flowing water.</note> the Manna from heauen, &amp; the rock flowing with water of life, ſacraments agreing with the holy ſacrament of the ſupper, were they changed into an accidence w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſubſtaunce?<note place="margin">Lambes offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by Abell.</note> the lambes without ſpot offered by Abel in ſacrifice wel pleaſing to god, were they chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into another nature?<note place="margin">Circumciſion</note> The lytle ſkynne cutte of for a
<pb facs="tcp:25622:81"/>
note &amp; marke of the couenaunt vnto the good patriarch Abraham, &amp; his poſteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, was it chaunged into an accident w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſubſtaunce?<note place="margin">Paſcal lambe.</note> The blood of the Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal lambe for thaſſuraunce of the helth of Iſraell, was it chaunged into another ſubſtaunce? The fleſhe of the vnſpotted lambe, ordeyned to be eaten in the daye of the Paſſeouer, a true figure of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye ſacrament of the Supper, was it chaunged into an accidence withoute ſubſtaunce?</p>
               <p>The braſen Serpente,<note place="margin">Braſen Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</note> by the onelye ſyght whereof health was geuen vnto diſſeaſes, left it to be a ſerpent of braſſe, was it chaunged in beynge ordeyned a ſacrament and holy ſygne vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Iſraell? The oblations offered in ſacrifices,<note place="margin">The offered ſacrifices.</note> as well of earthlye beaſtes as vnleauened bread, and other holye ſygnes ordeyned of GOD for Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentes and holye Sygnes, to cleanſe the people of Iſraell: Were they chaunged into an accidence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſubſtaunce? All the holye Sygnes
<pb facs="tcp:25622:82"/>
ordeyned of god in the church of Iſraell, not withſtanding that they did repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent really &amp; ſacramentally, that whiche they did figure, &amp; not as a ſimple ſygne without effect, yet ſo it is that there was neuer none ſo horrible an heritike that did inuent this witchcrafte of tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation. Yet muſte you confeſſe (O Maſſalians) that the good &amp; holy fathers of Iſraell were adopted graffed &amp; rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated by faith in Ieſus Chriſt, begotten before all worldes:<note place="margin">A conference of the fayth of the aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent fathers of Iſrael with ours.</note> and that they were nouriſhed &amp; got euerlaſting lyfe by Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, &amp; that they &amp; we haue but one only God, and one only Ieſus chriſt our mediatour &amp; redemer. And that thei through faith did ſacramentallye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, and ſpirituallye partake the blood of Ieſus Chriſt for their ſaluation and euerlaſting lyfe. And there is no difference (as touching God) betwene them that were before the incarnation of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; we that are after the incarnation. But they &amp; we are the churche of God bought with the bloode
<pb facs="tcp:25622:82"/>
of the iuſte &amp; vnſpotted lambe Ieſus Chriſt.<note place="margin">S. Auguſt. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Fauſt. lib. 20. cap. 21. &amp; 14. lib. 19. &amp; con. Petilan. lib. 2. ca. 37. 77</note> Furthermore that they had faith in the promiſe to come: and obſerued the ſacraments &amp; holy ſignes of the ſacrifice whiche oughte to be finiſhed by Ieſus Chriſt. And that we by the newe lawe do celebrate the memorie and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the ſacrifice already finiſhed by Ieſus Chriſt, hauing the fruition of his promiſe accompliſhed.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10. Auguſt. in Pſalm.</note> If then the Iſraelites did eate of the ſame heauenly bread, &amp; drynke of the ſame water of life (by faythe) that we do in one only Ieſus Chriſt: If they had holy ſygnes to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent actually &amp; really the death of Ieſus Chriſt to come, euen as we haue had holy ſignes of his death preſent or paſt: they for the tyme to come, &amp; we for the tyme paſt: Wherefore is it then that the Maſſalians haue inuented this newe Witchcraft of tourning one holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ordeyned of God into a Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft of tranſubſtantiation, and an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent without a ſubſtaunce? If god (to make knowen his power, &amp; to declare
<pb facs="tcp:25622:83"/>
the hardneſſe &amp; ſtiffeneckedneſſe of Pha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rao) pleaſed to do merueylous thynges by Moyſes &amp; Aaron,<note place="margin">Againſt the miracles alled<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged by the maſſalians. Exod 7.8.14.</note> in chaunging a rod into a Serpent, the water of the riuer into bloode, &amp; into Frogges, the duſte of the yearthe into lyce, and further to make the ſayleable ſea drye, and to do manye other miracles: Is this to bryng in a tranſubſtantiation of lytle rounde hoſtes, vnleauened, prynted full of pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, into an accidence without ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaunce? In what place of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (when there is mencion made of holy Sygnes, Sacramentes, or Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, ordeyned of God) is it ſayde the Sygne or Sacrament is chaunged?</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, God wyllyng to accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modate hym ſelfe to the infirmities of man hath ordeyned vnto him from time to time common Sygnes, for notes &amp; markes of the aſſuraunce of the thynge ſygnified. Wherein the myght of God is moore renowmed &amp; magnified by ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge vnto vs with the holye ſygne the thynge repreſented, by the power of
<pb facs="tcp:25622:83"/>
fayth &amp; the holy Ghoſt, than if the ſelfe ſygne were reallye chaunged by ſome viſible myracle.</p>
               <p>For the Sacramentes doe conteyne in them more ſpiritualnes then fleſhlynes, for which cauſe God did alwayes blame his people Iſraell by his Prophetes, for taking his ſacraments ouer fleſhlye,<note place="margin">The expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Ieſus chriſt of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of his body.</note> as we haue before briefly declared. But tel me (O Maſſalians) when Ieſus Chriſt would expounde, that he was the true bread of life which came down from hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen, to geue euerlaſting life, &amp; how theſe ſacramentall words oughte to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, to eate his fleſh &amp; drinke hys blood, when the Capharnaites your predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors wer offended, did he teach by his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation that to eate his fleſh ought to be vnderſtande by a litle rounde hoſte tranſubſtantiated? The rounde hoſte of flowre, and the wyne to be no more bread &amp; Wyne, but an accidence with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſubſtaunce? Is thys your abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Witchecrafte the doctrine of Ieſus Chriſte?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:84"/>Nothing leſſe: But Ieſus Chriſt as a true lawe geuer,<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> vnto whome the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation of his lawe appertayned, anſwered vnto the Doctours Caphar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naites, that they were to groſſe &amp; carnall and that they did abyde in the fleſh as ye do (O Maſſeſayers:) Notwithſtanding that the fleſhe alone profiteth nothing: ſaying that theſe ſacramentall wordes were ſpirituall.<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> The fleſhe (ſayeth he) profiteth nothing, it is the ſpirite that quickneth. Moreouer (O Maſſayers) howe can ye ſafelye make to agree your tranſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the doctrine of Ieſus Chriſt, whiche doeth promiſe &amp; aſſure to geue euerlaſtinge lyfe to thoſe whyche eate his fleſhe &amp; drynke hys bloode, if ye take theſe wordes carnallye? For you can not be ignoraunt that your bodyes (notwithſtandynge that they haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured the lytle rounde hoſtes tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated into fleſhe &amp; bone, &amp; ſupt and lycked the wyne chaunged into bloode) do dye &amp; are mortall, by the neceſſitie of the lawe. Wherefore lyfe euerlaſtyng
<pb facs="tcp:25622:84"/>
promyſed by this communion, maye not be vnderſtand of the body nor of the mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tall fleſhe. You muſte then of neceſſitie acknowledge, for a ſure interpretation that to eate the bodye and dryncke the blood of Ieſus Chriſt ought to be refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto the lyfe ſpirituall &amp; heauenly, &amp; that the fleſhe profiteth nothing,<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> but the ſpirituall worde &amp; communion of the body &amp; blood of Ieſus Chriſt by fayth &amp; in ſpirite geuyng euerlaſtyng lyfe. This interpretation is often recited by the holy apoſtle Iohn in many places when he vſeth theſe termes, he that commeth vnto me, ſhall neuer hunger, he that beleueth in me ſhall neuer thruſte, but ſhal haue euerlaſting lyfe. Are not theſe termes ſufficient playne to interprete this holy ſacrament of the body &amp; blood of Ieſus Chriſt, withoute running vnto your witchcraft of tranſubſtantiation.<note place="margin">Conference of baptiſme vnto the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the ſupper.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Another lyke interpretation of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour &amp; authour of the ſacramental law is deſcribed, when Ieſus Chriſt was aſked of Nicodeme the meane howe a
<pb facs="tcp:25622:85"/>
man coulde be regenerate &amp; borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. Is it poſſible (ſayeth Nicodeme) that man ſhould enter into his mothers wombe &amp; be borne agayne? Did Ieſus Chriſt anſwere vnto this demaunde, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in the holy ſacrament of Baptiſme the water was turned into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body into fleſh and into bloode, &amp; tranſubſtantiate into a carnall wombe to be thereby agayne engendred &amp; borne? Is there not as great reaſon after your witchchraft here to vſe this anſwere as in the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſupper? for by thone of theſe two holy ſacraments we be regenerate, &amp; by thother nouriſhed. And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> regenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is as merueylous vnto mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as the norriſhement. For after mans carnall iudgement it ſeemeth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible, twiſe to be engendred. But our good god hath vſed like interpretation for the regeneration as he did for the comu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of his fleſhe &amp; his blood namely that theſe ſacramental termes muſt be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually vnderſtand, &amp; not carnally: for the fleſhe profyteth nothynge but the ſpirit
<pb facs="tcp:25622:85"/>
quickneth. That whych is of the fleſh,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> is fleſhly that which of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſpirit is ſpirituall.</p>
               <p>The holye Apoſtle geuynge vnto the Corinthians that which he receyued at the hand of God,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> did admoniſhe them of the ſecond comming of Ieſu Chriſte, in loking for the which he commaunded to communicate the body &amp; bloode of Ieſus Chriſt by breaking of bread, &amp; the cuppe of bleſſyng called the newe Teſtament and the new couenant contracted by the blood of Ieſus Chriſt. For as much then as we are aſſured of the ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>minge of Ieſus Chriſt. Being gon vp into hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, and ſytteth on the right hand of god his father, vntill the day appoynted that he muſt come againe to iudge the quicke and the dead. How do ye agrée (o Maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lians) with this yſſue, when as by your magicke you ſaye that euerye daye you cauſe to come downe, and make to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tourne the bodye of Ieſus Chryſte in fleſhe and bone, before the tyme appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of hys ſecond comming, be come?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:86"/>This witchcrafte was reſtored by you from the fyrſt authour of your Maſſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice Numa Pompilius:<note place="margin">Tit. Liuius. 1. Decade. 1.</note> who by hys witchcraft gaue to vnderſtande that he cauſed hys Nymphe &amp; goddeſſe Acgerie and alſo his Iupiter Elicius to deſcende from heauen,<note place="margin">Valcai. Max. lib. 1. cap. 3.</note> by whoſe meanes the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly ſecretes &amp; myſteryes were reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto him. Euen ſo by your withcraft the rounde hoſt conſecrated, is tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiated into the true &amp; reall bodye of Ieſus Chriſt: The bread being no more bread. Howe haue ye learned this bolde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to bruſe &amp; breake in pieces the bodye of Ieſus Chriſt accordinge to the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Sergius the ſecond of that name your predeceſſour biſhop of Rome? Are not you more deteſtable hangmen, then your predeceſſours lieutenaunts of the churche of Rome,<note place="margin">iohn. 19. Exod 12. Num. 9.</note> which crucified Ieſus Chriſt, but without bruſing &amp; breaking his bodye in pieces, as it was prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied before.<note place="margin">Corruption of the holy ſacraments.</note> And that more is, you are not content to breake it in thre pieces, but in your Maſſe ſacrifice ye haue en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſed
<pb facs="tcp:25622:86"/>
to drowne or ſteepe one portion of it in the wyne chaunged into blood to deuour it.<note place="margin">Againſt tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> To confirme your witchcraft of tranſubſtantiation, haue ye not ordey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to preſerue your lytle rounde pryn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted hoſts, the whiche you do kepe &amp; laye vp ſo curiouſlye in bores &amp; ſhrynes after they be chaunged into fleſhe &amp; bone, &amp; into the reall bodye of Ieſus Chriſt? Is not thys a deteſtable heriſie to beleue that the bodye of Ieſus Chriſt can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue corruption? Yea,<note place="margin">Harman. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tt.</note> &amp; often it is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of wormes, mytes, rattes &amp; myce. Can you interpret,<note place="margin">Blond. Platine.</note> that this is an acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence without ſubſtaunce, ſeing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> your hoſts become often ſtinking, &amp; corrupt w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in your boxes? Many times alſo deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of earthly brute beaſts, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which you cauſe to be burned &amp; their aſhes to be put into the place for reliks. When y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> biſhop of Rome Victor the iij. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> name, recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued poyſon by your tranſubſtantiated wyne, was it an accidence without ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance? Or when themperour Henry y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> 7. of that name, was poyſoned in eating
<pb facs="tcp:25622:87"/>
a litle round hoſt conſecrated, was it an accidence without ſubſtaunce, ſeing it gaue him his deathes wound? There is a more manifeſt appearaunce in the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uenly Manna geuen vnto the people of Iſrael,<note place="margin">Neem. 1. Pſal. 78.104. Iohn. 6. Sapi. 16.</note> the which notwithſtanding that it became corrupt (if it were kept) yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put in the ſecret place of the arcke of the couenaunt, it was preſerued with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out corruption: was it therefore tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiated into fleſh &amp; bone, to be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the heauenly bread, the bread which came down from heauen, the bread of lyfe, &amp; the bread of angels?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The expoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal words.</note>Now it remaineth to bring into iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the ſubtel reaſons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſſayers, which for the whole foundation of their witchcrafte, do carnally abyde in this word <hi>Eſt,</hi> ſaying theſe words are expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly written. This is my body, this is my blood, when Ieſus chriſt did inſtitute the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of his body &amp; of his bloode vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſignes of bread &amp; wine. But I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche all that are zelous of the honour of god diligently to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider the holy inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:25622:87"/>
of the ſacrament, by the which god wold declare &amp; ſignifie the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of his body by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread, &amp; the drinking of his blood by the wine &amp; the cup. All will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the true &amp; principall nouriſhment of the body of man is conteyned vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> kinds of bread &amp; wine: ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the true bread is often taken in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holye ſcriptures for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> nouriſhment &amp; life of man. But let vs begin to bring in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> places of the Bible. To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt man created to the lykenes of god,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 3.</note> for puniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of his offence was it not ſaid vnto him before, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> he muſt eate his bread in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſweat of his body?<note place="margin">Geneſ. 28.</note> Is there any man ſo ignoraunt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> wil not confeſſe all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> food &amp; life of man to be vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread? when Iacob prayed vnto god to geue him bread &amp; clothing, did not he vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtand by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread al y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was neceſſary for his nouriſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t?<note place="margin">Exod. 16. Neem. 9. Pſalm. 78. Sapi. 15. Iohn. 6. Geneſ. 14.</note> when it is recited y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god made it to rain bread vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of Iſrael in the wildernes, &amp; that w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this heauenly bread y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> children of Iſrael wer filled, was not this terme bread vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand of the heauenly Manna ſent of god for the nouriſhing of the people Iſrael?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:88"/>This manna is it not called the breade of heauen, &amp; the breade of angells geuen vnto the people without trauell?<note place="margin">Geneſ. 41. Geneſ. 47. Num. 21. Leuit. 26.</note> When Melchiſedech would releue the hooſte of the good Father Abraham dyd he not preſente vnto hym breade and Wyne? When Abraham wold gratifie and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .3. angels apearing to him, did he not offer to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Cakes baked in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> aſhes. Gaue he not to Agar breade for her no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment? The mother of Iſaac fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringe her wel beloued ſonne, gaue hym bread. Ioſeph in Egipt offred bread vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his brethren for their norriſhement. When one wil diſcribe a famine &amp; darth dothe he not ſaye, there lacketh breade? When god promiſeth any fauour vnto people keping his commaundementes,<note place="margin">iohn. 4. Pſalm. 104. Math, 4. Luke. 4. iohn. 6. Math. 4.</note> doth he not geue them aſſurance of ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cient breade? When he commended the poore, as his members, dyd he not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund to geue them bread? It is than the bread that nouriſheth &amp; maintaineth the hart and life of men.<note place="margin">Luke. 9. Math. 15.</note> When Satan toke vpon him to tempt Ieſus Chriſt, to
<pb facs="tcp:25622:88"/>
declare vnto vs that he was very man, dyd he not choſe bread, to entyre hym to chaunge ſtones in bread?<note place="margin">Math. 6. Luke. 11.</note> When Ieſus Chriſt did celebrate his feaſts, to geue food one time vnto 5000 men, the other time vnto 4000 perſons, did he not ſhew his might vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne of bread? when he taught vs to make our praiers vnto god did he not ordeyne the lords prayer, to beſech god to giue vs our daily bread? And not only in the holy Bible is there mencion made of bread for corporall &amp; common food. But alſo in the ſacrifices celebrated by the prieſts of the Hebrues, there was a law preſcribed of the bread ordeyned of god,<note place="margin">Exod 21. Leuit. 24. Math. 11. 1. Kings. 21. Eſay. 30. Prouer. 20. Ezech. 4. Mala. 1. Pſal. 23. Ezech. 12, Ozec. 7.</note> namely ſwéete bread without leauen. Other bread there was called ſhewbread, which the prieſts did renew euery weeke &amp; eate, which Dauid vſed being preſented vnto him by Ache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>melech y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> high prieſt. Contrariwiſe this terme bread is applied vnto bread of wic<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kednes, vnto bread of lying, vnto bread of ſorowe, vnto vncleane bread of idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, vnto vncleane bread offered at the
<pb facs="tcp:25622:89"/>
aulter,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eu. 8. Math. 4. Luke. 4.</note> vnto the bread of trembling &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to the bread of teares. The Ephraimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes alſo are called the bread of aſhes not turned: that is to ſay in part baked &amp; part not, circumciſed Idolators. Wherefore, O Maſſayers Capharnaites, ye muſte not be ſo hardned &amp; rooted in your fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lynes, that you regard not the phraſes of the holy ſcriptures in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which the terme of bread is ſomtyme taken for the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly &amp; bodily bread,<note place="margin">Math, 15.</note> as when it is ſaid, that man liueth not by bread only but alſo by all that procedeth out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth of god. Sometime alſo bread is taken for the worde of god &amp; for doctrine, when Ieſus Chriſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded his apoſtles to take hede for eatyng of the leauened bread of the Scribes &amp; Phariſies,<note place="margin">Math. 15. Marke. 7.</note> are not theſe termes of bread &amp; leauen taken &amp; inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted for the doctrine of the Phariſies heretikes? When the woman of Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an did demaund grace &amp; mercye for the healthe of her doughter holden wyth a ſoore diſeaſe. Dyd not Ieſus Chriſt an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that it was not lawefull to take
<pb facs="tcp:25622:89"/>
the bread of the children and geue vnto doggs? In this anſwere is not the bread taken for life &amp; health, &amp; not only for the corporall nouriſhment? Seing then that bread is taken for the lyfe of man, the which hangeth chiefly of bread &amp; wyne, and that the goodnes of god willing to applie it ſelfe vnto our infirmities wold chuſe thoſe two ſignes, notes &amp; markes notable, to ſignifie his body &amp; blood, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mely bread &amp; wine, being two ſubſtaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces common to all nations, is that an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation to imagin a carnall tranſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation, as if w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out the ſame god were not able inough to figure &amp; repreſent really &amp; ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tally life to be geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs: yea euerlaſting life by the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the holy bread &amp; wine conſecrated, figures, &amp; ſignes of his body &amp; blood.<note place="margin">Math. 6. Mark. 14. Iohn. 6.</note> Ieſus Chriſt ſpake theſe words, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bread was his body &amp; the wine his blood, he ſaide alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is the liuing bread, that he is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread of life, that he is the liuing bread which came down fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen, he ſaith alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> eateth of this bread ſhall liue foreuer.
<pb facs="tcp:25622:90"/>
Is this to bring in that by this word (is) Ieſus Chriſt is turned &amp; tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted into bread, &amp; is no more chriſt, but an accident w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſubſtaunce? O deteſtable hereſie, O Maſſalians haue ye more rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to interpret carnally theſe words (this is my bodye) to chaunged the bread into his body, than when he affirmeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he is the bread, to chaunge him into bread, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that it is written that the parta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>king of this bred giueth life euerlaſting? Ieſus chriſt ſaid <hi>hoc eſt corpus meum.</hi> He ſaith alſo:<note place="margin">Iohn. 6. Math, 26. iohn. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Hic eſt panis qui de celo deſcendit:</hi> In both theſe places is there not this word (is) beſtowed? Muſte we therefore bring in a witchcraft of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, in place of ſounde inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting of the ſcriptures, by a likenes or familier compariſon of bread with Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus chriſt, cauſing vs to vnderſtand that by him life euerlaſting is geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs? And by him our ſpirituall nouriſhment is giuen vs like as by the bread we haue our bodily foode. How ſo euer it be we muſt always haue recourſe vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true
<pb facs="tcp:25622:90"/>
interpretation of Ieſus Chriſt, the true lawgeuer, &amp; authour of the holy ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, who putting forth his inſtitution ſaid in the firſt place, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was the bread of life, than after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this bread is his fleſh &amp; his body which muſt be geuen for the health of the world. He ſaid that his fleſh is true food, &amp; his blood the true drinke he ſaith, that he that eateth his fleſhe &amp; drinketh his blood ſhall abyde in him. How doth he interpret this eating?<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt doth interpret it himſelfe by theſe words. He that commeth vnto me ſhal neuer hunger, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleueth in me ſhall neuer thruſt. Is not this the true eating &amp; the true drinking, neuer to haue hunger &amp; neuer to haue thruſt? Beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth it to get faith, which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit: behoueth it to addreſſe our ſelues vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to Ieſus Chriſt our heauenly bread, our ſpiritual drink, to fil vs for euer, to quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che euerlaſtingly our thruſt of ſinne, to runne vnto a witchcraft of tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation &amp; to forge an accidence without a ſubſtaunce. Wherefore (O Maſſalians)
<pb facs="tcp:25622:91"/>
haue ye inuented another interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than that of Ieſus Chriſt, who wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſeth that the fleſhe profiteth nothing, but the ſpirite quickeneth? and that his words are not carnall, but ſpirituall, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſpirite &amp; life by fayth &amp; hope that he is the ſauiour of the worlde, incarnate, dead &amp; crucified to geue vs eternall lyfe, &amp; after roſe again, aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth on the right hand of god hys father, abiding an euerlaſting prieſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piciator, mediator &amp; redemer.</p>
               <p>Let vs returne again to this terme (is) which tormenteth the braines of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers ſo ſoore,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn. 15.</note> to imagin a tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation. If Ieſus Chriſt hath ſayde that he is the true vine,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ohn. 14.</note> that god his father is a huſbande man, and we are the bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Is this to bring in this terme (is) a Witchcrafte of chaunging god into a huſbandman, Ieſus Chriſt into a vine, &amp; vs into vinebranches? If Ieſus chriſt is ſaid to be the vnſpotted lambe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> blotteth out the ſins of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worlde: is this to bring in a tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? if Ieſus chriſt hath
<pb facs="tcp:25622:91"/>
ſaide that he is the dore of the ſhepefold, by the which we muſt enter to ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; that he is the ſhepehard &amp; we the ſhepe muſt we therfore ratch theſe places of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcripture ſo far, that neceſſarily we muſt beleue a tranſubſtantiation, for as much as this terme (is) is there? When Ieſus chriſt admoniſhed his diſciples ſai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yng to them that they were the ſalt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth,<note place="margin">Math. 5.</note> did he chaunge &amp; tranſubſtantiate them into pillors of ſalt as he did y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wife of Loth?<note place="margin">Geneſ. 19.</note> If Ieſus chriſt hath ſaid by his apoſtles y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of god wherin y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy goſt doth dwel: is this to imagin y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we are tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiat into a pece of ſtone?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3. 2. Cor. 6.</note> If y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> apoſtle haue ſaid that chriſt is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> rock out of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which did com y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> liuing water to waſh vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our ſinnes:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> is this craftily to deuiſe a changing of Ieſus chriſt into a rocke or materiall ſtone?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> If the apoſtles haue witneſſed that we are the bodye of Chriſt: Is this to brynge in that we are vaniſhed awaye, and are no moore men, but chaunged into an accidence withoute a ſubſtaunce?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:92"/>I foreſée well (o maſſayers) moore than hardened, that you will obiect, that in all theſe places before alledged wherin this word (is) is founde, that no mencion is made of ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, which muſt be depe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidered, for aſmuch as they be holy myſteries ordeyned of god, which alſo is true. And alſo this worde (is) is not only found in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſcriptures before noted,<note place="margin">Geneſ. 17. Exod. 12 13.</note> but alſo when there was ſpeaking of the holy ſacraments ordeyned before of god vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people of Iſrael, was it not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten that circumciſion is the band &amp; coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunt of god?<note place="margin">Geneſ. 17. Num 10. Pſalm. 68.94. Math. 21. iohn. 2.</note> In thother holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of the paſchal lambe, is it not ſayd y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the lambe is the paſſeouer or paſſage? Is this to bring in a witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft of tranſubſtantiation? will ye not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe (o maſſalians &amp; chaungers of ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtances) that in theſe places of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſpeaking of the ſacraments, thys word (is) can not otherwiſe be expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded but to ſignifie: &amp; that circumciſion was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſigne &amp; marke of the bande &amp; couenaunt contracted betwen god &amp; Abraham: and
<pb facs="tcp:25622:92"/>
that the paſchal lambe was alſo the ſign of tholy paſſage: for remembraunce of their deliueraunce fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Egipt. The arck of the couenaunt for another ſacrament whereof it is written, that it is the true power of the lord. Is this to ſaye that it was tranſubſtantiated into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> maieſty of god? It behoueth to interpret the holye ſcripture w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> diſcretion &amp; humilitie, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſophiſtrie &amp; Witchcraft, to vnderſtande ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dly the true meaning of words, &amp; not to abide in the letter y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> killeth: but to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue the word of god in ſpirit that quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keneth. If than the holy arcke be named the lord &amp; called god, for that in it he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed his might, &amp; ſhewed his wonders and myſteries, to draw the people of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, by an outward ſigne to remember god, &amp; to feare &amp; obey him. Alſo if Ieſus chriſt is called the bread that came from heauen, the bread of life, that the bread broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is his body, &amp; the wine is his blood, that the cup is the new teſtament, that by theſe outward ſignes of bread &amp; wine he might cauſe vs to vnderſtand our life
<pb facs="tcp:25622:93"/>
and nouriſhment of ſaluation to ſtai on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ieſus chriſt, &amp; that by his death &amp; bloodſheding we are ſo aſſured of euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting life, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread &amp; wine are nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body, &amp; that it pleaſed him to ordein theſe holy ſignes, to ſerue vs for ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> trial &amp; confirmation of our faith: is this an occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to play y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Caphar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naites or y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Nicodemia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to dout of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of god. How is it poſſible to eate the body &amp; drink y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood of Ieſus chriſt? how is it poſſible to be regenerate &amp; borne a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain? Then ſeing we haue a promiſe ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto vs by the word of god, wherfore (o Maſſalia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) haue ye imagined a carnal tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, miſtruſting the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible power of god? oght it not to ſuffice you to beleue ſimple that the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die &amp; blood of Ieſus chriſt is offered vnto vs really &amp; ſacramentally to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate for our nouriſhment, &amp; to geue vs euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting life by the bread &amp; wine conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with geuing of thanks, the bread be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing truly his body: &amp; the wine his blood, which ought to be receiued worthely by
<pb facs="tcp:25622:93"/>
faith, &amp; in purenes of conſcience, as holy ſignes &amp; marks of the godly badge, with out enquiring euer ſubtilly the meanes otherwiſe then Ieſus Chriſt hath enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted (ſaying) the fleſhe ꝓfiteth nothing it is the ſpirite that quickneth, &amp; that his wordes were ſpirite &amp; life. Ought we to doute, that god hathe not the power to make vs partakers of the body &amp; blood of Ieſus Chriſt, by the holy ſignes of bread &amp; wine conſecrated, the bread neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les remaining bread, &amp; the wine, wine. If it were otherwyſe, thys ſhoulde not be called a ſacrament but a myracle, as when Ieſus Chriſte tourned the water into wine that he vſed a miracle of tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> changing water into wine But he did not then ordain a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,<note place="margin">Iohn. 2.</note> as he did of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion of his body &amp; blood, by the holy figures of bread &amp; wine Was it not as eaſy for god to make the wine to be cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged into blood,<note place="margin">Exod. 4.7.</note> or the bread into fleſh, as for Moiſes &amp; Aaron to cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the water of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> riuer into blood to apꝓue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hardnes of pharoo, or whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> clouds were turned into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh of quals which rained
<pb facs="tcp:25622:94"/>
vpon the people of Iſraell, alwayes god did not ordeyne theſe miracles to ſerue for ordinary ſacraments, but would ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply himſelf to our infirmitie, geuing vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs ſignes holy &amp; not tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtantiated, which are nother vain nor fantaſies, but are outwarde ſignes, which we can ſée, touch, eate, &amp; taſte, abiding in their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, &amp; neuertheles repreſenting ſacra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentally, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is compriſed &amp; ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them, wherein our triall of fayth doth ſtand, to declare vs by a ſacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal worke to be of the number of them y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> are regenerated &amp; nouriſhed by the holy ſacraments of baptiſme &amp; of the ſupper.<note place="margin">A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the two holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</note> If it be lawful to vſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſons of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> .ij. holy ſacraments of baptiſme &amp; of the ſup<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>per, notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is difference betwene regeneration, which doth not reiterate (for it ſufficeth once to be rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate &amp; borne again.) But the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t muſt be often done again according to the order of nature, &amp; other differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces largely diſcribed by the holy apoſtles and miniſters of the worde of god. Yet
<pb facs="tcp:25622:94"/>
the ſame end, the ſame god, the ſame Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt is ſhewed &amp; declared aſwel in baptiſme, as in the ſupper. By the blood of Ieſus chriſt we be regenerat &amp; by the ſame blood nouriſhed. By the blood of Ieſus chriſt we are renewed, ſet, &amp; graf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed, &amp; by the ſame blood we are kept &amp; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hunger &amp; thruſt for euermore By the blood of Ieſus chriſt we are ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led of thold corrupt ſkinne, &amp; cled wyth his body, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſelf ſame alſo we haue our nouriſhment &amp; euerlaſting life. By the blood of Ieſus chriſt we haue acceſſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdom of heauen. And by the ſame blood we haue the fruition of the kingdom, for vnto the ſame purpoſe the holy apoſtle witneſſeth, we are al bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the vertue of one holy ſpirit, &amp; we haue all dronke of one ſpirituall drinke geuen vnto vs by Ieſus Chriſt. Be not theſe compariſons taken out of the holy ſcripture, to iuſtifie that Ieſus Chriſt is the only ende, vnto the whiche tendeth as well Baptiſme as the holy Supper? It foloweth then that the ſygnes of the
<pb facs="tcp:25622:95"/>
ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal water for baptiſme, &amp; bread &amp; wine for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupper of Ieſus chriſt, ar holy ſignes, ernes, gages, paunes, marks, ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les, &amp; ſacraments, inſtituted of god for profe &amp; aſſurance of our faith. Wel then (o Maſſalians) ſeing ye haue inuented a witchcraft of tranſubſtantiation for the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the ſupper:<note place="margin">Againſt the Maſſalians.</note> why haue ye not alſo ſubtelly deuiſed the ſame witchcraft in the ſacrament of baptiſme? why haue ye not ordeyned the ſacramentall water (after that it is by you coniured &amp; bewit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched with ſalt to driue away diuelles) to be changed into the blood of Ieſus chriſt, the water to be no more water but acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence without ſubſtaunce, as ye haue imagined of the bread &amp; wyne? What difference can you ſhew, but ſophiſtries, ſophiſmes, &amp; maſſe ſubtelties. If ye con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue your hereſie by this worde (is) it is alſo founde in the water of Baptiſme, whiche is called renuynge &amp; regenerati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the ſame is alſo named the holy goſt, and the garment w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which, &amp; by whiche we are clothed, renued &amp; borne again in
<pb facs="tcp:25622:95"/>
the blood of Ieſus chriſt. Then ſeyng (o Maſſalians) that you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe that ye can not fynde a ſeconde Berengarie, to make a decre of recantation, to thend to enlarge your witchcraft of tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation vnto the holy water of baptiſme and by the ſame meane to chaunge your ſpittell &amp; ſalte water, your oyle, your creames, your ſalte &amp; other drougges, wherewith you haue corrupted the holy ſacrament of baptiſme. Wherfore then are ye ſo hardened &amp; waxt olde in your Pompilian religion, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> you would pluck Ieſus chriſt from the right hand of god, to make him to diſcende in body &amp; blood by your whiſpering Witchcraft (as Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter Elicius did) before the day apoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of his ſecond comming?<note place="margin">Luke. 1. Malach. 4. A compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the ſunne with Ieſus chriſt, the vvhiche S. Iuſtyne the martyr vſed in his treatiſe of the expoſi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion of fayth. chap. 3.</note> I can bring you in the ſimilitude of the ſunne called by ſome apoſtles the ſunne of rightuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes Ieſus chriſt, becauſe that light com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen by this great &amp; bright ſtar. And euen ſo the ſpiritual light is ge<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen vnto vs by Ieſus chriſt, who hath re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtored vs to light, out of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> night &amp; darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25622:96"/>Well then (o ye Capharnaits carnall &amp; groſſe) vnderſtand nowe a comparriſon ſufficient ynough to ſhowe you the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite power of god to be much more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite then your abhominable inuention of tranſubſtanciation. Doe ye not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (if you haue not your eyes blinded &amp; holden in the depth of the darknes of frowardnes) that the ſun doth geue vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs his light, his beames, his force, his heate and ſtrength. And yet the bodye it ſelf of the ſunne doth reſt &amp; abide in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? Doe not ye ſaye ordinaryly in your common language, when the windowe of the houſe toward the ſunne is open, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſunne commeth into the houſe? Yet the ſun remaineth alwayes in heauen? Behoueth it to ſnatch &amp; katch y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of the ſunne, cauſing it to come downe and be tranſubſtantiate in this earthly place before it can geue his heate, his beames his light, and nouriſhement to plantes, herbes trées &amp; earthly creatures? Are ye ſo brutiſhe (o Capharnaites) that ye will not confeſſe the true ſonne of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
<pb facs="tcp:25622:96"/>
Ieſus chriſt, to haue much more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer then this ſtar of the ſunne create and mortal? If then the mortal creature haue this power to geue vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue, &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of his body, by his beames, by his light, &amp; by his heat ſent down into y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth realy, &amp; effectuouſly y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding abiding in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It behoueth to beleue that god the euerlaſting creator hath muche more power to geue vs the true ſonne of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſnes Ieſus Chriſt to geue vs y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> force and vertue of his body and bloode ſhed for vs, by the beames, light, &amp; heat of his holy ſpirite, without conſtraining him by your witchcraft to be plucked fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the rightha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of god, &amp; to be drawen out of heauen by your tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> into erth. Wherfore hath not Ieſus Chriſt this power to geue vs his light, &amp; to offer to vs his body &amp; his blood, to entre w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in vs, if by faith &amp; pure co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience we wil receyue him by the vertue of his holy ſpirit, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as wel &amp; better than the ſonne entreth into our houſes by his might &amp; power, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out drawing it out of heauen to chaunge the ſubſtance thereof? The ſunne is one only body created, abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in heauen, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cauſe of the growing of
<pb facs="tcp:25622:97"/>
plants, trees, &amp; herbes, which geueth nou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>riſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by force &amp; heat vnto al thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the erth, &amp; in one &amp; the ſame moment hath power to quicken, heat, &amp; nouriſh an infinite number of plants, trées, herbes &amp; earthly creatures, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out ſeperating, diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or plucking his body fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> heauen to tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtantiat it. The body alſo of Ieſus chriſt which he hath caried into heauen &amp; ſet at the right hande of god, hath it not more force, more vertue, &amp; more ſtrength, to regenerate vs, to féede &amp; nouriſh vs, to geue his vertue, his light &amp; his beames, to inſpire, quicken, ſuſtayne, lighten, &amp; in a moment make vs through faith parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of his body &amp; blood: to make vs mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of his members, knit together in him &amp; by him, by his true promiſe contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vnder the bages &amp; holy ſignes, left vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to vs till that the ſecond co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of his hu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manitie be ſeen vpon the earth. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore (o Maſſayers) haue ye inuented this witchcraft of tranſubſtantiation, to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme againſt god, to leſſen his power, &amp; leſſe to eſteeme his power &amp; vertue then the vertue of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſunne his creature? wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore will ye pluck the body of Ieſus chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:25622:97"/>
from heauen before the time appoynted, to change his ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce into your litle rou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d hoſts vnleuened &amp; printed ful of pictures,<note place="margin">Ieſus Chriſt as god ay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth all.</note> which you cauſe to be worſhipped, ſeing that Chriſt as god, doth ayde his churche euerlaſtingly, &amp; hath power to regenerat feed, &amp; nouriſh vs, yea w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> euerlaſting life &amp; food, by his promiſe witneſſed &amp; aſſured by his holy ſacraments of Baptiſme, &amp; of his holy ſupper. For other compariſons (o Maſſayers) familier &amp; homely, conſider how the earthly &amp; mortall princes are eſte<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med reuerenced, &amp; honored for the ſacred ſignes ordeyned by them. I wyll only ſet forth vnto you two, that is to ſay waxe &amp; metalles: of thone is made the ſeale of the prince wherwith is ſealed the graces, par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dons, &amp; forgeueneſſes, the letters &amp; priui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leges graunted by the prince. He that cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terfeiteth this ſeale is he not puniſhed for treaſon, euen as if he he had hurt the very perſon of the prince. Doth not this ſeale repreſent y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very perſon of the prince as if he himſelf were there preſent? yet y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> waxe notw<hi rend="sup">t</hi>ſtanding y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is called y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeale of the prince) is not therfore tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſubſtantiat, but remaineth ſtil waxe, yet after that it hath
<pb facs="tcp:25622:98"/>
receyued y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reuerend print of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prince it is no more called waxe, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> princes ſeale. The metalls of golde &amp; ſiluer marked for the coyne of the prince to ſerue for money, although they be called no more gold, nor ſiluer, but haue changed their names at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> wil of the prince, be it into the name of du<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cate, crown, ſhillings, pence, or other na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes, do thei leaue to be metals &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame ſubſtance thei wer before? this only diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence there is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thei are apointed, &amp; ſtam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the print of the prince, whiche doth really repreſent him, in ſuch ſort, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he that clippeth or cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>terfeiteth this monie, is pu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niſhed as for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> crime of treaſon, and as he had hurt the ꝓper perſon of the prince.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.</note> By much better reaſon the bread &amp; wine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated &amp; marked to be ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy &amp; blood of Ieſus chriſt, do really repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent him, &amp; not in painting. Wherfore he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> vſeth it vnworthely ſhall haue euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting damnation, as a traitour to the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie of god. If ye (o Maſſalians, Nicolai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, &amp; tranſubſtantiators) are not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently ſatified w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thinterpretation of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus chriſt &amp; of his apoſtles, ne yet with ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militudes &amp; familier co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pariſons, to bring
<pb facs="tcp:25622:98"/>
you to the true way, &amp; certain forme ordei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned of god, for the celebration of his holy ſacraments, in aboliſhing your Maſſe and Pompilian idolatries, caſting away alſo your abhominable witchcraft of tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, at the leſt, yet wil ye geue no credit vnto the interpretation of thaunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent doctours of the church? Heare than y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which S. Auguſtin doth recite againſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damantin,<note place="margin">Auguſt. ca. 12. authorities of the auncient doctours. The expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſainct Auguſtine.</note> euen as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> blood in many places of the holy ſcriptures is called the water &amp; the rock chriſt. So is the bread called the body of Ieſus chriſt, the which thre places muſt be expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to be figures &amp; ſignes. When that (ſaith the ſame doctor) Ieſus chriſt ſpake theſe words, <hi>hoc eſt corpus meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">lib. de doctri. chriſti. &amp; in prefati. Pſal. 3</note> this is my body, &amp; gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bred. He gaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſigne of his body, for he thought o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it was a thing vnlawfull, &amp; to vncourteous, to deuour the fleſh &amp; body of Ieſus chriſt,<note place="margin">lib. 10. de can. des. cap. 5. ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificium de conſecr. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct. 2.</note> if there wer not a figure ther namely, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bread to put vs in minde of the fleſhe &amp; body of Ieſus chriſt to haue bene offered vp, for our life, &amp; euerlaſting food. Moreouer the ſame doctor vſeth this inter<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the viſible ſacrament, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is to ſai the holy ſigne of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> inuiſible
<pb facs="tcp:25622:99"/>
ſacrifice. The like interpretations are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by Tertullian againſt Marcio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the heritick:<note place="margin">Tertul. lib. 1. &amp; 3.4.</note> wherfore then (o maſſalia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s) haue not you folowed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> autoritie of the holy do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctors of the church, which wold not blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme againſt god by a witchcraft of tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtanciatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?<note place="margin">Vt quid paras dentem &amp; ve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>trem, crede &amp; ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducaſti. ca. Vt quid de co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecratione diſtinct. 2. Auguſt. in li. de remedi. poeniten. &amp; in ioh. tract. 25. cap. 6. S. Hierom in epiſt. ad Eph.</note> but haue frely acknowled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to be a ſigne or holy viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble figure, ſignifiyng in ſpirite &amp; by faith, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is inuiſible? wherfore prepare ye y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> mouth &amp; the belly to deuour the fleſhe of chriſt corporally? why do ye not offer your ſoules by liuely faith worthely to eat Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus chriſt? why did you not interpret y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Ieſus chriſt by the nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the holy doctor Ierom, ſay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the fleſh of Ieſus chriſt is vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>did fleſhly whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there is me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tion made of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the bloud &amp; crucifiing of the body of Ieſus chriſt for our ſaluation.<note place="margin">Ca. dupliciter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſtinct.</note> But ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually when it is ſaid, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the fleſhe is the true meat which muſt be eaten. For ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy doctor I wil alledge Gelaſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome,<note place="margin">Sainct Gelaſe againſt Euty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chius &amp; Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorius.</note> who diſputing againſt the heritiks Eutichians &amp; Neſtoriens, doth affirme y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the bread &amp; wine conſecrated &amp; made ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, do not leaue in ſubſtance
<pb facs="tcp:25622:99"/>
ſtill to bread &amp; wine, but are figures &amp; ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body &amp; blod of Ieſus chriſt, by the miſterie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.<note place="margin">S. Ambroſe in his booke of ſacraments. chap. 11.</note> Wil ye haue more large witneſſes of ſ. Ambroſe who vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> epiſtle to the Corinthia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hath expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded eating &amp; drinking the bread &amp; the wine, to ſignifie, the fleſh &amp; the blod of Ieſus chriſt offered for vs?<note place="margin">Origin in Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ui. homil. 7.</note> Origin alſo in his homilies hath expou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to be figures, which muſt be examined ſpiritually &amp; not carnally: for this (ſaith he) y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the letter kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, if it be not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſpiritually,<note place="margin">S. Chriſoſtom in homil. 31. ca. 15. com. 1. Pſalm. 22.</note> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to eat the fleſh of chriſt. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore S. Chriſoſtom warneth to honor this ſacrament, in offring the ſoule vnto god, for which chriſt was crucified, and that by this holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of bread &amp; wine, is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified vnto vs the likenes of the body &amp; blood of Ieſus chriſt. To make an end, it behoueth to be ruled by the holy interpre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tation of our doctor Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; of his apoſtles, to honor &amp; reuerence his holy ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ordened of him for outward ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, to lift vp our minds to heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to take y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is repreſented by the ſame ſignes not to eſteme the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as vain paintings or fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies, but worthely to receiue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in liue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:25622:100"/>
faith by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vertue of the holy goſt, to the end to be fed &amp; nouriſhed w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly bred, in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> helth of our ſoules, to com to life euer laſting. Let vs then be aſſured in Ieſus Chriſt as membres of his body:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> Let vs all come into vnitie to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate one only bread, &amp; to drinke one only wyne, made of many graines knit together, to the end y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we may ſay w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the holy apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 12.</note> all we the faithful are y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body of Ieſus chriſt, ſaued &amp; redemed by his body crucified, &amp; blod ſhed for vs. Thus dwelling &amp; abiding by faith in Ieſus chriſt, eating him, &amp; drinking his blood. Let vs beleue ſurely y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, dead, &amp; riſen again, &amp; his body aſcen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded into heauen,<note place="margin">D. Auguſt. in ioan. tract. 30. Act. 1.3.</note> ſitting at the right hand of god in a certen place, vntil y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he returne w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his humanitie, as he went vp. Neuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theles his power &amp; diuinitie are diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto vs, &amp; ſpred ouer all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, in all places, ſpecially in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che he hath lefte vnto vs for gages, &amp; out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde triall of our faythe, for a remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braunce of the deathe and paſſion of our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25622:100"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
